<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www-test.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 02:02:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>International Day of Women and Girls in Science</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/international-day-of-women-and-girls-in-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Andrews]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 23:46:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45949</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[February 11th 2024 is the United Nations International Day of Women and Girls in Science. It is an opportunity to celebrate the achievements of women and girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), whilst acknowledging the persistent gaps in representation and equality in these fields.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p id="block-ba076711-c44c-4edc-8dcc-1f8122d81987">February 11th 2024 is the <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/women-and-girls-in-science-day">United Nations International Day of Women and Girls in Science</a>. It is an opportunity to celebrate the achievements of women and girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), whilst acknowledging the persistent gaps in representation and equality in these fields.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="680" src="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider-1024x680.jpeg" alt="green bird" class="wp-image-45952" style="width:568px;height:auto" srcset="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider-1024x680.jpeg 1024w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider-300x199.jpeg 300w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider-768x510.jpeg 768w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider-1536x1020.jpeg 1536w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider-1920x1275.jpeg 1920w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/princess-parrot-cc-by-nc-mschneider.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Call for applications – GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-friday/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 Jul 2023 21:51:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45737</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The 2024 programme will provide two €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD $8,200) recognising the work of two early-career researchers. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through the&#160;Global Biodiversity Information Facility&#160;(GBIF). The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1024x320.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49207"/></figure>



<p>The 2024 programme will provide two €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD $8,200) recognising the work of two early-career researchers. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a>&nbsp;(GBIF). The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA are also accessible via GBIF.</p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p><strong><em><mark>Australian applications to the ALA are due by 31st May 2024.</mark></em></strong></p>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;if you require further information.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat.</p>



<p>Note: Awardees are expected to acknowledge GBIF support when disseminating research results via peer-reviewed publications, presentations at professional meetings, and other media.</p>



<p><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></p>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol start="1">
<li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)</li>



<li><strong>Project description</strong>&nbsp;(<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em> <em>font</em>) that describes:<br>a. How the research advances biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity.<br>b.&nbsp;<strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.</li>



<li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.</li>



<li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate program of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li>
</ol>



<p><strong>How to submit an application to the ALA (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol start="1">
<li>Visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/0YedTUAf3Nk14JKZqBn0a/call-opens-for-nominations-to-2024-gbif-graduate-researchers-award#_national-deadlines-for-2024">GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award</a>&nbsp;page&nbsp;and follow the instructions.&nbsp;<br></li>



<li>Submit your nominations to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;with ‘2024 GBIF Graduate Researchers Application _YOUR NAME’ in the subject line by&nbsp;<strong>31st May 2024.</strong></li>
</ol>



<p>The criteria for the awards include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Originality and innovation</li>



<li>Use of and strategic significance for data accessed through GBIF</li>



<li>Measurable effectiveness and impact in advancing biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/0YedTUAf3Nk14JKZqBn0a/call-opens-for-nominations-to-2024-gbif-graduate-researchers-award#_national-deadlines-for-2024">GBIF</a>&nbsp;website.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blog/">&nbsp;Back to Articles</a></p>





<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protecting Australian biodiversity with data</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-tuesday-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sushant.ghimire@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 06:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Meet our ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species. While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Meet our ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners</strong></p>



<p>As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species.</p>



<p>While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used to address specific research goals, these data often require additional resources to ensure they can be digitised and made available nationally as open data.</p>



<p>To improve data accessibility the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) launched the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a> in 2022. This program is designed to support Australian museums, biological collections, herbaria, and research teams to digitise their data, and making it available through the ALA, and internationally through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1024x577.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49179"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program banner.</figcaption></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-left">Through a nationally competitive application process, projects were awarded grants to digitise their priority biodiversity data. The output from this program will enable data on rare and unique species to become open and accessible through the ALA. Using FAIR principles (findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable), this data will support research, decision-making and conservation efforts to better protect Australian biodiversity.</p>



<p><strong>Funded projects:</strong></p>



<p><strong>2022 projects</strong>:</p>



<ul>
<li>New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, NSW – mobilising plant pest and disease data from the NSW Biosecurity Collections (~600,000 records).</li>



<li>South Australia Museum (SAM), SA– mobilise the SAM’s Australian Biological Tissues Collection of 39 donated frozen tissue collections of Australian freshwater fishes (around 90% of all known species and ~46,000 records).</li>



<li>Queensland Museum Network, QLD – mobilising and enhancing data from the Cribb Australian Fish Trematode Collection (&gt;20,000 records of &gt;1,000 fish species).</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery, TAS – mobilising wildlife molecular and tissue data (&gt; 8,500 sample vials and 1,650 formalin-fixed specimens in the histology collection).</li>



<li>Edith Cowan University, WA – mobilising plant and fungi data from the Robert Brown Herbarium.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and Parks Authority, WA – mobilising data in the Kings Park and Botanic Garden Herbarium collection (18,200 specimens).</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>2023 projects:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>National Herbarium of Victoria, Royal Botanic Gardens of Victoria – mobilising more than 5,000 specimen-based occurrence data records from Australian macroalgae.</li>



<li>Western Australian Museum – mobilising thousands of native bee data records from physical specimens collected southwestern WA, representing more than 200 bee species.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and State Herbarium, South Australia – making &gt;30,000 bryophyte and &gt;6,000 lichen records available to the ALA through digitisation of physical collection labels.</li>



<li>D’Estrees Entomology and Science Services – delivery of 7,000 -10,000 insect occurrence records from Kangaroo Island, focused on underrepresented taxa.</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery – mobilising more than 15,000 invertebrate species records representing Tasmanian spiders, echinoderms, cnidarians and annelids.</li>
</ul>



<p>Congratulations to the successful projects, we look forward to working with them to make their data available nationally. We’d like to also acknowledge the applications that were not successful as they were universally excellent making our assessment process very challenging. We are also grateful to the independent review panel for their work in reviewing proposals and selecting a fantastic suite of final recipients.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47969"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Leanne Wheaton working on collections specimens at South Australia Museum, Photo Credit Denis Smith, South Australia Museum. </figcaption></figure>



<p>The 2024 grant round for the Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program will open for applications in&nbsp;<strong>late autumn 2024</strong>. Keep an eye on the ALA website, social media channels and blogs for more information shortly.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Transforming Australia’s biological collections to open data</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-tuesday/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sushant.ghimire@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Aug 2022 06:37:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45640</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The&#160;Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) first webinar of 2024 showcased a selection of amazing projects from the&#160;Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program. This important initiative supports the mobilisation of Australia’s biodiversity data which may not yet be digital, making it available through the ALA, and internationally to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility. By improving digital access, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) first webinar of 2024 showcased a selection of amazing projects from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>. This important initiative supports the mobilisation of Australia’s biodiversity data which may not yet be digital, making it available through the ALA, and internationally to the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a>. By improving digital access, the program delivers stronger research and conservation outcomes for Australia’s unique biodiversity.</p>



<p>Hear from three projects that were supported through the program. Learn about the transformative power of biodiversity data, and how previously inaccessible physical specimens in biological collections can be made available as open data.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by CSIRO.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar Transforming Australia’s biological collections to open data" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G7GIp7LTryk?start=111&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Weblink to recording: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7GIp7LTryk&amp;t=111s" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7GIp7LTryk&amp;t=111s</a>. The event was hosted on 20 Feb 2024 at 11AM AEDT. It was attended by more than 400 live viewers on the day. </figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p><strong>Dr David Hocking</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/DavidHocking-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6ED9FEC654AB56C83666A26317AF962652BBB6F2" alt="Dr David Hocking"/></figure>



<p>Dr David Hocking is the Senior Curator of Vertebrate Zoology at the Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery (TMAG). TMAG houses the Tasmanian Devil Tissue Bioarchive and also curates a growing collection of frozen tissue specimens for a wide range of vertebrate wildlife. The 2023 Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program allowed TMAG to digitise a remaining bulk collection of devil tissues and establish a new TMAG Tissue Collection on the ALA providing a public portal into this growing resource of specimens for future research and analysis.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Mieke Strong</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/MiekeStrong-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6C8427B3B9EB5A9979FE4527484D02147E28644D" alt="Dr Mieke Strong"/></figure>



<p>Mieke has over 15 years working and studying biological sciences and has a PhD in the taxonomy of fish parasites from the University of Queensland and the Queensland Museum. She has worked as a technical officer at the Department of Fisheries in Western Australia, as a researcher at the Western Australian Museum (terrestrial invertebrates), and as an environmental consultant at Biota Environmental Sciences. As part of her current role at Gaia Resources, Mieke interest is in determining data formatting and data requirements for natural sciences and collections projects, focusing on data standards.</p>



<p><strong>Dean Beasley</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/DeanBeasley-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=AAB8F0C1D16AA865B158CF43E4385C520DF0689E" alt="Dean Beasley"/></figure>



<p>Dean Beasley joined Queensland Museum in 2019, and administer the Vernon Collection Management System used to catalogue Biodiversity &amp; Geosciences specimens as well as Cultures &amp; Histories objects held by the museum. The Vernon database holds over 1.1 million records. Its functionality includes, but is not limited to, processes that assist with accessioning specimens and objects, managing incoming and outgoing loans, acquisition proposals, tracking specimen and object locations, valuations, managing exhibitions, storing associated images and documentation. Prior to QM, Dean worked for the Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries (DAF) within the Plant Pathology Herbarium (2000) and Insect Collection (2008), where he administered the KE EMu database, and developed Lucid keys to plant pathogens.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Kit Prendergast</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/KitPrendergast-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FEF01E130CBAACECB8E5D599B69A0AF9759E27FB" alt="Dr Kit Prendergast"/></figure>



<p>Dr Kit Prendergast is a native bee researcher. She has conducted native bee biodiversity surveys across the Swan Coastal Plain and Jarrah forest of southwest of Western Australia, the wheatbelt, Gascoyne and Goldfields of WA, and Traditional landowner lands in northern Western Australia for her PhD, surveys for local and state government, land care groups, and communities. She has amassed an incredible collection of native bee specimens, which includes new range records, species not collected for decades, and many undescribed species. Thanks to the ALA Data Mobilisation Program, these specimens are finally making their way onto the map and being catalogued at the WA Museum, representing a rich dataset for researchers now and in the future.</p>



<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>This is one bird to be cass-o-wary of!</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-monday/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2022 07:13:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45636</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Err&#8230; is that a bird or a dinosaur? Well, both (kind of)! We’re talking about the Southern Cassowary (Casuarius casuarius), often described as one of the closest living relatives of dinosaurs. These gigantic flightless birds (‘ratites’) occupy tropical areas of northern Australia and Papua New Guinea. Cassowaries are the second heaviest birds in the world [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Err&#8230; is that a bird or a dinosaur?</p>



<p>Well, both (kind of)! We’re talking about the <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/5fc1b9fe-ccdd-4c3a-adfc-6f6e5c5c396b">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em></a>), often described as one of the closest living relatives of dinosaurs.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-Tom-Hunt-CC-BY-NC-819x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48810" style="width:1000px;height:1024px"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em>) adult. Photo Credit Tom Hunt CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>These gigantic flightless birds (‘ratites’) occupy tropical areas of northern Australia and Papua New Guinea. Cassowaries are the second heaviest birds in the world (after ostriches), with females reaching a maximum weight of 55kgs and males up to 76kgs! They lay bright green eggs, with dads stepping up to be in charge of incubation and chick rearing. Once the eggs hatch, baby cassowaries can walk almost immediately with their strong back legs. Babies are not born with their signature black plumage, instead have banded yellow and brown striped patterning as chicks. </p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-DHFischer-CC-BY-NC.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48811"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em>) chick. Photo Credit DHFischer CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Keep your distance</strong></p>



<p>You&#8217;ll often hear these big birds before you see them! Cassowaries are notorious for communicating through deep rumbles, hisses and grunting sounds. Cassowaries use various vocalisations to communicate through their dense rainforest habitats. If you hear a cassowary calling, make sure you keep your distance. Equipped with a razor-sharp beak, talons and a particularly territorial nature, cassowaries are more than capable of tearing through flesh if they feel threatened. </p>



<p><strong>Keystone species</strong></p>



<p>Cassowaries are ‘keystone species’ &#8211; species which has a disproportionately important role in their natural ecosystems. In rainforest habitats across northern QLD, cassowaries play a critical role in dispersing many native seeds through fragmented rainforest landscapes. Due to their large size, cassowaries can swallow fruits and other plants whole, digest the pulp and excrete seeds intact in dung piles (aka natural fertilisers). This ability to disperse large seeds helps to maintain healthy ecosystems by promoting vegetation regeneration.</p>



<p>To better illustrate how cassowaries support native plant dispersal across rainforest ecosystems, Callum and Shandiya from the ALA Science and Decision Support team have created an interactive map. The map shows 15 native plant species across the QLD wet tropics against cassowary records in the ALA!</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://cjwaite23.shinyapps.io/cassowary_app/" data-type="link" data-id="https://cjwaite23.shinyapps.io/cassowary_app/">Check out the interactive map!</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://cjwaite23.shinyapps.io/cassowary_app/"><img decoding="async" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-1024x534.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48855"/></a></figure>



<p>To learn more about native seeds in tropical areas, check out the <a href="https://www.ath.org.au/">Australian Topical Herbarium</a>.</p>



<p>#WorldCassowaryDay</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Test Blog 5</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-5/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sushant.ghimire@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Aug 2022 02:19:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45634</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Empty test blog]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Empty test blog</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Test blog 4. please ignore.</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-4-please-ignore/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sushant.ghimire@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 01:46:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45632</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Test blog 4. please ignore.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Test blog 4. please ignore. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Test Blog 3</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-3/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sushant.ghimire@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2022 01:13:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45630</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This is a test blog]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This is a test blog</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Test Blog post</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/test-blog-post/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[sushant.ghimire@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2022 23:58:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45626</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Test post please ignore.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Test post please ignore. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Tiws-day arrives again</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/tiws-day-arrives-again/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Andrews]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:41:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=45394</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In breaking news, we have heard that the rumours of the imminent arrival of Tiws-day (known by the younger generation as Tuesday) have proven correct. Take cover!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In breaking news, we have heard that the rumours of the imminent arrival of Tiws-day (known by the younger generation as Tuesday) have proven correct. Take cover!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
