<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 05:56:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>New biodiversity data set to benefit all</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-biodiversity-data-set-to-benefit-all/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lucinda Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 04:49:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50141</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia's (ALA) Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program (ABDMP) offers grants to support people and institutions in making their biodiversity data more accessible. Read about our 2024 grant recipients.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) <a href="https://ala.org.au/abdmp/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program (ABDMP)</a> offers grants to support people and institutions in making their biodiversity data more accessible. &nbsp;</p>



<p>You may have read about the ABDMP projects <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-ala-data-mobilisation-projects/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">we announced in July 2024</a> which improved the accessibility of previously untapped biosecurity data. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Well, now we can announce five new projects which have received an ABDMP grant to enable the provision of new biodiversity data into the ALA. </p>



<p>The recipients are:&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ol start="1" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Australian Wildlife Conservancy (AWC):</strong> The largest private land conservation organisation in Australia holding data from remote regions across the continent that are historically under-surveyed, such as the Kimberley, Cape York and the arid zone. AWC surveys have focused on threatened species and restricted-range endemics. It’s estimated AWC will provide more than 260,000 records to the ALA including records from areas that have less published data and from longitudinal surveying.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<ol start="2" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Museums Victoria: </strong>This grant will support the digitisation of a significant Click Beetle (Elateridae) collection for approximately 800 species within Australia. At approximately 15,000 records, this project will add data for an additional 99 species to the ALA and increase in species-level occurrence records by 180%, increase the number of species by 36%, and increase the number of genera by 38%. </li>
</ol>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1024x683.jpg" alt="Woman looking at computer with beetle on screen. " class="wp-image-50142" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1920x1280.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Photo: Joseph Byford Photography</figcaption></figure>



<ol start="3" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Royal Botanical Gardens Victoria: </strong>This grant supports the mobilisation of specimen-based occurrence data from Australian macrofungi specimens collected by renowned mycologist and fungi photographer Bruce Fuhrer OAM (1930–2023). The project will see the transcription and digitisation of data associated with approximately 1800 specimens and a selection of field images taken by Mr Fuhrer.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<ol start="4" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>University of Melbourne: </strong>This project will facilitate the mobilisation of data for non-vascular bryophyte (phylum Bryophyta) and liverwort (phylum Marchantiophyta) specimens, collected by bryologist Dr David Meagher, into the Atlas of Living Australia. Dr Meagher has been described as ‘Australia’s most competent bryologist’. He authored 60 publications, many describing or revising bryophyte and liverwort taxa during his 20+ year research career. In digitising Meagher’s specimens, this project will contribute data for specimens collected from throughout Australia within the last 20 years, documenting contemporary taxon distributions and habitat occupancy for non-vascular taxa that are under-represented in the ALA.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<ol start="5" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>West Australian Museum: </strong>Dr Barbara York Main (1929–2019) was Australia’s ‘spider-lady’ with an international reputation as a spider researcher and author of books describing the Western Australian environment. Dr Main’s collection is comprised primarily of thousands of trapdoor spiders that she collected over a 60+ year period and is considered the most significant historical collection of this iconic group of spiders in Australia. It also includes Barbara’s field notebooks that describe critical data on burrow structure, and soil and vegetation associations. The collection is estimated to contain 3,500–4,000 specimens and will support a greater understanding of these species in the future.  </li>
</ol>



<p>We congratulate the successful projects and grant recipients for 2024 and thank our review panel for their time and expertise in evaluating many high-calibre applications this year. &nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Generous interfaces for discovering complex biodiversity data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-generous-interfaces-for-discovering-complex-biodiversity-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 01:08:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50118</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How can we ensure our data can be easily and generously accessed? In this webinar, Generous interfaces for discovering biodiversity data, the ALA&#8217;s Dr Martin Westgate and the ANU&#8217;s Prof Mitchell Whitelaw and Prof Adrian Mackenzie delve into their recent work with the ALA on finding more generous ways to explore biodiversity data. We explore [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>How can we ensure our data can be easily and generously accessed? In this webinar, Generous interfaces for discovering biodiversity data, the ALA&#8217;s Dr Martin Westgate and the ANU&#8217;s Prof Mitchell Whitelaw and Prof Adrian Mackenzie delve into their recent work with the ALA on finding more generous ways to explore biodiversity data.</p>



<p>We explore how the development of novel interfaces is transforming the way biodiversity data is presented, making it more inviting and accessible for a diverse range of users.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar: Generous interfaces for discovering complex biodiversity data" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/25yFLAT89E0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The event was hosted on 12 November 2024 at 12PM AEDT.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p>The ALA was grateful to be joined by the following speakers for this webinar: </p>



<p><a href="https://mtchl.net/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prof Mitchell Whitelaw</a> and <a href="https://researchportalplus.anu.edu.au/en/persons/adrian-mackenzie" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prof Adrian Mackenzie</a> from the <a href="https://www.anu.edu.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Australian National University</a> (ANU)</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure></div>


<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[geoff.egan@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 03:27:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50098</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out ALA&#8217;s November 2024 newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Check out <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/nov-2024-newsletter">ALA&#8217;s November 2024 newsletter</a>. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image is-resized is-style-default"><a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/nov-2024-newsletter"><img decoding="async" width="1272" height="1160" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2.png" alt="ALA's November 2024 newsletter header banner - it includes the ALA logo and a dried wattle specimen, and a welcome message" class="wp-image-50104" style="width:1450px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2.png 1272w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2-300x274.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2-1024x934.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2-768x700.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1272px) 100vw, 1272px" /></a></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; November 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/newsletter/directors-update-november-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[geoff.egan@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 05:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[directors update]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GBIF]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50093</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the November 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter. I recently had the pleasure of representing Australia at the 31st meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facilities (GBIF) Governing Boarding hosted in Vairao, Vila do Conde Portugal. The event brings together close to 100 international partners that contribute to the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="719" height="938" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48109" style="width:251px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger-230x300.png 230w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 719px) 100vw, 719px" /></figure></div>


<p>Welcome to the November 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>I recently had the pleasure of representing Australia at the 31st meeting of the <a href="https://gb31.gbif.org/" data-type="link" data-id="https://gb31.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facilities (GBIF) Governing Boarding</a> hosted in Vairao, Vila do Conde Portugal. The event brings together close to 100 international partners that contribute to the network both strategically, and through the provision of biodiversity data and related services. For the ALA this event is critical as it allows us to benchmark our strategic priorities, contextualise our annual workplan against partner priorities, and ultimately engage with our partners to realise technical efficiencies. For example, the planned implementation of GBIF’s unified data model can directly support ALA’s efforts to improve the interoperability of more complex biodiversity data emerging from our partners, including from <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-exploring-next-gen-biodiversity-detection-technologies/">eDNA, camera trap, and ecoacoustic-based monitoring</a>.</p>



<p>Some of the key themes to emerge from the 2024 Governing Board meeting included the establishment of Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) Regional Centres and the potential role of biodiversity data infrastructure, improving our collective approach to Indigenous data governance, expansion of the Data4Nature program potentially into Asia and the Pacific, embedding Environment, Sustainability, and Governance (ESG) principles into the operation of research infrastructure, and importantly the critical role of research infrastructure in supporting international biodiversity policy programs, given the meeting preceded the COP16 meeting in Colombia by a few weeks. <a href="https://www.gbif.org/event/4PLhy0XlJHGFLvH6rb4KmM/cop-16-sixteenth-meeting-of-the-parties-to-the-convention-of-biological-diversity">GBIF had a strong presence at COP16</a>, highlighting the fundamental role data can play in not only supporting policy formulation, but also informing priorities.</p>



<p>As GBIF’s largest national node, ALA continues to play an important global leadership role that is valued across the network. There are opportunities to strengthen this by more actively partnering with GBIF around aligned technical projects and improving our engagement with the international biodiversity data infrastructure community. Elements of this have already commenced, with the ALA recently taking on the leadership role for two years for the Oceania Regional Node, and jointly hosting a <a href="https://www.gbif.org/event/jxlmvxokGDXhOpN1fNpwn/oceania-regional-nodes-meeting-or-engagement-meeting-for-bid-pacific">regional node meeting with New Zealand in October</a>.</p>



<p>It was a great meeting, with an engaged network of member nations working to a common goal to make biodiversity data more interoperable and accessible.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy reading our November 2024 Newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>An iNaturalist Australia milestone</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/an-inaturalist-australia-milestone/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[geoff.egan@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 14 Oct 2024 23:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50020</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[After launching internationally in 2008, iNaturalist has blossomed into one of the most popular citizen science platforms in the world with more than 214 million observations across approximately 491,000 species, contributed by almost 3.4 million users (as of October 2024). While these are incredible collective results, it&#8217;s safe to say our local iNaturalist Australia node [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>After launching internationally in 2008, iNaturalist has blossomed into one of the most popular citizen science platforms in the world with more than 214 million observations across approximately 491,000 species, contributed by almost 3.4 million users (<a>as of October 2024). </a></p>



<p>While these are incredible collective results, it&#8217;s safe to say our local iNaturalist Australia node is a heavyweight on the global stage and, as a major contributor to Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) records, we&#8217;re celebrating a big milestone this month with iNaturalist Australia&#8217;s fifth birthday!</p>



<p><strong>iNaturalist Australia beginnings</strong></p>



<p>Although Australian observations on iNaturalist date <a>all the way back to </a><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/245">2008</a>, things were slow going for the first eight years. Records started to accumulate faster in late-2016 after the creation of the <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/projects/australasian-fishes"><em>Australasian Fishes</em> project</a>, but it wasn’t until late-2019 that things really took off. This kickstart to the exponential rise of observations for Australia was no coincidence: it marked the official launch of iNaturalist Australia as a node of the iNaturalist Network, with the local node run by the ALA.</p>



<p>To celebrate this five-year anniversary, we’ve summarised just some of what the iNaturalist community in Australia has achieved.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-style-default"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="724" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/iNat-usage-1024x724.jpg" alt="Graph showing total Australian iNaturalist observations over time, rising from under 1 million before 2020 to over 8 million by mid 2023." class="wp-image-50032" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/iNat-usage-1024x724.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/iNat-usage-300x212.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/iNat-usage-768x543.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/iNat-usage.jpg 1379w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Total Australian iNaturalist observations over time. Since June, this figure has now surpassed 9 million records!</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<p><strong>Some quick statistics</strong></p>



<p>Australia is one of the most significant contributors to iNaturalist globally, punching well above our weight relative to our population. We rank third in the world for the number of observations, second for the number of species (behind only the United States), and first in the southern hemisphere across all key metrics. As of <a>October 2024</a>, there are <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations?place_id=6744,7333,7616,10287,10293,118147">more than 9 million Australian observations on the platform</a> across approximately 60,000 species, contributed by 100,000 users. Importantly, more than 34,000 users have contributed identifications to Australian iNaturalist observations.</p>



<p>The most observed Australian species is the <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations?place_id=6744,7333,7616,10287,10293,118147&amp;taxon_id=8575">Australian Magpie, with almost 35,000 observations</a>, followed by the Laughing Kookaburra, Koala, Superb Fairywren and Rainbow Lorikeet. The most observed major group, however, is <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations?place_id=6744,7333,7616,10287,10293,118147&amp;iconic_taxa=Plantae">plants with 2.85 million observations</a>, followed closely by <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations?place_id=6744,7333,7616,10287,10293,118147&amp;iconic_taxa=Insecta">insects with 2.51 million observations</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="845" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/inat-selection-845x1024.jpg" alt="A gallery of iNaturalist photos" class="wp-image-50036" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/inat-selection-845x1024.jpg 845w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/inat-selection-248x300.jpg 248w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/inat-selection-768x931.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/inat-selection-1268x1536.jpg 1268w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/inat-selection.jpg 1322w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 845px) 100vw, 845px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Selection of the most popular Australian iNaturalist observations (as voted by the online iNaturalist community). From top to bottom, left to right:</em><br><em>1. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/84263774">Ampurta (Dasycercus hillieri)</a>, a carnivorous marsupial found across central Australia. Photograph by Yingyod Lapwong (@charliev), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>2. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/2383945">Thorny Devil (Moloch horridus)</a>, one of Australia’s most famous reptiles. Photograph by John Sullivan (@sullivanribbit), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>3. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/112244234">Jelly Ear (Auricularia auricula-judae)</a>, a very appropriately named fungus! Photograph by Charmaine Thomas (@charmainet), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>4. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/8913526">Megamouth Shark (Megachasma pelagios)</a>, a rare deepwater shark species. This was an invaluable historical record of a beach-cast specimen from 1988! Photograph by Glenn Moore (@gmoo), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>5. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/63946322">Miteception: Rainbowia sp. mite with parasitic larval erythraeid mites</a>. Photograph by Andrew Allen (@andrew_allen), CC BY.</em><br><em>6. </em><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/199173851">Dofleinia armata</a><em>, an alien-like sea anemone. Photography by @thero-pod, CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>7. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/196793204">Brown Skua (Stercorarius antarcticus)</a> taking a break on Macquarie Island. Photograph by Kate E. Sutherland (@pterodroma), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>8. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/63300674">Donut Nembrotha (Nembrotha rosannulata)</a>, one of the more colourful nudibranchs getting around. Photograph by Chris Ross (@chrisross), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>9. </em><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/147015177">Inimia nat</a><em>, a newly described genus and species of preying mantis discovered through iNaturalist. Photograph by Glenda Walter (@glendawalter), CC BY-NC.</em><br><em>10. <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/observations/182438959">Eastern Queen of Sheba (Thelymitra speciosa)</a>, an iconic Western Australian orchid. Photograph by Michael Keogh (@bushbandit), CC BY-NC-SA.</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Why was the ALA-iNaturalist Australia partnership so important?</strong></p>



<p>By hosting iNaturalist Australia, the ALA sparked greater recruitment of two key demographics. First, more observers joined the platform, accelerating the accumulation of records. It took six years for Australia to reach 10,000 total iNaturalist records from 2008─2014 but now more than 10,000 new Australian records are uploaded to the platform <strong>every single day</strong>, and the number of observations uploaded to the site continues to grow exponentially. <strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Second, the ALA’s support of iNaturalist prompted many more experts to join the platform and contribute their expertise and knowledge, which has been <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.3001843">crucial for improving data quality</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="992" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-1024x992.png" alt="Diagram showing a cycle: citizen scientists make better identifications and become enthused to make more and better observations, leading to quality of data across iNaturalist improving, leading to more experts joining iNaturalist, leading to more observations being identified and experts teaching citizen scientists, leading back to citizen scientists making more and better identifications" class="wp-image-50033" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-1024x992.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-300x291.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-768x744.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-1536x1488.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-2048x1984.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/10/Mesaglio-Callaghan_Fig7-1920x1860.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Figure from <a href="https://www.publish.csiro.au/wr/wr20154">Mesaglio and Callaghan 2021</a> demonstrating the importance of expert engagement with iNaturalist.</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>How is your data being used?</strong></p>



<p>iNaturalist data are used extensively in conservation planning, land management, and thousands of scientific journal papers around the globe. In Australia, iNaturalist records feed directly into the ALA, allowing researchers all around the country to access the data at any time. Australian iNaturalist records are being used for a wide range of exciting and important research, including <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0048969720358770?casa_token=-R-YI0mMMCoAAAAA:RzC-t2Qr07fBLAh6s6_kV_hRlFRNhk8ynNfBOSIASjEckHcfTTywlp5XLkmA39qzxurqTg">understanding the effects of bushfires on biodiversity</a>, <a href="https://www.publish.csiro.au/wr/WR24046">monitoring species of biosecurity concern</a>, <a href="https://www.int-res.com/abstracts/meps/v688/p167-172/">quantifying habitat composition from images</a>, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7381433/">rediscovering long unobserved species</a>, and <a href="https://mapress.com/zt/article/view/zootaxa.5380.3.1">even discovering, and facilitating the description of, undescribed genera and species</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>How can I get involved?</strong></p>



<p>You can use iNaturalist through <a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/">a browser on your computer</a><a href="#_msocom_6"> </a>or via the mobile phone app: check out <a href="https://ala.org.au/publications/a-guide-to-inaturalist/">our in-depth guide</a> to get you started. iNaturalist Australia is the fastest growing citizen science platform in the country, so there’s no better time to join than now! The achievements to date have all been thanks to the dedicated and passionate people observing, identifying and curating observations of Australia’s amazing biodiversity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Improving the ALA&#8217;s search results</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/improving-the-alas-search-results/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2024 07:56:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49978</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA's Data Profile has been updated for better search results]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a>When using the Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s occurrence search, our Data Profile tool</a> filters out potentially problematic records to lift the visibility of higher quality data. We&#8217;re changing it to filter iNaturalist records that are verifiable but haven&#8217;t yet been verified by default.</p>



<p>iNaturalist Australia is one of the largest and most up to date datasets in the ALA. As of September 2024, <a href="https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dr1411">more than 7.5 million iNaturalist records</a> are loaded into the ALA, with tens of thousands of new records every week.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1821" height="1365" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited.jpeg" alt="close up view of brushlike grevillea flowers" class="wp-image-50009" style="width:405px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited.jpeg 1821w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited-1536x1151.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/red-tooth-brushes-grevillea-hookeriana-thebeachcomber-CCBY-edited-640x480.jpeg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1821px) 100vw, 1821px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Red tooth brushes (<em>Grevillea hookeriana</em>) Credit: thebeachcomber CC-BY</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The ALA accepts two main types of verifiable record from iNaturalist: &#8216;Research Grade&#8217; and &#8216;Needs ID&#8217;. While this will continue to be the case a new ALA data profile update means only Research Grade records will now be shown by default on maps and in search results.</p>



<p><a>A third category is &#8216;Casual&#8217;, which includes records of cultivated plants, records missing important metadata such as the date and/or location, and records with no evidence of the organism. The ALA does not ingest Casual records. </a></p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="why-did-we-make-this-change">Why did we make this change?</h2>



<p>Although the identification accuracy of Needs ID iNaturalist records is still relatively high for many groups of organisms (see for example, <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/blog/94061-observation-accuracy-experiment-v0-4-is-underway">the most recent accuracy experiment run by iNaturalist staff</a>), a number of recent studies <a>(including some major work in preparation on iNaturalist records of Western Australian plants</a>) have shown that Research Grade records have a higher identification accuracy than Needs ID records for most taxa. Filtering Research Grade records in the ALA by default therefore maximises data quality for all users.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-the-difference-between-needs-id-and-research-grade">What is the difference between Needs ID and Research Grade?</h2>



<p>When an observation is first uploaded to iNaturalist, it is designated as &#8216;Needs ID&#8217;. The entry will remain in this category while it only has a single identification at species-level or finer or is identified to a rank coarser than species.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="841" height="966" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic1-1.png" alt="a record page with species name, needs ID flag, photos and one suggested identification" class="wp-image-49993" style="width:600px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic1-1.png 841w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic1-1-261x300.png 261w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic1-1-768x882.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 841px) 100vw, 841px" /></figure>



<p>This iNaturalist record is currently categorised as Needs ID as it only has a single identification attached to it.</p>



<p><a>Broadly speaking, ob</a>servations will shift from Needs ID to Research Grade when at least two identifications have been added (including the observer&#8217;s original identification), the community ID is at a species-level or finer, and more than two-thirds of identifiers agree on the identification (two from two, three from three, three from four, four from five, and so on). Research Grade observations can shift back to Needs ID at any time based on new identifications.</p>



<p>For a more detailed explanation of these grades, refer to pages 27-28 of <em><a href="https://ala.org.au/publications/a-guide-to-inaturalist/">A Guide to iNaturalist: An Australian Perspective</a></em>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="761" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic2-761x1024.png" alt="a record page with species name, research grade flag, photos and two suggested identifications " class="wp-image-49991" style="width:600px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic2-761x1024.png 761w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic2-223x300.png 223w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic2-768x1034.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic2.png 853w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 761px) 100vw, 761px" /></figure>



<p>This iNaturalist record is currently Research Grade, as it has two identifications at a species level which both agree with each other.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-change-has-the-ala-made">What change has the ALA made?</h2>



<p>In the ALA, these Research Grade and Needs ID categories are represented in the Darwin Core field <em>identificationVerificationStatus</em>. The change to the default Data Profile, called &#8220;ALA General&#8221;, now excludes all Needs ID iNaturalist records by default on maps and in search results with a newly established <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000240256-getting-started-with-the-data-quality-filters">group</a>: &#8216;Exclude unverified records&#8217;. This profile is visible at the top of any page of occurrence records in the ALA.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="534" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3-1024x534.png" alt="a search results page showing the data quality profile section at the top highlighted" class="wp-image-49995" style="width:880px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3-1024x534.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3-300x156.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3-768x400.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3-1536x801.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3-1920x1001.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/09/pic3.png 1982w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="can-i-still-view-these-needs-id-records">Can I still view these Needs ID records?</h2>



<p>Needs ID records are still retrievable at any time. All you have to do is untick the checkbox next to the data profile, and the records will then be included in your results. Learn more about <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241038-how-do-i-turnoff-or-modify-the-data-profile">how to modify the ALA data profiles</a>.</p>



<p>If you’re unsure about this change or have any questions, please reach out to <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Exploring next gen biodiversity detection technologies</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-exploring-next-gen-biodiversity-detection-technologies/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 04:41:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49778</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Access to high-quality biodiversity data is more essential than ever in understanding and responding to changes in our natural environment. This information is used for informing planning, policy and decision-making and delivering research. Through the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), more than 135 million species occurrence records are available as open data, with rich information [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Access to high-quality biodiversity data is more essential than ever in understanding and responding to changes in our natural environment. This information is used for informing planning, policy and decision-making and delivering research. Through the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), more than 135 million species occurrence records are available as open data, with rich information accompanying these records such as images, location, spatial, genetic and related data.</p>



<p>By enhancing traditional methods to monitor species with novel technologies, a more comprehensive view of Australia’s biodiversity can be developed. To celebrate Biodiversity Month in September, hear from three speakers as they discuss their use of ecoacoustics, eDNA and camera trapping as innovative methods to enhance our ability to detect and monitor biodiversity in Australia.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar: Exploring next-gen biodiversity detection technologies" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tCcza7ZZqPc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The event was hosted on 4 September 2024 at 11AM AEST.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p>The ALA was grateful to be joined by the following speakers for this webinar: </p>



<p>Christine Chivas from <a href="https://www.mq.edu.au/">Macquarie University</a>, Matthew Luskin from <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/project/the-wildlife-observatory-of-australia-wildobs/" data-type="link" data-id="https://ardc.edu.au/project/the-wildlife-observatory-of-australia-wildobs/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">WildObs</a> at the <a href="https://www.uq.edu.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">University of Queensland</a>, and Paul Roe from <a href="https://www.qut.edu.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Queensland University of Technology</a>.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure></div>


<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Make biodiversity data cleaning shrimp-ler!</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/make-biodiversity-data-cleaning-shrimp-ler/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 06:25:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49699</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA’s new book – Cleaning Biodiversity Data in R]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Why did we publish this book?</strong></p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-1 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<p>Tidying messy data can be difficult, but it is a task that anybody who works with data must face if they want to use data to tackle scientific questions!</p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) Science &amp; Decision Team recently authored a book titled&nbsp;<a href="https://cleaning-data-r.ala.org.au/">Cleaning Biodiversity Data in R</a>. This free resource provides up-to-date information on data cleaning processes for anybody who handles their data using code in R. As Australia’s national biodiversity database, the ALA is frequently asked questions about the best way to clean data using code.&nbsp; To provide advice on this topic, our first step was to investigate what the currently accepted “best” way might be. We deep-dived into multiple recent peer-reviewed research to see whether experts cleaned their biodiversity data in the same way.</p>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow"><div class="wp-block-image is-style-default">
<figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="712" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R-712x1024.png" alt="cover of the data cleaning book, with dark blue background and an orange crustacean" class="wp-image-49700" style="width:312px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R-712x1024.png 712w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R-208x300.png 208w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R-768x1105.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R-1067x1536.png 1067w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R-1423x2048.png 1423w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Cleaning-Biodiversity-Data-in-R.png 1640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px" /></figure></div></div>
</div>



<p>Through this process we discovered that the steps to clean ecological data can be really messy! Even among experts, data cleaning can look completely different depending on the type of investigation and study species. No wonder people ask how to do it!</p>



<p>This book is our response to questions about how to clean biodiversity data in R. The book provides guidance on many of the processes for cleaning biodiversity data.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="513" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-1024x513.png" alt="flow diagram with multiple grey lines intersecting, to illustrate the high number of possible workflows" class="wp-image-49710" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-1024x513.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-300x150.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-768x385.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-1536x770.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-2048x1027.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/simplified_workflow-1920x963.png 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>A flow diagram of possible ecological data cleaning workflows (made using data from ALA’s review). Credit: Martin Westgate</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>What’s covered in the book and who is it for?</strong></p>



<p>In <em>Cleaning Biodiversity Data in R</em>, we provide an overview of a typical biodiversity data cleaning workflow for open-access geo-referenced biodiversity data—from acquisition, to error identification, to correction. These processes are broken down into sections on exploring data, general data cleaning, and data cleaning processes that require expertise in your study species. The book has information suited to those just starting out working with biodiversity using R, to those who are looking for more advanced techniques.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Landscape-socials-1-1024x577.png" alt="green and yellow dots on a map of NSW showing kingfisher records, most are focussed near the Sydney region" class="wp-image-49702" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Landscape-socials-1-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Landscape-socials-1-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Landscape-socials-1-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Landscape-socials-1-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/08/Landscape-socials-1.png 1640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>An informative, artistic representation of Kingfisher records near Sydney, New South Wales, Australia. Credit: Dax Kellie</em></figcaption></figure>



<p>We hope that&nbsp;<a href="https://cleaning-data-r.ala.org.au/">this resource</a> can help support your data cleaning tasks in the future, and act as a useful learning or reference tool for teaching and sharing knowledge around data cleaning.</p>



<p>For more information on working with data in R and Python, check out the&nbsp;<a href="https://galah.ala.org.au/">galah package</a>&nbsp;and<a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/">&nbsp;ALA Labs.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter July 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-july-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49683</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out the ALA&#8217;s July 2024 Newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p id="block-e6556f64-c2e0-49e7-b903-7825bd5b688f">Check out the ALA&#8217;s <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/july-2024-newsletter-9577615">July 2024 Newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="658" height="918" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ala-newsletter-july-24-thumbnail.png" alt="ALA's July 2024 newsletter header banner - it includes the ALA logo and a frog, and a welcome message" class="wp-image-49685" style="width:590px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ala-newsletter-july-24-thumbnail.png 658w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ala-newsletter-july-24-thumbnail-215x300.png 215w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 658px) 100vw, 658px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; July 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-july-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 01:35:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49626</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the July 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter. In this issue, we are excited to release our 2024-25 ALA Annual Workplan which is a key element of our strategic and operational planning process. Priorities in the workplan are informed by ALA’s Strategy 2020–2025, operational priorities that may emerge in [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Welcome to the July 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>In this issue, we are excited to release our <a href="https://ala.org.au/publications/ala-annual-work-plan-2024-2025/">2024-25 ALA Annual Workplan</a> which is a key element of our strategic and operational planning process. Priorities in the workplan are informed by<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/publications/ala-strategy-2020-2025/"> ALA’s Strategy 2020–2025</a>, operational priorities that may emerge in any year, and partnerships that the ALA has commenced establishing. The workplan acts as both an internal planning tool to guide team priorities, and for external communication purposes to provide our stakeholders with greater visibility into ALA operations.</p>



<p>2024-25 will be the fifth year of delivery under the ALA’s current strategy. Priorities will include the production release of several important initiatives that commenced 2023-24, including the (a) operational national biosecurity alerts service, (b) new ALA home page, species pages and global search interface under the UX/UI project, and (c) stage two of the taxonomic architecture project which will include improved species names matching. Collectively, these capabilities will be transformational for Australia’s biodiversity data community, and we look forward to their release. &nbsp;</p>



<p>As a national research infrastructure supported under the NCRIS program, partnerships are fundamental to how the ALA benefits Australia’s researchers, decision-makers and community. In 2024-25, the ALA will further partner with Australia’s biological collections sector and to develop a case to support a <a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Accelerating_Discovery_and_Access_to_Australias_Biological_Collections_2024_June.pdf">national approach to biological collections</a> akin to the major programs currently underway in Europe and the United States. Beyond the biological collections sector, the ALA will improve the reach and depth of its partnerships with Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander People, working more closely with Indigenous ranger programs to co-design and deliver training programs to enhance the utility of the ALA. Similarly, this year we established a number of partnerships with the environmental consulting sector given the critical role they play in assessing and monitoring Australia’s biodiversity, and we plan to extend these partnerships to support improved translation of research infrastructure to industry.</p>



<p>Our workplan also identifies project leads from the ALA, and we encourage you to reach out to our team to learn more or to collaborate. I hope you enjoy reading our July 2024 Newsletter. </p>



<p><strong>Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director.</strong></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
