<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 00:48:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter March 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-march-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 00:48:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49356</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out the ALA&#8217;s March 2024 Newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p id="block-e6556f64-c2e0-49e7-b903-7825bd5b688f">Check out the ALA&#8217;s <a href="https://us14.campaign-archive.com/?u=b238aea31bbd4bd103ff7368c&amp;id=3b73febd33" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">March 2024 Newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="692" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24-692x1024.png" alt="ALA's March 2024 newsletter header banner - it includes the ALA logo and a waratah, a large red flower" class="wp-image-49359" style="width:663px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24-692x1024.png 692w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24-203x300.png 203w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24.png 724w" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; March 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-march-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 23:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49342</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the March 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In this issue we are proud to be launching Round 3 of the ALA Australian Biodiversity Mobilisation Program. This is one of ALA’s flagship programs that was designed three years ago to provide a mechanism to support the digitisation and provision of important biodiversity that may otherwise not be provided to the ALA. In the first two years the program has supported 12 remarkable teams to digitally enable their data and make it available to the ALA as open data, and through that effort internationally to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility. These <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">12 current projects </a>span a range of incredible institutions, species, and provide important geographic coverage. This year we are excited to have secured additional support from <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/about/challenges-missions/biosecurity">CSIRO’s Catalysing Australia’s Biosecurity initiative</a>. This will provide additional focus on species of biosecurity concern which we know will generate additional excitement around the program, and deliver data to the ALA that assists Australia’s biosecurity sector to better assess risk, and mitigations.</p>



<p>ALA’s <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA-Strategy-2020-2025.pdf">Strategy 2020-2025</a> has an action to ‘establish data priorities to ensure Australia has a nationally comprehensive, representative and adequate biodiversity data infrastructure’. In addition to supporting those parts of the biodiversity data sector that may be resource constrained, the Data Mobilisation Program has become an important mechanism for independently identifying data priorities, whether geographic or taxonomic and starting to fill these gaps in our national biodiversity data system. The existing 12 projects, and approximately nine projects we expect to fund in 2024 will play a fundamental role in ensuring the Australian biodiversity research, management and policy landscape has access to the best available data. The launch of Round 3 also provides a timely reminder that we are keen to grow this important national program through <a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/ALA-Australian-Biodiversity-Data-Mobilisation-Program-Prospectus-December-2022.pdf">partnerships</a> with government, industry and the research sector so please do reach out if you’d like to play a supporting role in future years.</p>



<p>We hope you enjoy our March Newsletter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Taxonomist Appreciation Day</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/taxonomist-appreciation-day-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 21:16:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49299</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[19th March is the perfect day to celebrate and share some facts about tax(onomy) in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA)! We sat down with Cam Slatyer who is a Project Manager in the ALA to chat about his extensive experience and incredible stories working across taxonomy throughout his career. Q: How is taxonomy evolving [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>19<sup>th</sup> March is the perfect day to celebrate and share some facts about tax(onomy) in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA)!  We sat down with Cam Slatyer who is a Project Manager in the ALA to chat about his extensive experience and incredible stories working across taxonomy throughout his career. </p>



<p><strong>Q: How is taxonomy evolving in the ALA and what’s your role in this project?</strong></p>



<p>A: The ALA has a fascinating challenge with taxonomy. We bring together data from Australia and the world, historic and new. Taxonomy is a living, evolving science where names are proposed by scientists as theories, some are accepted, and some aren’t. Names change over time.&nbsp; Take the Platypus, which has the scientific name (<em>Ornithorhynchus anatinus). </em>When it was first described by science, it was called <em>(Platypus anatinus</em>), but someone discovered that the name was already being used for a group of beetles (and still is). You can’t have that in taxonomy. The International Codes of Nomenclature (which definitely aren’t like the Pirate Code in <em>Pirates of the Caribbean</em>) try to stop that sort of thing. It’s like not having two people in the same friendship with the same name: they end up getting called Cam 1 and Cam 2 or Blue because one has red hair. This has meant that the poor old Platypus has a scientific name that means duck-like bird-snout&#8230; which is a pretty good description really.</p>



<p>In the ALA, we need to cope with all names,  for everything from viruses to mountain ash to make sure that data end up under the best available name. That has been a challenge ever since the ALA first started, but now with more than 135 million records, it is vast. My job with my colleagues, is to improve it. We rely heavily on the Australian Government’s Australian Biological Resources Study, who have spent the last few years putting together a National Species List, as well as the Australian Plant Census, run by all the herbaria in Australia, to get our names. We also take names from the New Zealand Organism Register and the International Catalogue of Life to make names match. So our job for the next year or so, is removing things like duplicates, adding missing names and improving name matching. One of our biggest challenges is the differences between Australia and New Zealand. It isn’t just the All Blacks we need to keep an eye on! There are important scientific reasons why Australia and New Zealand have different names for the same things, but we are trying to make sure the New Zealand species have New Zealand names and the Australian species have Australian names.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Platypus-Ornithorhynchus-anatinus-Photo-Credit-adamrichardt-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49300" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Platypus-Ornithorhynchus-anatinus-Photo-Credit-adamrichardt-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Platypus-Ornithorhynchus-anatinus-Photo-Credit-adamrichardt-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Platypus-Ornithorhynchus-anatinus-Photo-Credit-adamrichardt-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Platypus-Ornithorhynchus-anatinus-Photo-Credit-adamrichardt-CC-BY-NC-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Platypus-Ornithorhynchus-anatinus-Photo-Credit-adamrichardt-CC-BY-NC.jpg 1740w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Platypus (<em>Ornithorhynchus anatinus) </em>Photo Credit adamrichardt CC BY NC.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Q: Tell us about your experience working in taxonomy!</strong></p>



<p>A: I’m not a taxonomist, but I’ve been lucky enough to work alongside taxonomists for many years. I’ve seen an amazing array of new species and been privileged enough to have three species named after me. My favourite experience was working on heritage listing mound springs, which are incredibly important and unique freshwater springs in Queensland and South Australia, having species that are often found nowhere else on Earth. I was accompanying a freshwater snail taxonomist, looking for new species and checking on existing ones. We’d been through dozens of springs and hadn’t found any new species, which was enormously frustrating. I was looking for frogs while my colleagues were sieving for snails (mound spring snails are tiny). I found these little black dots on some leaves and showed them to the scientist. Turns out it was the only new species of the trip, were described and then immediately identified as endangered. Not bad for a frog person!</p>



<p><strong>Q: What are some current challenges in the field of taxonomy?</strong></p>



<p>A: Sadly, the biggest challenge is the same as when I first started working with taxonomists in the late 1990s. We are running out of taxonomists, which is frightening given they are essential for identifying threats such as the recent Varroa mite incursion, or understanding the status of threatened species. Over a third of the taxonomists in Australia are voluntary – retirees or people doing taxonomy in their spare time. Government funding for taxonomy hasn’t been increased since 1974 and museums and herbaria are the mainstay of our capacity.</p>



<p><strong>Q: Do you have a favourite species?</strong></p>



<p>A: Australia has around 154,000 named species. I think I have new favourites as I learn about them. But most of my regular favourites are frogs, including the stuttering frog (<em>Mixophyes balbus</em>) or bats like the golden-tipped bat (<em>Phoniscus papuensis</em>)!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-49301" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC-1536x1024.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC-1920x1280.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Stuttering-Frog-Mixophyes-balbus-Photo-Credit-Daniel-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Stuttering Frog (<em>Mixophyes balbus)</em> Photo Credit Daniel CC BY NC.</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-49302" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-1920x1440.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/Golden-tipped-Bat-Phoniscus-papuensis-Photo-Credit-donnamarietomkinson-CC-BY-CN.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Golden-tipped Bat (<em>Phoniscus papuensis</em>) Photo Credit donnamarietomkinson CC BY NC.</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>What’s in a Name? Refreshing the ALA taxonomy</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/whats-in-a-name-refreshing-the-ala-taxonomy/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 03:53:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49248</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Changing the taxonomic backbone of the Atlas of Living Australia]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>What’s the difference between<a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/ALA_DR656_1862#classification"></a><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/d1a27333-c288-46d5-a034-f42920ddb1b8#overview">(<em>Tyto novaehollandiae kimberli)</em></a> and <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/2c30d58b-572b-4dab-8644-b222c28eb0ec#overview"><em>(Tyto novaehollandiae castanops)</em></a>? Although these two birds are similar, they are different sub-species of Masked Owls that are found on completely opposite ends of Australia, and as such have different taxonomic names!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Fungi-Friday-31-1024x577.png" alt="two different owls, one is grey with mottled brown wings (northern Australian masked owl) and the other is yellow-brown all over (Tasmanian masked owl) " class="wp-image-49249" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Fungi-Friday-31-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Fungi-Friday-31-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Fungi-Friday-31-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Fungi-Friday-31-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Fungi-Friday-31.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Northern Australian Masked Owl <em>(Tyto novaehollandiae ssp. kimberli</em>) and Tasmanian Masked Owl (<em>Tyto novaehollandiae castanops</em>).</figcaption></figure>



<p>Taxonomy is the scientific practice of naming, describing and classifying organisms, and is the fundamental basis for how data in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) are organised. Species taxonomy is continuously evolving based on new scientific discoveries (new species being described), as well as techniques such as genetic sequencing, bioinformatics and advanced imaging which can change the way researchers understand existing species leading to re-classification.</p>



<p>To accurately reflect current taxonomy of species listed within the ALA, we are continuously working to improve our ‘taxonomic backbone’ i.e. source material for which species in the ALA are structured.</p>



<p><strong>How species are structured in the ALA</strong></p>



<p>The ALA&nbsp;<a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000261677-taxonomy-in-the-ala">taxonomic backbone</a>&nbsp;is principally sourced from the&nbsp;<a href="https://biodiversity.org.au/nsl/">National Species List (NSL)</a>, but we also draw names from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.nzor.org.nz/">New Zealand Organism Register (NZOR)</a>&nbsp;as well as the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.catalogueoflife.org/">Catalogue of Life (CoL)</a>. We have recently undergone significant changes to align our taxonomic backbone to better fit current scientific names recognised in Australia. This reduces duplication of species listings in the ALA and improves accuracy and navigation when users are searching for new species or threatened species records.</p>



<p><strong>What’s the numbers?</strong></p>



<p>In May 2023, the ALA had 154,506 species of animals (with 2,400 unranked animal species listings) and 48,972 species of plants (with 5,555 unranked plant species listings), giving a total of ~ 211,000 plant and animal species recorded in the ALA. Unranked species are species that either cannot be placed in the taxonomy or have been added to enable data matching to an existing species.</p>



<p>Through our recent work to improve ALA’s taxonomic backbone removing duplication and aligning to current taxonomy, we have reduced these listings to 124,999 animal species (with 11 unranked) and 41,740 plant species (with 37 unranked). Whilst improving ALA’s taxonomy is an evolving process, this represents a major removal of duplication and error fixing in the ALA’s species listings.</p>



<p><strong>What do these changes look like in the ALA?</strong></p>



<p>Though much of the work to refresh the ALA taxonomic backbone is in the back-end, here are some visible changes that you may notice across the ALA:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Improving synonym matching</strong> – With thousands of unique species in Australia, and more being described and named every year, many species are known by more than one name. While the ALA uses the NSL to source synonyms for species (different names referring to the same speices), there are still differences in names, particularly those used internationally. For example, the <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/0d3239e3-927e-43c1-9d65-4a5e75fe33d3">Green Tree Frog (<em>Litoria caerulea</em>)</a> is known internationally as (<em>Ranoidea careulea)</em> in data sets such as iNaturalist. The changed taxonomy will now mean that many of these synonyms will match to the scientific name that species are most commonly known by in Australia.</li>



<li><strong>Placing names in the taxonomic hierarchy</strong> – The ALA places species within a taxonomy tree, like a family tree. The taxonomic backbone refresh means that we have resolved many previous errors and repeat entries for invertebrates, vertebrates and vascular plants.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Correcting species entries</strong> – We have taken steps to remove duplications and unresolved synonyms in the ALA by reducing the number of sources for our taxonomic backbone. We have therefore removed the Codes for Australian Aquatic Biota (CAAB) and the NZOR as a source of names for vertebrates and invertebrates. We have also consolidated all minor sources into four edited lists that add names used in legislation or species management that do not occur in the NSL – these include a conservation list, a migratory species list, a pests and weeds list and a biosecurity invasive list (species not found in Australia).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="737" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Taxonomy-ala-1024x737.jpg" alt="the taxonomic classification of the masked owl, shown in the form of a hierarchy" class="wp-image-49250" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Taxonomy-ala-1024x737.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Taxonomy-ala-300x216.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Taxonomy-ala-768x552.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Taxonomy-ala.jpg 1297w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Example of classifying species in a hierarchy on the ALA.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>What’s next?</strong></p>



<p>We will continue to further improve the ALA taxonomic backbone over the next twelve to eighteen months and resolve issues that have not already addressed.</p>



<p>We are continuing to provide both NSL and NZOR names for plant species, at the request of the <a href="https://chah.gov.au/">Council of Australasian Herbaria</a>.&nbsp;There will continue to be some duplication both in the taxonomic tree and in scientific name synonyms between Australia and New Zealand. For fungi, protists (including algae), bacteria and viruses, we will continue accepting names from NSL, NZOR and CoL.</p>



<p>All changes to the ALA taxonomic backbone have been actioned in consultation with the<a href="https://www.dcceew.gov.au/science-research/abrs">&nbsp;Australian Biological Resources Study</a>&nbsp;and the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anbg.gov.au/cpbr/program/hc/hc-APC.html">Australian Plant Census.</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-1024x1024.jpg" alt="a small green frog" class="wp-image-49252" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC-1920x1920.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Green-Tree-Frog-Litoria-caerulea-Photo-Credit-aleckarcz-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Green Tree Frog (<em>Litoria caerulea</em>) Photo Credit aleckarcz CC BY NC.</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Australia’s most unwanted: Tackling invasives with The ALA Biosecurity Alerts Service</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/australias-most-unwanted-tackling-invasives-with-the-ala-biosecurity-alerts-service/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2024 06:13:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48781</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Helping to protect our biodiversity from the threats of invasive species.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="http://ala.org.au/">Atlas of Living Australia</a> (ALA) is Australia’s largest open-source biodiversity data infrastructure. Home to more than 132 million species occurrence records of native and introduced species, the ALA is often the first platform where invasive species incursions are publicly recorded. Invasive species – like pests, weeds, and diseases – are a major driver of biodiversity loss and pose significant threats to both the economy and our community. To ensure management authorities are notified of new incursions, the ALA has partnered with the <a href="https://www.agriculture.gov.au/">Commonwealth Department of Agriculture, Fisheries and Forestry</a> and <a href="https://www.csiro.au/">CSIRO</a> through the <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/about/challenges-missions/biosecurity">Catalysing Australia’s Biosecurity</a> initiative to develop the Biosecurity Alerts Service.</p>



<p>The ALA’s Biosecurity Alerts Service provides weekly email notifications of occurrences of invasive species to management authorities. These occurrences are aggregated from more than 850 data suppliers, including <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/">iNaturalist</a> and <a href="https://www.feralscan.org.au/">FeralScan</a>. The Biosecurity Alerts Service reports the species name, observation location, images, data provider and provides direct links to the ALA occurrence record. Up until the end of 2023, 1,441 occurrences of invasive species had triggered a biosecurity alert, which included reports of highly invasive species, such as red imported fire ants (<em>Solenopsis invicta)</em>, Asian sho<a>re crabs (<em>Hemigrapsus sanguineus</em>), m</a>yrtle rust and <em>Opuntia </em>cacti. Land management agencies who receive the alerts are using the information in many ways, including verifying reports, undertaking management actions and <a>correcting false identifications.</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48782" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC-1920x1281.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Spotted-Lanternfly-Lycorma-delicatula-Photo-Credit-Solomon-Hendrix-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The ALA&#8217;s Biosecurity Alerts are on the lookout for Spotted Lanternflies <em>(Lycorma delicatula</em>), a highly invasive planthopper on Australia’s most unwanted list<em>s</em>. Photo credit Solomon Hendrix CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>“There is no doubt that the biosecurity alert system has improved our statewide surveillance capability [in Queensland]. While we have only been using it for a short period we have already recorded several significant detections. I’ve been promoting the system at every opportunity,” said Steve Csurhes, Biosecurity Queensland, Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.</p>



<p>Recently, the ALA has developed new <a>spatial filtering features </a>within the Biosecurity Alerts Service. This has allowed users to limit alerts to within state/territory or local government boundaries (including marine boundaries) or provide a custom spatial boundary (shapefile) for alerts within a user-defined area. This has improved the utility of biosecurity alerts, allowing them to be used more readily for reporting within National Parks boundaries or outside of biosecurity containment zones.</p>



<p>The ALA is currently delivering Phase 1 of the Biosecurity Alert Service, which includes roll out of the Service to Commonwealth, State and Territory biosecurity managers. Phase 2 will begin in mid-2024 with operational enhancements allowing the service to scale nationally better, and the inclusion of interested local government areas, natural resource managers, non-government organisations and others within the biosecurity sector. You can read more about this project in our <a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/ALA-Case-Study-Biosecurity-Alerts-Fact-Sheet-Jan-2024.pdf">Impact Case Study</a> or <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/">contact us</a> if you’d like to learn more about ALA’s services to support biosecurity.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Combating myrtle rust with citizen science</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/combating-myrtle-rust-with-citizen-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 05:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Tackling invasive species with data]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Exotic species are reaching Australian shores at&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/news/All/News/2023/September/Expert-Commentary-Invasive-Alien-Species">unprecedented rates</a>, due to increased human movement and trade. Each introduction of an invasive species poses a potential threat to Australia’s unique biodiversity and ecological communities. Invasive species monitoring is therefore essential to understanding their spread, range and abundance in Australia. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia’s (ALA)&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">Biosecurity Hub</a>&nbsp;is a one-stop-shop for biosecurity records, projects and information. The ALA currently holds information on more than 2,383 exotic species and 1.9 million occurrences of pests, weeds, and diseases. Although this information has helped to inform&nbsp;<a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/ALA-Case-Study-Biosecurity-Alerts-Fact-Sheet-Jan-2024.pdf">current biosecurity responses</a>, continuous data collection is required to create the most detailed picture of Australia’s invasive species landscape.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Citizen scientists play a crucial role in invasive species monitoring by reporting observations at a local level. These reports help to inform early detection and long-term management of biosecurity threats. The ALA works with more than 850 data partners to aggregate native and invasive records, making this information easily accessible through open data. As an example, the ALA has a weekly data integration feed with the citizen science platform&nbsp;<a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/">iNaturalist</a>, enabling rapid discovery of recent citizen science data, as well as supporting data users and providers such as&nbsp;the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.anpc.asn.au/">Australian Network for Plant Conservation</a> and the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/projects/gum-tree-guardians">Gum Tree Guardians</a>&nbsp;through facilitating open access to aggregated biodiversity records.</p>



<p><strong>One threat among many: The invasive myrtle rust fungus</strong></p>



<p>If you’ve visited the east coast of Australia in spring or autumn since 2010, you may have noticed plants developing bright yellow spores due to myrtle rust infection. Myrtle rust is an invasive fungus that infects plants in the&nbsp;<a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/id.biodiversity.org.au/taxon/apni/51376810"><em>Myrtaceae</em>&nbsp;family</a>, including more than 1,500 species of Australian native trees and shrubs such as&nbsp;tea trees, bottlebrushes, paperbarks, and lily-pillies. Non-native <em>Myrtaceae, </em>which are often grown in gardens or urban forests, are also affected and contribute to the spread of myrtle rust. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49195" style="width:699px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Eugenia-reinwardtiana-foliage-2-Noosaville-1920x1280.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Myrtle rust on Beach cherry/Bay cherry (<em>Eugenia reinwardtiana)</em> foliage – Photo Credit Geoff Pegg, Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.</figcaption></figure>



<p>In the short time since its introduction, myrtle rust has had devastating impacts on plant communities. Senior Principal Forest Pathologist Dr Geoff Pegg at Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries has said that since myrtle rust was first detected in Australia, it has been a significant contributor to the decline in some of our most iconic native trees like the native guava and scrub turpentine, which were previously common across Queensland and New South Wales.</p>



<p><em>“People often think that biosecurity starts and stops at the border, but what happens post-border is just as important. Managing these threats in native ecosystems is challenging. I’ve seen first-hand the devastating effects that invasive diseases like myrtle rust have on our biodiversity. Areas of outstanding natural beauty and ecological significance, such as the Daintree and the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organisation</em>&nbsp;(<em>UNESCO) World Heritage Gondwana Rainforests, are now threatened due to the rapid spread of myrtle rust.”</em><strong></strong></p>



<p><strong>How to spot myrtle rust infection</strong></p>



<p>Myrtle rust affects seedlings, saplings and old established trees.&nbsp;The most distinct symptom of myrtle rust is bright yellow spores on new leaves, stems, flowers, or fruit. Leaves can become deformed and in severe cases, may die and appear scorched. Repeated infections can reduce plant vigour, cause significant defoliation, killing more susceptible trees and preventing flowering and fruiting on others, thereby interfering with reproduction and reducing the food resources for many native animals.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="786" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Austromyrtus-dulcis-fruit5-786x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49196" style="width:446px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Austromyrtus-dulcis-fruit5-786x1024.jpg 786w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Austromyrtus-dulcis-fruit5-230x300.jpg 230w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Austromyrtus-dulcis-fruit5-768x1000.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Austromyrtus-dulcis-fruit5-1179x1536.jpg 1179w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Austromyrtus-dulcis-fruit5.jpg 1448w" sizes="(max-width: 786px) 100vw, 786px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Myrtle rust on <a>Midgen berr</a>ies (<em>Austromyrtus dulcis)</em> &#8211; Photo Credit Geoff Pegg, Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="628" height="942" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Geoff-Pgg.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49197" style="width:446px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Geoff-Pgg.jpg 628w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Geoff-Pgg-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 628px) 100vw, 628px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Repeated myrtle rust infection has almost killed this 100-year-old Sour cherry tree (<em>Syzygium corynanthum</em>) in the Tallebudgera Valley <a>&#8211; Photo Credit Geoff Pegg</a>, Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Help provide up-to-date myrtle rust data</strong></p>



<p>To combat the threat of myrtle rust, current data is required to inform researchers, policymakers, landholders and decision-makers about how myrtle rust spreads&nbsp;and impacts different plant communities. Members of the public across Australia can play a vital role by reporting possible myrtle rust infections through citizen science, providing data that helps to protect Australia’s high-risk species. Data from citizen science contributes to a more complete record of the abundance and impacts of invasive species.</p>



<p>Alyssa Martino, a PhD student at the University of Sydney who is studying myrtle rust infection and leads the iNaturalist Gum Tree Guardians project says that,</p>



<p><em>“People submit myrtle rust reports from their gardens or out in the bush – places that are hard for professional researchers to monitor. When people report these myrtle rust sightings, we get a broader understanding of the extent of the disease which gives us a chance to fight back against the spread.”&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>The myrtle rust data from citizen scientists are then aggregated in the ALA with data collected from other sources, such as professional scientists, industry and government agencies, to be open and accessible data points.</p>



<p><strong>How to report myrtle rust sightings</strong></p>



<p>By collecting myrtle rust data, you’re helping to paint a more detailed picture of Australia’s invasive species.</p>



<ol>
<li>Install a citizen science app such as&nbsp;<a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/pages/getting+started">iNaturalist</a>&nbsp;or&nbsp;<a href="https://naturemapr.org/content/how-to">NatureMapr</a>.</li>



<li>Use the <strong><a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/ALA-Myrtle-Rust-Reporting-Guide.pdf">ALA Myrtle Rust Reporting Guide</a></strong> to help you identify and capture the critical information to report possible myrtle rust sightings.</li>



<li><strong>Don’t touch!</strong>&nbsp;Follow&nbsp;<a href="https://www.dcceew.gov.au/environment/invasive-species/diseases-fungi-and-parasites/myrtle-rust">best practices</a>&nbsp;to avoid accidentally spreading pathogens like myrtle rust!</li>



<li>Check out citizen science projects like the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/projects/gum-tree-guardians">iNaturalist project Gum Tree Guardians</a>&nbsp;to connect with experts and learn more about myrtle rust in Australia.</li>
</ol>



<p>For more information, visit the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">ALA Biosecurity Hub</a>&nbsp;or contact us&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/">here</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/projects/gum-tree-guardians"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="717" height="253" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Gum-tree-guardians.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49198" style="width:278px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Gum-tree-guardians.png 717w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Gum-tree-guardians-300x106.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 717px) 100vw, 717px" /></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.anpc.asn.au/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/ANPC_inline_col-1024x300.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49271" style="width:283px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/ANPC_inline_col-1024x300.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/ANPC_inline_col-300x88.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/ANPC_inline_col-768x225.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/ANPC_inline_col.png 1210w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Transforming Australia’s biological collections to open data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-transforming-australias-biological-collections-to-open-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 23:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49259</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[View the recording from the ALA's first webinar of 2024.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) first webinar of 2024 showcased a selection of amazing projects from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>. This important initiative supports the mobilisation of Australia’s biodiversity data which may not yet be digital, making it available through the ALA, and internationally to the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a>. By improving digital access, the program delivers stronger research and conservation outcomes for Australia’s unique biodiversity.</p>



<p>Hear from three projects that were supported through the program. Learn about the transformative power of biodiversity data, and how previously inaccessible physical specimens in biological collections can be made available as open data.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by CSIRO.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar Transforming Australia’s biological collections to open data   Web" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G7GIp7LTryk?start=111&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Weblink to recording: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7GIp7LTryk&amp;t=111s" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7GIp7LTryk&amp;t=111s</a>. The event was hosted on 20 Feb 2024 at 11AM AEDT. It was attended by more than 400 live viewers on the day. </figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p><strong>Dr David Hocking</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/DavidHocking-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6ED9FEC654AB56C83666A26317AF962652BBB6F2" alt="Dr David Hocking"/></figure>



<p>Dr David Hocking is the Senior Curator of Vertebrate Zoology at the Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery (TMAG). TMAG houses the Tasmanian Devil Tissue Bioarchive and also curates a growing collection of frozen tissue specimens for a wide range of vertebrate wildlife. The 2023 Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program allowed TMAG to digitise a remaining bulk collection of devil tissues and establish a new TMAG Tissue Collection on the ALA providing a public portal into this growing resource of specimens for future research and analysis.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Mieke Strong</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/MiekeStrong-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6C8427B3B9EB5A9979FE4527484D02147E28644D" alt="Dr Mieke Strong"/></figure>



<p>Mieke has over 15 years working and studying biological sciences and has a PhD in the taxonomy of fish parasites from the University of Queensland and the Queensland Museum. She has worked as a technical officer at the Department of Fisheries in Western Australia, as a researcher at the Western Australian Museum (terrestrial invertebrates), and as an environmental consultant at Biota Environmental Sciences. As part of her current role at Gaia Resources, Mieke interest is in determining data formatting and data requirements for natural sciences and collections projects, focusing on data standards.</p>



<p><strong>Dean Beasley</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/DeanBeasley-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=AAB8F0C1D16AA865B158CF43E4385C520DF0689E" alt="Dean Beasley"/></figure>



<p>Dean Beasley joined Queensland Museum in 2019, and administer the Vernon Collection Management System used to catalogue Biodiversity &amp; Geosciences specimens as well as Cultures &amp; Histories objects held by the museum. The Vernon database holds over 1.1 million records. Its functionality includes, but is not limited to, processes that assist with accessioning specimens and objects, managing incoming and outgoing loans, acquisition proposals, tracking specimen and object locations, valuations, managing exhibitions, storing associated images and documentation. Prior to QM, Dean worked for the Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries (DAF) within the Plant Pathology Herbarium (2000) and Insect Collection (2008), where he administered the KE EMu database, and developed Lucid keys to plant pathogens.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Kit Prendergast</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/KitPrendergast-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FEF01E130CBAACECB8E5D599B69A0AF9759E27FB" alt="Dr Kit Prendergast"/></figure>



<p>Dr Kit Prendergast is a native bee researcher. She has conducted native bee biodiversity surveys across the Swan Coastal Plain and Jarrah forest of southwest of Western Australia, the wheatbelt, Gascoyne and Goldfields of WA, and Traditional landowner lands in northern Western Australia for her PhD, surveys for local and state government, land care groups, and communities. She has amassed an incredible collection of native bee specimens, which includes new range records, species not collected for decades, and many undescribed species. Thanks to the ALA Data Mobilisation Program, these specimens are finally making their way onto the map and being catalogued at the WA Museum, representing a rich dataset for researchers now and in the future.</p>



<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Call for applications – GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/call-for-applications-gbif-2024-graduate-researchers-award/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 22:15:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49206</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are open for the GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award! This award is an annual program aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics at the Masters and PhD student level.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="320" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1024x320.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49207" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1024x320.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-300x94.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-768x240.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1536x480.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1920x600.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The 2024 programme will provide two €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD $8,200) recognising the work of two early-career researchers. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> (GBIF). The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA are also accessible via GBIF.</p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p><strong><em><mark>Australian applications to the ALA are due by 31st May 2024.</mark></em></strong></p>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;if you require further information.</p>



<p>A jury organised by <a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a> will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat.</p>



<p>Note: Awardees are expected to acknowledge GBIF support when disseminating research results via peer-reviewed publications, presentations at professional meetings, and other media.</p>



<p><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></p>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol start="1">
<li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)</li>



<li><strong>Project description</strong> (<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em> <em>font</em>) that describes:<br>a. How the research advances biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity.<br>b. <strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.</li>



<li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.</li>



<li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate program of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li>
</ol>



<p><strong>How to submit an application to the ALA (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol start="1">
<li>Visit the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/0YedTUAf3Nk14JKZqBn0a/call-opens-for-nominations-to-2024-gbif-graduate-researchers-award#_national-deadlines-for-2024">GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award</a> page and follow the instructions. <br></li>



<li>Submit your nominations to <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a> with ‘2024 GBIF Graduate Researchers Application _YOUR NAME’ in the subject line by <strong>31st May 2024.</strong></li>
</ol>



<p>The criteria for the awards include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Originality and innovation</li>



<li>Use of and strategic significance for data accessed through GBIF</li>



<li>Measurable effectiveness and impact in advancing biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/0YedTUAf3Nk14JKZqBn0a/call-opens-for-nominations-to-2024-gbif-graduate-researchers-award#_national-deadlines-for-2024">GBIF</a> website.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blog/">&nbsp;Back to Articles</a></p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>International Day of Women and Girls in Science</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/international-day-of-women-and-girls-in-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 01:45:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[February 11th 2024 is the United Nations International Day of Women and Girls in Science. It’s an opportunity to celebrate the achievements of women and girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), whilst acknowledging the persistent gaps in representation and equality in these fields. We spoke to one of the Atlas of Living Australia’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>February 11th 2024 is the <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/women-and-girls-in-science-day">United Nations International Day of Women and Girls in Science</a>. It’s an opportunity to celebrate the achievements of women and girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), whilst acknowledging the persistent gaps in representation and equality in these fields.</p>



<p>We spoke to one of the Atlas of Living Australia’s (ALA) current internship students Clara Peers Tejero about what motivated her to pursue higher education in STEM.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49213" style="width:365px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-2048x2048.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1920x1920.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Clara Peers Tejero</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Q: What degree are you currently studying?</strong></p>



<p>I’m currently studying at <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/">UNSW</a> and finishing a double degree in Bioinformatic Engineering and Science (Genetics).</p>



<p><strong>Q: What made you decide to study science?</strong></p>



<p>I decided to study science because it’s a way to learn more about how the world works. I love it because I’m constantly learning new things. Science gives us a much deeper understanding about <strong>everything</strong>: from the mechanisms of genomics and personalised medicine to the wonders of exoplanet exploration, and from the complexities of neuroscience and brain plasticity to the delicate balance of Earth&#8217;s biodiversity and the strategies for its conservation. The more you learn, the more amazed you are!</p>



<p><strong>Q: What’s your internship project at the ALA focused on?</strong></p>



<p>My project is focused on <a href="https://ecoassets.org.au/">EcoAssets</a> which combines environmental data collected from three national research infrastructures – the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">ALA</a>, the Integrated Marine Observing System (<a href="https://imos.org.au/">IMOS</a>) and the Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network (<a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a>). I’m looking at ways to improve how people interact with this data, by revamping the website and exploring how to communicate the data. I have been learning so much about data visualisation and how to make it more interesting and interactive for users.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="943" height="911" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49214" style="width:499px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample.png 943w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample-300x290.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample-768x742.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 943px) 100vw, 943px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Data visualisation created by Clara Peers Tejero using ALA&#8217;s galah coding package. </figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Q: Do you have any advice that you would give to somebody considering studying science?</strong></p>



<p>I would say: go for it! There are so many different fields of study in science that I would suggest exploring your areas of interest. Stay up to date on the latest breakthroughs and research happening and seek inspiration from scientists who are doing exciting work in that area.</p>



<p>And make sure to learn some basic coding/programming skills! This will be so useful (even essential) no matter what you end up studying or working in.</p>



<p><strong>Where to find Clara:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/clara-peers-tejero-7b7b30158/">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protecting Australian biodiversity with data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/protecting-australian-biodiversity-with-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:03:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47966</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Meet our ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species. While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Meet our ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners</strong></p>



<p>As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species.</p>



<p>While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used to address specific research goals, these data often require additional resources to ensure they can be digitised and made available nationally as open data.</p>



<p>To improve data accessibility the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) launched the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a> in 2022. This program is designed to support Australian museums, biological collections, herbaria, and research teams to digitise their data, and making it available through the ALA, and internationally through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1024x577.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49179" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program banner.</figcaption></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-left">Through a nationally competitive application process, projects were awarded grants to digitise their priority biodiversity data. The output from this program will enable data on rare and unique species to become open and accessible through the ALA. Using FAIR principles (findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable), this data will support research, decision-making and conservation efforts to better protect Australian biodiversity.</p>



<p><strong>Funded projects:</strong></p>



<p><strong>2022 projects</strong>:</p>



<ul type="1">
<li>New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, NSW – mobilising plant pest and disease data from the NSW Biosecurity Collections (~600,000 records).</li>



<li>South Australia Museum (SAM), SA– mobilise the SAM’s Australian Biological Tissues Collection of 39 donated frozen tissue collections of Australian freshwater fishes (around 90% of all known species and ~46,000 records).</li>



<li>Queensland Museum Network, QLD – mobilising and enhancing data from the Cribb Australian Fish Trematode Collection (&gt;20,000 records of &gt;1,000 fish species).</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery, TAS – mobilising wildlife molecular and tissue data (&gt; 8,500 sample vials and 1,650 formalin-fixed specimens in the histology collection).</li>



<li>Edith Cowan University, WA – mobilising plant and fungi data from the Robert Brown Herbarium.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and Parks Authority, WA – mobilising data in the Kings Park and Botanic Garden Herbarium collection (18,200 specimens).</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>2023 projects:</strong></p>



<ul type="1">
<li>National Herbarium of Victoria, Royal Botanic Gardens of Victoria – mobilising more than 5,000 specimen-based occurrence data records from Australian macroalgae.</li>



<li>Western Australian Museum – mobilising thousands of native bee data records from physical specimens collected southwestern WA, representing more than 200 bee species.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and State Herbarium, South Australia – making &gt;30,000 bryophyte and &gt;6,000 lichen records available to the ALA through digitisation of physical collection labels.</li>



<li>D’Estrees Entomology and Science Services – delivery of 7,000 -10,000 insect occurrence records from Kangaroo Island, focused on underrepresented taxa.</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery – mobilising more than 15,000 invertebrate species records representing Tasmanian spiders, echinoderms, cnidarians and annelids.</li>
</ul>



<p>Congratulations to the successful projects, we look forward to working with them to make their data available nationally. We’d like to also acknowledge the applications that were not successful as they were universally excellent making our assessment process very challenging. We are also grateful to the independent review panel for their work in reviewing proposals and selecting a fantastic suite of final recipients.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47969" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Leanne Wheaton working on collections specimens at South Australia Museum, Photo Credit Denis Smith, South Australia Museum. </figcaption></figure>



<p>The 2024 grant round for the Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program will open for applications in&nbsp;<strong>late autumn 2024</strong>. Keep an eye on the ALA website, social media channels and blogs for more information shortly.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
