<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 23:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA Insights: The hidden world of sensitive species data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-insights-the-hidden-world-of-sensitive-species-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 22:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50691</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) provides reliable biodiversity data for research and conservation, but did you know it also plays a key role in managing sensitive species information? In this session, you’ll learn how the ALA identifies and protects sensitive species records, and how you can request access to the data and contribute by [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) provides reliable biodiversity data for research and conservation, but did you know it also plays a key role in managing sensitive species information?</p>



<p>In this session, you’ll learn how the ALA identifies and protects sensitive species records, and how you can request access to the data and contribute by suggesting the addition of species to the sensitive lists.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="ALA Insights: The hidden world of sensitive species data" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AVigz0nlQY4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This event was hosted on 24 July 2025 at 12pm AEST.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id=""></h3>



<p><strong>Tania Laity &#8211; ALA Business and Policy Analyst<br>Cam Slatyer &#8211; ALA National Biodiversity Data Initiatives Project Manager</strong></p>



<p>Tania Laity and Cam Slatyer both have over thirty years of experience working on science and biodiversity issues in government, conservation and the collections sectors. Cam is currently the subject matter lead on taxonomy for the Atlas of Living Australia and Tania is the Business Analyst. They are currently leading an international working group to develop a data standard for handling Restricted Access Species Data.</p>



<p>Previously, they led a diverse group of government and non-government stakeholders that produced the <a href="https://rasd.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Framework for the Sharing of Restricted Access Species Data</a> in Australia, supported by the Australian Research Data Commons, Atlas of Living Australia and CSIRO as part of the Australian Government&#8217;s National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy.</p>



<p></p>



<p>This event was hosted by <strong>Juliet Seers, </strong>the ALA Training and Outreach Coordinator.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA interns dive into real-world projects</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-interns-dive-into-real-world-projects/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lucinda Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 03:24:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50433</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Supporting the next generation to gain hands-on experience in STEM fields is critical to engaging and inspiring our future researchers and data scientists. That&#8217;s why, each year, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) offers several internship positions with our science and support teams. We chatted with our recent 2025 Summer students, Yaohang, Jarod and Jeff [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Supporting the next generation to gain hands-on experience in STEM fields is critical to engaging and inspiring our future researchers and data scientists. That&#8217;s why, each year, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) offers several internship positions with our science and support teams.<br></p>



<p>We chatted with our recent 2025 Summer students, Yaohang, Jarod and Jeff to find out more about their ALA internship experience and what they’ve learned along the way.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" id="yaohang-li-is-studying-a-bachelor-of-software-engineering-honours-at-the-university-of-technology-sydney"><strong>Yaohang Li is studying a Bachelor of Software Engineering (Honours) at the University of Technology Sydney.</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="565" height="742" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Yaohang-Li.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-50435" style="width:359px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Yaohang-Li.jpg 565w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Yaohang-Li-228x300.jpg 228w" sizes="(max-width: 565px) 100vw, 565px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Yaohang Li said he had the opportunity to gain hands-on experience in his areas of interest, cloud computing and automation, during his internship with the ALA. Photo: Erin Roger</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>1. What&#8217;s your study background?<br></strong>I am an international student currently pursuing a Bachelor of Software Engineering (Honours) at the University of Technology Sydney (UTS). I’m in my final year and I have always had an interest in software and cloud technologies. Throughout my studies, I’ve gained a solid foundation in programming, software and engineering, and I’m really excited to apply my academic knowledge to practical environment and real-world projects.<br></p>



<p><strong>2. What was the topic you chose to focus on? What factors led you to choose this topic?<br></strong>I chose to focus on DevOps engineering, which involved migrating the ALA’s Restricted Access Species Data system’s deployment process. I chose this one because it involves continuous integration and continuous delivery and cloud technologies. My interest in cloud computing and automation, along with the opportunity to work on real-world problems related to my major, made this topic quite interesting for me. Although I’m interested in other topics as well, this one suited me the best for my background.<br></p>



<p><strong>3. What’s a new skill that you learned through the program?<br></strong>I gained valuable experience with cloud technologies, particularly in using infrastructure-as-code solutions that aligns with ALA’s workflow and developed much deeper understanding of different use cases of cloud services and best practice of cloud native technology when building out the infrastructure.<br>I also learned a lot about DevOps and approaches to managing infrastructure. There’s always a gap between learning it from documentation and then applying that to a project. I’m also impressed how ALA manage all the infrastructure and services efficiently.<br></p>



<p><strong>4. What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?<br></strong>One challenge I encountered was differences between two tools we used when migrating the deployment process of API. The existing tool Pulumi made things simple by letting me set up the API with just a few basic settings, but it is highly abstracted. When I switched to using our internal technologies, it provided a more detailed and fine-grained control—I had to manually set up several pieces and make sure they all worked together. At one point, I missed a step, which led to a significant amount of time spent troubleshooting the issue. It was a real learning experience in paying attention to details and troubleshooting issues.<br></p>



<p><strong>5. What was the highlight of your internship experience?<br></strong>The highlight of my internship was successfully completing the system migration with minimal downtime. It was rewarding to see the deployment go smoothly, especially after the long preparation during this summer.<br>Working with my team at ALA was a fantastic experience. Everyone was incredibly supportive, and I learned so much from their expertise—especially from my mentor, Joe. Their guidance helped me apply ALA’s best practices while recreating the infrastructure, allowing us to fully automate the process when setting up and tearing down different environments.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" id="jarod-wright-is-studying-a-bachelor-of-science-majoring-in-ecology-and-conservation-biology-at-the-university-of-wollongong"><strong>Jarod Wright is studying a Bachelor of Science majoring in Ecology and Conservation Biology at the University of Wollongong.</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="891" height="751" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jarod-Wright.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-50437" style="width:404px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jarod-Wright.jpg 891w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jarod-Wright-300x253.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jarod-Wright-768x647.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 891px) 100vw, 891px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jarod Wright participated in the ALA’s 2025 Summer Internship Program.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>1. What’s your study background?<br></strong>My background is a mix of computer science and science. I’m currently studying a Bachelor of Science majoring in Ecology and Conservation Biology, with previous studies majoring in Computer Science.<br></p>



<p><strong>2. What was the topic you chose to focus on? What factors led you to choose this topic?<br></strong>I looked at the impact that the Black Summer bushfires had on Southern Greater Gliders (Petauroides volans) distribution. As a proud Wodi Wodi man, I am deeply interested in understanding how megafires like the Black Summer fires have impacted biodiversity and species distribution in Australia, especially so given the wide scale prevention of the community from continuing traditional fire regimes on the east coast of Australia since colonisation.<br></p>



<p><strong>3. What’s a new skill that that you learned through the program?<br></strong>Species distribution modelling is the biggest skill I learnt! It was a lot of fun and really eye opening to learn about, being able to go out and find data to analyse, and then to produce a species distribution map was a very enjoyable experience and it was very rewarding to produce that final output.<br></p>



<p><strong>4. What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?<br></strong>Managing spatial data and pushing the limits of what my computer could handle was the biggest challenge. The spatial data I was working with is quite big, and modelling is computationally intensive, so it often took a while to run and crashes were frequent, which made debugging and producing the final result a very long but ultimately rewarding experience.<br></p>



<p><strong>5. What was the highlight of your internship experience?<br></strong>The highlight of my internship was definitely getting to know the Science and Decision Support team and working closely with them, whilst spending my summer developing my R skills on a topic that I am very passionate about.</p>



<div style="height:32px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" id="jeff-lu-is-studying-a-bachelor-of-information-systems-at-the-university-of-nsw"><strong>Jeff Lu is studying a Bachelor of Information Systems at the University of NSW.</strong></h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="796" height="930" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jeff-Lu.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-50436" style="width:391px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jeff-Lu.jpg 796w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jeff-Lu-257x300.jpg 257w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/Jeff-Lu-768x897.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 796px) 100vw, 796px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jeff Lu participated in the ALA’s 2025 Summer Internship Program. Photo: Erin Roger</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>1. What’s your study background?<br></strong>I study Information Systems at UNSW.<br></p>



<p><strong>2. What was the topic you chose to focus on? What factors led you to choose this topic?<br></strong>The topic of focus involves gathering user requirements to redesign the user interface of ALA’s Profile Collections site. I chose this topic because I have a keen interest in UX/UI and business analysis, and this topic was perfect for me to apply these skills that I learned in university.<br></p>



<p><strong>3. What’s a new skill that you learned through the program?<br></strong>A new skill that I earned through the program was interviewing people. Before this internship, I had never interviewed anyone before, so naturally, I wouldn’t know how to structure an interview or how to ask questions effectively. Through the guidance of my supervisor and buddy in this project, I was able to learn the key techniques and methods of interviewing people, as well as what questions to ask in order to get the most insights out of people.<br></p>



<p><strong>4. What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?<br></strong>The biggest challenge I encountered during this internship was that I had to work remotely away from my supervisors. Personally, I enjoy collaborating face-to-face with people as it allows for more interactive discussions and immediate feedback.<br></p>



<p><strong>5. What was the highlight of your internship experience?<br></strong>The highlight of my internship would have to be meeting so many amazing people from within ALA. Even though most of us are based in different locations, I was still able to chat and have meaningful conversations with many of my colleagues. Additionally, my colleagues in the Sydney office have been super kind and welcoming to me since day one, which made my internship experience a whole lot better.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" class="wp-block-heading has-medium-font-size" id="more-information"><strong>More information</strong></h2>



<p>If you would like to know more, see our <a href="https://ala.org.au/internships/">ALA internship opportunities</a> page, or contact us at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How do we get more rare species records?</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/how-do-we-get-more-rare-species-records/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 05:21:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50402</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[While some species have millions of observations recorded in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), many lesser-known species have few or even no public records. The ALA has been working to improve taxonomic representativeness of our data with a little help from the international community! So how do we get more rare records? Species specimens [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>While some species have millions of observations recorded in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), many lesser-known species have few or even no public records. The ALA has been working to improve taxonomic representativeness of our data with a little help from the international community!</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="927" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/orchid-927x1024.png" alt="close up of two orchid flowers on a single plant. The flowers have six purple long pointed petals, and the centre of each flower is orange " class="wp-image-50406" style="width:375px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/orchid-927x1024.png 927w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/orchid-272x300.png 272w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/orchid-768x848.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/orchid-1391x1536.png 1391w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/orchid.png 1811w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 927px) 100vw, 927px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Blue Tinsel Lily (<em>Calectasia cyanea</em>), photo credit: botanistbob CC-BY-NC </figcaption></figure></div>


<p>So how do we get more rare records? Species specimens from museums or herbaria are invaluable sources for this task. The thing is, getting access to specimen data isn&#8217;t always easy.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One challenge stems from a strength of taxonomy: It&#8217;s a global discipline. Natural history specimens are sent around the world to experts for careful description and classification. This means that specimens, including those of Australian species, can end up anywhere on the planet.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Another challenge is getting access to specimen data. Digitising specimens helps to make important specimens discoverable by end users. Museums and herbaria face a vast task in digitising their collections, and even though Australia is one of the leading countries in this respect, when there are only one or two existing specimens of a species in the world, it can be difficult to even find these amidst the ocean of specimens awaiting digitisation!&nbsp;</p>



<p>While progress continues to be made digitising the global backlog, it is important to also gather existing lesser-known datasets with <em>digitised </em>specimen data – digitally catalogued physical specimens, photographs or sounds (and metadata about the place and time they were recorded). People often don&#8217;t think to look in international digital specimen datasets for data on Australian species.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The ALA is fortunate to partner with the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> (GBIF), an international repository of many regional and national <a href="https://living-atlases.gbif.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Living Atlases</a> like the ALA. From GBIF, the ALA was able to source an additional three million records of Australian species to the ALA&#8217;s 150 million records.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These additional records have provided the first digital records of a whopping 7,914 Australian species. Another 6,177 had the number of records doubled.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="533" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/gecko.jpg" alt="close up of a gecko with large golden eyes, and mottled yellow and brown body" class="wp-image-50405" style="width:751px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/gecko.jpg 800w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/gecko-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/gecko-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Gulbaru Gecko (<em>Phyllurus gulbaru</em>), photo credit: dhfischer CC-BY</figcaption></figure>



<p>The result is even more exciting for threatened species. These GBIF data have contributed more than 72,703 records of 1,393 federally threatened species! Crucially, GBIF data has contributed records for 482 data-poor species (species with less than 80 records). For another seven threatened species, these data provided their first Australian digital records.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Improving the taxonomic breadth of Australian species records in the ALA is incredibly important for both science and conservation. &nbsp;</p>



<p>More species with openly accessible data means scientists can save time and effort searching for data, having positive impacts on conservation assessments and modelling.&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter March 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-march-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 06:07:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50368</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Discover the ALA&#8217;s March 2025 newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Discover the ALA&#8217;s <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/mar-2025-newsletter" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">March 2025 newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="631" height="837" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/mar-newsletter-cropped-1.png" alt="Top section of the ALA newsletter for March, including ALA logo and banner with a shingleback lizard. " class="wp-image-50373" style="width:459px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/mar-newsletter-cropped-1.png 631w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/03/mar-newsletter-cropped-1-226x300.png 226w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 631px) 100vw, 631px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; March 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-march-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 13 Mar 2025 02:06:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50350</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the March 2025 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter. In December I had the privilege of attending a fantastic event on the topic of Nationally Distributed Collections Infrastructure to Solve Global Research Challenges, as a side event to International Conference on Research Infrastructures held in Brisbane. The ALA hosted the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="719" height="938" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48109" style="width:251px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger-230x300.png 230w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 719px) 100vw, 719px" /></figure></div>


<p>Welcome to the March 2025 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>In December I had the privilege of attending a fantastic event on the topic of Nationally Distributed Collections Infrastructure to Solve Global Research Challenges, as a side event to <a href="https://icri2024.au/" data-type="link" data-id="https://icri2024.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">International Conference on Research Infrastructures</a> held in Brisbane. The ALA hosted the event in partnership with the Queensland Museum, Phenomics Australia and CSIRO.  </p>



<p>The event focussed on the fundamental role research collections and biobanks play in supporting science, decision-making, and industry applications which has received renewed interest, given technological advances that can rapidly generate new data and insights from physical specimens. Novel techniques in genomics, advanced imaging, and, increasingly artificial intelligence and machine learning, means that more information than ever can be derived from Australia’s research collections.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The event brought together international and local experts from across the collections and biobanking sector to explore a number of areas that are seen as critical for supporting future science needs, including (a) Collection digitisation, storage and management, (b) Digital infrastructure, data access and integration, (c) Emerging transformational technology, (d) Skills and workforce development, and finally (e) Sectoral leadership.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The importance of Indigenous data sovereignty and the opportunity to improve how a future state incorporates non-Western knowledge systems was also identified as fundamental.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>With ALA’s historic focus on partnering with Australia’s biological collections sector, it was great to see the parallels within other domains such as human health biobanking and it’s clear there is much to be gained for partnering further.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The ICRI congress itself was fantastic and inspiring to see the current ‘state of the research infrastructure’ internationally, across a number of domain areas. Several ICRI presentations remain available at <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@ICRI2024/videos" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.youtube.com/@ICRI2024/videos</a> and I encourage you to view some of these as they so effectively highlight the strength of Australia’s research infrastructure system, and future opportunities confronting our sector.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy reading our March 2025 Newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director.</strong></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Harnessing biodiversity data to support Australian industry</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-harnessing-biodiversity-data-to-support-australian-industry/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 22:57:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50357</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Access to biodiversity data supports many industries, such as environmental consulting, agriculture, mining, forestry and tourism. By leveraging this valuable resource, businesses can make more informed decisions, minimise environmental impacts, and contribute to Australia&#8217;s sustainability goals. Join this webinar hosted by the ALA to hear how industry professionals utilise biodiversity data to support their business [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Access to biodiversity data supports many industries, such as environmental consulting, agriculture, mining, forestry and tourism. By leveraging this valuable resource, businesses can make more informed decisions, minimise environmental impacts, and contribute to Australia&#8217;s sustainability goals. Join this webinar hosted by the ALA to hear how industry professionals utilise biodiversity data to support their business needs.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar: Harnessing biodiversity data to support Australian industry" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QIXH9kyVGZc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This event was hosted on 4 March 2025 at 12pm AEDT.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p>The ALA was grateful to be joined by the following speakers for this webinar: Juliet Seers from the ALA, Ali Cotton from <a href="https://apemgroup.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">APEM Group</a>, and Elizabeth Stark from <a href="https://www.symbolix.com.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Symbolix</a>.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure></div>


<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New biodiversity data set to benefit all</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-biodiversity-data-set-to-benefit-all/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lucinda Ross]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 04:49:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50141</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia's (ALA) Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program (ABDMP) offers grants to support people and institutions in making their biodiversity data more accessible. Read about our 2024 grant recipients.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) <a href="https://ala.org.au/abdmp/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program (ABDMP)</a> offers grants to support people and institutions in making their biodiversity data more accessible. &nbsp;</p>



<p>You may have read about the ABDMP projects <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-ala-data-mobilisation-projects/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">we announced in July 2024</a> which improved the accessibility of previously untapped biosecurity data. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Well, now we can announce five new projects which have received an ABDMP grant to enable the provision of new biodiversity data into the ALA. </p>



<p>The recipients are:&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ol start="1" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Australian Wildlife Conservancy (AWC):</strong> The largest private land conservation organisation in Australia holding data from remote regions across the continent that are historically under-surveyed, such as the Kimberley, Cape York and the arid zone. AWC surveys have focused on threatened species and restricted-range endemics. It’s estimated AWC will provide more than 260,000 records to the ALA including records from areas that have less published data and from longitudinal surveying.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<ol start="2" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Museums Victoria: </strong>This grant will support the digitisation of a significant Click Beetle (Elateridae) collection for approximately 800 species within Australia. At approximately 15,000 records, this project will add data for an additional 99 species to the ALA and increase in species-level occurrence records by 180%, increase the number of species by 36%, and increase the number of genera by 38%. </li>
</ol>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1024x683.jpg" alt="Woman looking at computer with beetle on screen. " class="wp-image-50142" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/12/JOSEPHBYFORD-101345-1533-1920x1280.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Photo: Joseph Byford Photography</figcaption></figure>



<ol start="3" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria: </strong>This grant supports the mobilisation of specimen-based occurrence data from Australian macrofungi specimens collected by renowned mycologist and fungi photographer Bruce Fuhrer OAM (1930–2023). The project will see the transcription and digitisation of data associated with approximately 1800 specimens and a selection of field images taken by Mr Fuhrer. </li>
</ol>



<ol start="4" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>University of Melbourne: </strong>This project will facilitate the mobilisation of data for non-vascular bryophyte (phylum Bryophyta) and liverwort (phylum Marchantiophyta) specimens, collected by bryologist Dr David Meagher, into the Atlas of Living Australia. Dr Meagher has been described as ‘Australia’s most competent bryologist’. He authored 60 publications, many describing or revising bryophyte and liverwort taxa during his 20+ year research career. In digitising Meagher’s specimens, this project will contribute data for specimens collected from throughout Australia within the last 20 years, documenting contemporary taxon distributions and habitat occupancy for non-vascular taxa that are under-represented in the ALA.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<ol start="5" class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>West Australian Museum: </strong>Dr Barbara York Main (1929–2019) was Australia’s ‘spider-lady’ with an international reputation as a spider researcher and author of books describing the Western Australian environment. Dr Main’s collection is comprised primarily of thousands of trapdoor spiders that she collected over a 60+ year period and is considered the most significant&nbsp;historical collection of this iconic group of spiders in Australia. It also includes Barbara’s field notebooks that describe critical data on burrow structure, and soil and vegetation associations. The collection is estimated to contain 3,500–4,000 specimens and will support a greater understanding of these species in the future. &nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<p>We congratulate the successful projects and grant recipients for 2024 and thank our review panel for their time and expertise in evaluating many high-calibre applications this year. &nbsp;</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Generous interfaces for discovering complex biodiversity data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-generous-interfaces-for-discovering-complex-biodiversity-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 01:08:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50118</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[How can we ensure our data can be easily and generously accessed? In this webinar, Generous interfaces for discovering biodiversity data, the ALA&#8217;s Dr Martin Westgate and the ANU&#8217;s Prof Mitchell Whitelaw and Prof Adrian Mackenzie delve into their recent work with the ALA on finding more generous ways to explore biodiversity data. We explore [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>How can we ensure our data can be easily and generously accessed? In this webinar, Generous interfaces for discovering biodiversity data, the ALA&#8217;s Dr Martin Westgate and the ANU&#8217;s Prof Mitchell Whitelaw and Prof Adrian Mackenzie delve into their recent work with the ALA on finding more generous ways to explore biodiversity data.</p>



<p>We explore how the development of novel interfaces is transforming the way biodiversity data is presented, making it more inviting and accessible for a diverse range of users.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar: Generous interfaces for discovering complex biodiversity data" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/25yFLAT89E0?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>The event was hosted on 12 November 2024 at 12PM AEDT.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p>The ALA was grateful to be joined by the following speakers for this webinar: </p>



<p><a href="https://mtchl.net/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prof Mitchell Whitelaw</a> and <a href="https://researchportalplus.anu.edu.au/en/persons/adrian-mackenzie" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Prof Adrian Mackenzie</a> from the <a href="https://www.anu.edu.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Australian National University</a> (ANU)</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure></div>


<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[geoff.egan@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Nov 2024 03:27:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50098</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out ALA&#8217;s November 2024 newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Check out <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/nov-2024-newsletter">ALA&#8217;s November 2024 newsletter</a>. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image is-resized is-style-default"><a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/nov-2024-newsletter"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1272" height="1160" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2.png" alt="ALA's November 2024 newsletter header banner - it includes the ALA logo and a dried wattle specimen, and a welcome message" class="wp-image-50104" style="width:1450px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2.png 1272w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2-300x274.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2-1024x934.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/11/newsletterq4-shot2-768x700.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1272px) 100vw, 1272px" /></a></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; November 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/newsletter/directors-update-november-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[geoff.egan@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 05:16:19 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[directors update]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[GBIF]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50093</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the November 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter. I recently had the pleasure of representing Australia at the 31st meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facilities (GBIF) Governing Boarding hosted in Vairao, Vila do Conde Portugal. The event brings together close to 100 international partners that contribute to the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="719" height="938" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48109" style="width:251px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger-230x300.png 230w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 719px) 100vw, 719px" /></figure></div>


<p>Welcome to the November 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>I recently had the pleasure of representing Australia at the 31st meeting of the <a href="https://gb31.gbif.org/" data-type="link" data-id="https://gb31.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facilities (GBIF) Governing Boarding</a> hosted in Vairao, Vila do Conde Portugal. The event brings together close to 100 international partners that contribute to the network both strategically, and through the provision of biodiversity data and related services. For the ALA this event is critical as it allows us to benchmark our strategic priorities, contextualise our annual workplan against partner priorities, and ultimately engage with our partners to realise technical efficiencies. For example, the planned implementation of GBIF’s unified data model can directly support ALA’s efforts to improve the interoperability of more complex biodiversity data emerging from our partners, including from <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-exploring-next-gen-biodiversity-detection-technologies/">eDNA, camera trap, and ecoacoustic-based monitoring</a>.</p>



<p>Some of the key themes to emerge from the 2024 Governing Board meeting included the establishment of Convention on Biological Diversity (CBD) Regional Centres and the potential role of biodiversity data infrastructure, improving our collective approach to Indigenous data governance, expansion of the Data4Nature program potentially into Asia and the Pacific, embedding Environment, Sustainability, and Governance (ESG) principles into the operation of research infrastructure, and importantly the critical role of research infrastructure in supporting international biodiversity policy programs, given the meeting preceded the COP16 meeting in Colombia by a few weeks. <a href="https://www.gbif.org/event/4PLhy0XlJHGFLvH6rb4KmM/cop-16-sixteenth-meeting-of-the-parties-to-the-convention-of-biological-diversity">GBIF had a strong presence at COP16</a>, highlighting the fundamental role data can play in not only supporting policy formulation, but also informing priorities.</p>



<p>As GBIF’s largest national node, ALA continues to play an important global leadership role that is valued across the network. There are opportunities to strengthen this by more actively partnering with GBIF around aligned technical projects and improving our engagement with the international biodiversity data infrastructure community. Elements of this have already commenced, with the ALA recently taking on the leadership role for two years for the Oceania Regional Node, and jointly hosting a <a href="https://www.gbif.org/event/jxlmvxokGDXhOpN1fNpwn/oceania-regional-nodes-meeting-or-engagement-meeting-for-bid-pacific">regional node meeting with New Zealand in October</a>.</p>



<p>It was a great meeting, with an engaged network of member nations working to a common goal to make biodiversity data more interoperable and accessible.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy reading our November 2024 Newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director.</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
