<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 21:48:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Delivering data to improve reporting on Australia&#8217;s environment</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/delivering-data-to-improve-reporting-on-australias-environment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 21:48:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45791</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Australia’s national research infrastructures are working together to streamline access to integrated data for State of the Environment reporting and other environmental assessments. The collaborative project is ensuring easy, open access to comparable, time-series datasets for key measures of the state of Australia’s environment and biodiversity.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:24px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/_5DBOq9YB-io5hFIFp6nCV9Ko1Y6Jt8H0XrjKuSE6QfIRc-_QbfN_10bdXIsB8HbFK5KdD22hBrMXRyYwsEcKUJq8jMXaxHVFIOCOexaUQwVj0a-NevAgM1AoYjBPs7WRNVzzajO" alt="illustrated flowchart of observations to datasets" width="302" height="453"/></figure></div>



<p>Every five years, the Australian Government delivers the State of the Environment (SoE) report, a review of how Australia’s environment is being affected by changing pressures on land and marine areas and how these changes will impact the economy and society.</p>



<p>Australian research infrastructures and their data partners collect massive amounts of data each year on all aspects of the environment, but this information does not feed readily into the processes that support reporting at the national scale or in each State and Territory.</p>



<p>To address this, four National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) research infrastructure projects are working with the Australian Government Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (DAWE) to deliver integrated data for future SoE reporting and other environmental assessments.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="comprehensive-environmental-monitoring-data">Comprehensive environmental monitoring data</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), Integrated Marine Observing System (IMOS), and Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network (TERN) collect and collate data on Australia’s environment and maintain metadata on environmental survey and monitoring activities.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Through the new <a href="http://doi.org/10.47486/XN005">EcoAssets</a> project they are partnering with the Australian Research Data Commons (ARDC) to share these resources in standard formats as integrated data assets, making them directly available to SoE reporting through the ARDC’s data publishing service, <a href="https://researchdata.edu.au/">Research Data Australia</a>.</p>



<p>EcoAssets is also identifying opportunities to increase alignment between data from all partners, in particular to simplify spatio-temporal analysis and to address differences in terminology and vocabularies.</p>



<p>The research infrastructures will operationalise EcoAssets data pipelines so that each data asset developed by the project can be updated at regular intervals, ensuring that SoE reporting and similar processes will have access to comparable time series for key measures of the state of Australia’s environment and biodiversity.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>&#8220;Australia is home to many world-leading environmental researchers and ALA, ARDC, TERN and IMOS play important national roles in both helping their research through access to data and through providing their data to help our managers plan for the future.</em><br><br><em>The EcoAssets project will streamline the flow of data and knowledge from Australia’s national research infrastructures into SoE reporting by creating structured, automated data pathways and useful data products and visualisations.&nbsp;</em><br><br><em>Our vision is for SoE reporting to become more efficient and, most importantly, more accurate as we incorporate more and more of the nation&#8217;s environmental data. I am certain that this project lays the foundation for future SoE reports to benefit greatly from the ongoing digital updates resulting from the EcoAssets project.&#8221;</em><br><br><em>Dr Ian Cresswell, Co-Chief Author, 2021 National State of the Environment Report</em></p></blockquote>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/P_UtH8CGeuV-ne9znHeuPu2PucFB9kYDS1Ekk95mq8M-Sh4FLCzzRFtTj1SN8kBgZ3_YmIFdB1MC3CdJxBL2bSkXrzyCT7MKG4AI666aHpRZakKv_nXVcRlleFswinfJFAwJz9yO" alt="map of Australia showing occurrence, monitoring and station locations (land and sea)"/><figcaption><em>Environmental survey and monitoring activities 2016-2020 from the Atlas of Living Australia, Integrated Marine Observing System and Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network</em>.</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="integrated-datasets-for-better-reporting">Integrated datasets for better reporting&nbsp;</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>EcoAssets will focus on two cross-infrastructure data assets.</p>



<ol><li><strong>Integrated species distribution</strong> data asset updated regularly with new data collected by all three infrastructures. IMOS collects data on marine communities around Australia’s reefs and tracks individual animals via tags and acoustic telemetry. TERN conducts a wide range of site-based surveys from which species distribution data can be extracted. These will be combined with other sources of species distribution data aggregated by the ALA.</li></ol>



<ol start="2"><li><strong>Integrated survey and monitoring activity</strong> data asset collating the survey effort applied towards understanding different aspects of the Australian environment. Combined, TERN and IMOS maintain a wide range of fixed and mobile monitoring infrastructure and collect data and metadata by undertaking time series site-based surveys. The ALA also collates data from standardised biodiversity surveys, including published project metadata. These sources will all be mapped and organised using a common vocabulary to facilitate comparison of survey effort across time and space.</li></ol>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>“One of the challenges in compiling State of the Environment Report chapters is that studies are often place-based, meaning that compiling a truly national picture requires integrating separate studies, often conducted using different methods, and with gaps between them. </em><br><br><em>EcoAssets will make it simpler to obtain national perspectives, with all of the underpinning data available for scrutiny or re-analysis, ensuring users can have confidence in the summary reports presented.”</em><br><br><em>Dr Dan Metcalfe, CSIRO and State of the Environment report 2016 &amp; 2021 chapter author</em></p></blockquote>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>The EcoAssets data collection is intended as a launchpad for discovery and access to other nationally significant environmental data assets. Once the data collection pipelines for EcoAssets are created, they will be opened to other national environmental information holders, including national research infrastructures, state and federal agencies, non-governmental organisations and more.</p>



<p>Bringing these resources into a common framework will encourage increased reuse and standardisation, as well as providing a valuable resource for researchers, government decision makers and evidence-based policy.</p>



<h2 id="more-information">More information</h2>



<ul><li>View the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/21331-ALA-EcoAssets-Info-Sheet-V5_final.pdf"><strong>EcoAssets brochure</strong></a></li><li>Discover ALA <a href="https://collections.ala.org.au/datasets"><strong>data collections</strong></a></li><li>Discover IMOS <a href="https://portal.aodn.org.au/"><strong>data collections</strong></a></li><li>Discover TERN <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/data/"><strong>data collections</strong></a></li><li>For reference, the full title of this project is “Ecosystem data integration to support national environmental reporting (State of the Environment)” (doi.org/10.47486/XN005)</li></ul>



<div style="height:25px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="the-partners">The Partners&nbsp;</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>In partnership with the Australian Research Data Commons (ARDC), the <a href="http://doi.org/10.47486/XN005">EcoAssets project</a> will build data linkages between three world-leading research infrastructures funded under Australia’s National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS).</p>



<p><a href="http://ala.org.au">The Atlas of Living Australia</a> (ALA) harmonises occurrence records of Australian plant and animal species, bringing together data from labels on museum and herbaria specimens,</p>



<p>field surveys, citizen science observations, molecular sequencing and literature.</p>



<p>The<a href="https://imos.org.au/"> Integrated Marine Observing System</a> (IMOS) collects observations and measurements of ocean conditions, species and habitats from the open ocean to coastal waters. These high-quality ocean observations help monitor marine ecosystems, define patterns and trends, and address challenges facing our marine estate.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">The Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network</a> (TERN) monitors changes over time in the biodiversity of Australia&#8217;s terrestrial ecosystems by consistently measuring essential biodiversity and climate variables at continental, regional and site scales.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/">Australian Research Data Commons</a> (ARDC) enables the Australian research community and industry access to nationally significant, data intensive digital research infrastructure, platforms, skills and collections of high quality data.</p>



<p>These infrastructures are working with the Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (DAWE) to ensure that their data combine to meet the needs for future SoE and other national monitoring and assessment processes.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 02:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45759</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter November 2021]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ALA-newsletter-November-2021_2.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/thumbnail-889x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45760" width="405" height="467" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/thumbnail-889x1024.png 889w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/thumbnail-260x300.png 260w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/thumbnail-768x885.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/thumbnail.png 1161w" sizes="(max-width: 405px) 100vw, 405px" /></a></figure>



<p></p>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ALA-newsletter-November-2021_2.pdf">ALA Newsletter November 2021</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Message from our Director &#8211; November 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/message-from-our-director-november-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Nov 2021 22:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45729</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the November 2021 edition of our newsletter&#160; The importance of investing in fundamental research infrastructure&#160;such as the ALA&#160;to support unanticipated science and decision-making needs has been highlighted so effectively in a fantastic body of work led by the National Environmental Science Programme’s Threatened Species Recovery Hub&#160;in&#160;their report titled&#160;Assessment of the impacts of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Welcome to the November 2021 edition of our newsletter&nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.nespthreatenedspecies.edu.au/publications-and-tools/assessment-of-the-impacts-of-the-2019-20-wildfires-of-southern-and-eastern-australia-on-invertebrate-species-final-report"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/TSR-Hub-repoert-Oct-2021.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45730" width="224" height="183" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/TSR-Hub-repoert-Oct-2021.png 793w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/TSR-Hub-repoert-Oct-2021-300x245.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/TSR-Hub-repoert-Oct-2021-768x627.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/TSR-Hub-repoert-Oct-2021-790x647.png 790w" sizes="(max-width: 224px) 100vw, 224px" /></a><figcaption>National Environmental Science Programme’s Threatened Species Recovery Hub report <em><a href="https://www.nespthreatenedspecies.edu.au/publications-and-tools/assessment-of-the-impacts-of-the-2019-20-wildfires-of-southern-and-eastern-australia-on-invertebrate-species-final-report">Assessment of the impacts of the 2019-20 wildfires of southern and eastern Australia on invertebrate species&nbsp;final report (Marsh et al 2021)</a></em></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>The importance of investing in fundamental research infrastructure&nbsp;such as the ALA&nbsp;to support unanticipated science and decision-making needs has been highlighted so effectively in a fantastic body of work led by the National Environmental Science Programme’s Threatened Species Recovery Hub&nbsp;in&nbsp;their report titled&nbsp;<em>Assessment of the impacts of the 2019-20 wildfires of southern and eastern Australia on invertebrate species&nbsp;final report (Marsh et al 2021).</em></p>



<p>Although the study identifies some&nbsp;notable&nbsp;data gaps with respect to our understanding of the occurrence and distribution of Australian invertebrates, it also&nbsp;effectively&nbsp;highlights the&nbsp;richness&nbsp;of analysis that is now possible&nbsp;at regional scales in Australia – this includes instant access to some of the world’s most comprehensive biodiversity data, combined with world-class ecological modelling capability, and deep science understanding with respect to species risk and conservation planning. The recommendations and future directions&nbsp;parts are&nbsp;a must read and&nbsp;have&nbsp;already started to shape some of our&nbsp;strategic thinking in the ALA.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>With that study in-mind we are excited to profile a new partnership the ALA has established with the Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (DAWE) around three innovative citizen science projects to enhance our understanding of how Australia’s biodiversity respond to fire, and ultimately to support species recovery from bushfire impacts. The project is supported by the Australian Government’s Bushfire Recovery Program for Wildlife and their Habitat. One project is engaging members of the public to help digitise data from CSIRO’s Australian National Insect Collection using DigiVol, the Australian Museum and ALA supported digitisation platform. Many of the specimens being digitised by volunteers have few or no occurrence records in the ALA thereby starting to address some of the data gaps identified in the NESP study.  </p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-Citizen-Science-V4.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45496" width="210" height="290"/></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-Citizen-Science-V4.pdf">Download Bushfire recovery projects impact case study</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Why connect these two projects? Collectively they highlight that Australia does have the component parts to build a truly comprehensive, adequate and representative national biodiversity data capability. The combination of world class ecological science and taxonomic expertise, the passion and skill of volunteers and the infrastructure to support data mobilisation and integration through the ALA and DigiVol places Australia in a remarkable position to connect these elements in a more strategic manner. Improving these connections is indeed one of the frontiers we hope to explore further in coming years.  </p>



<p>I hope you enjoy reading&nbsp;our November newsletter.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Dr Andre&nbsp;Zerger&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Citation</strong>: Marsh, J., Bal, P., Fraser, H., Umbers, K., Greenville, A.,&nbsp;Rumpff, L.,&nbsp;Woinarski, J., 2021. Assessment of the impacts of the 2019-20 wildfires of&nbsp;southern and eastern Australia on invertebrate species. NESP Threatened Species Recovery Hub Project 8.3.1 Final report, Brisbane.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ESA Conference 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/esa-conference-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 01:08:28 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45549</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As we prepare for ESA2021 'Renewal', we share some insights from four ALA presenters: Jessica Fenker, Nat Raisbeck-Brown, Donald Hobern and Dax Kellie. We also hear about the exciting work of our friends at EcoCommons.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:24px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>This year marks the 61st Annual Conference of the Ecological Society of Australia, held on 22-26 November. A key event attended by hundreds of Australian ecologists, it is a great opportunity to hear about the latest ecological research happening around the country. This year the conference will be held online; you can visit the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://esa2021.org.au/" target="_blank">ESA2021 website</a> to learn more.</p>



<p>Several members of the ALA team will be presenting at the conference this year, and we couldn&#8217;t be prouder of their achievements! We can&#8217;t give away any spoilers from their presentations, so we decided to interview them instead. Here Jess, Nat, Dax and Donald share a little about their work and why they do what they do. </p>



<div style="height:50px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Jess-EcoCommons.png" alt="Dr Jessica Fenker" class="wp-image-45608" width="200" height="200" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Jess-EcoCommons.png 237w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Jess-EcoCommons-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>



<h2 id="jessica-fenker-ala-ecocommons"><strong>Jessica Fenker</strong> (ALA &amp;&nbsp;EcoCommons)</h2>



<h3 id="a-life-in-tropical-savannas-patterns-of-ecomorphological-diversification-on-independent-squamate-radiations"><strong>A life in&nbsp;tropical savannas –&nbsp;patterns of ecomorphological diversification on&nbsp;independent squamate&nbsp;radiations&nbsp;</strong></h3>



<p>Presenting on Monday, 22 November 2021.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>How would you describe your work?</strong></p>



<p>Reptiles are the most diverse group of vertebrates, with a huge variety of body forms, and occurring from cold mountain-tops to the sea. But what promotes this incredible diversity? In my work, I investigate the principal factors that shape the adaptation and diversification of reptiles at multiple dimensions, ranging from speciation processes, to variations in morphology, ecology and genetic diversity.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p class="has-text-align-left"><strong>What made you pursue this kind of work?</strong></p>



<p>I’ve always loved reptiles and wanted to learn more about them, including their great diversity, as well as help in their conservation. I’m also very interested in studying questions around climate variation given our rapidly changing environment. I’ve been fortunate to be able to combine these interests as reptiles, as well as being amazing creatures, are an excellent model of study for the questions I am interested in ­– as ectotherms, they are sensitive to climate variation in space and time.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Morelia_viridis.jpeg" alt="Morelia viridis, a green tree python - juvenile (yellow)" class="wp-image-45618" width="559" height="521" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Morelia_viridis.jpeg 811w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Morelia_viridis-300x280.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Morelia_viridis-768x717.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 559px) 100vw, 559px" /><figcaption><em>Morelia viridis</em> (Green Python) – juvenile. Photo by Jessica Fenker.</figcaption></figure></div>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What is your role at the ALA, and what do you do?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>I am an R programmer, working on code to generate models that relate species distribution and environmental variables. These kinds of analyses are essential for a few reasons. Firstly, it helps scientists better understand why species live where they do, and secondly, this helps in decision-making – for how and where to prioritise conservation.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Is there something in particular at the ESA conference you’re looking forward to this year?</strong></p>



<p>My colleagues from EcoCommons and I will be presenting one of our first public workshops – so I’m very much looking forward to meeting and interacting with everyone in attendance!</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Could you please share one fun fact with our readers?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Australia has the highest diversity of reptiles in the world, with more than 1,109 species! We have over one million reptile occurrence records in the ALA, representing 1,078 of these species.</p>



<div style="height:50px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="200" height="200" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Nat-sizedforweb.png" alt="Nat Raisbeck-Brown" class="wp-image-45706" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Nat-sizedforweb.png 200w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Nat-sizedforweb-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>



<h2 id="nat-raisbeck-brown-indigenous-ecological-knowledge-program-lead-ala">Nat Raisbeck-Brown (Indigenous Ecological Knowledge Program Lead, ALA)<br></h2>



<p></p>



<p>At ESA2021, Nat is presenting with Lynette Knapp, Gail Yorkshire, and Denise Smith-Ali from the Noongar Boodjar Language Centre.  </p>



<h3 id="linking-indigenous-ecological-knowledge-to-western-science-through-language"><strong>Linking Indigenous ecological knowledge to western science through language</strong></h3>



<p>Presenting on Tuesday, 23 November 2021.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>How would you describe your work?</strong></p>



<p>One of our recent projects with Noongar Boodjar Language Centre in Perth is the creation of the Noongar-Wudjari Plant and Animal Online Encyclopedia. Noongar-Wudjari is in the south-west corner of Western Australia. Working specifically with Wudjari knowledge holders – Lynette Knapp and Gail Yorkshire – this project involves recording ancestral language and knowledge about plants and animals, to preserve and share. Knowledge and language records for over 90 plants and animals have been collected and are now ready for publication through the ALA.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What made you pursue this kind of work?</strong></p>



<p>I am a map maker. I fell in love with the ALA when I started using the spatial portal to show the relationships between plants, animals and place. I was constantly calling the ALA to ask to show it off at schools and workshops – finally they reneged and based on my extensive work with Aboriginal communities in the Kimberley and fire mapping, offered me the position to lead the IEK. I feel incredibly honoured to be doing this work, with the amazing people I work with in community and the ALA, and to be sharing this knowledge that helps bridge the gap between traditional and western science and ultimately improves our management of our land and sea.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Screen-Shot-2021-11-12-at-4.50.18-pm.png" alt="Baardi (genus Endoxyla) from an Acacia tree" class="wp-image-45623" width="756" height="529" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Screen-Shot-2021-11-12-at-4.50.18-pm.png 505w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Screen-Shot-2021-11-12-at-4.50.18-pm-300x210.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 756px) 100vw, 756px" /><figcaption>Baardi (genus <em>Endoxyla</em>) from an Acacia tree. Image courtesy of Noongar Boodjar Language Centre.</figcaption></figure></div>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What is your role at the ALA, and what do you do?</strong></p>



<p>I lead the ALA’s Indigenous Ecological Knowledge (IEK) program. The aim of the IEK program is to promote Indigenous ecological knowledge in the ALA. I am doing this by working with Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander communities to include their language and knowledge in the ALA where it directly links to the Western science knowledge for plants and animals. While I lead the IEK program within the ALA each project with each community is co-led and co-designed with our Partner Researchers &#8211; people and organisations who are working directly with communities to collect, store and protect Indigenous language and ecological knowledge about plants and animals. My role is to facilitate the flow of knowledge into the ALA from our Partner Researchers and work with the ALA to ensure the communities goals and aspirations around sharing their language and knowledge are being met.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Is there something in particular at the ESA conference you’re looking forward to this year?</strong></p>



<p>I am excited to share this work with ecologists and environmental scientists from around Australia as an integral step in accessing all the knowledge we need to look after our environment. I am very pleased to be standing with the Noongar-Wudjari knowledge holders, Lynette Knapp and Gail Yorkshire, and our Noongar Partner Researcher and senior linguist, Denise Smith-Ali, as they present our work and explain why this is important to them, their families, their communities and the public.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Could you please share one fun fact with our readers?</strong></p>



<p>The ALA now has Indigenous language names listed for over 700 species, in 12 languages.</p>



<p></p>



<div style="height:50px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-1024x1024.jpg" alt="Dr Dax Kellie" class="wp-image-45567" width="200" height="200" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-2048x2048.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/dax-1920x1920.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>



<h2 id="dax-kellie-ala"><strong>Dax Kellie</strong> (ALA)</h2>



<h3 id="the-changing-shape-of-data-in-the-atlas-of-living-australia"><strong>The changing shape of data in the Atlas of Living Australia</strong></h3>



<p>Presenting on Tuesday, 23 November 2021.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>How would you describe your work ?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>I&nbsp;am a&nbsp;data analyst in the Science and Decision Support team within the ALA. I work to improve the ALA’s scientific transparency and to help researchers, government and public users access and analyse data&nbsp;in the ALA&nbsp;more easily.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What made you pursue this kind of work?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>I was lucky enough to get an opportunity working with some exceptional scientists&nbsp;last year&nbsp;on a paper investigating&nbsp;how much&nbsp;the methods and the environment&nbsp;in which an ecological&nbsp;experiment is conducted&nbsp;affect the&nbsp;experiment’s&nbsp;final results. This work reinvigorated my love of ecology and biology after spending several years researching human behaviour.&nbsp;Over my&nbsp;PhD, I also&nbsp;grew passionate about&nbsp;learning how to conduct&nbsp;open&nbsp;and&nbsp;reproducible&nbsp;science (which is much harder than you might think). So,&nbsp;when the&nbsp;ALA was&nbsp;searching&nbsp;for someone&nbsp;to help&nbsp;improve&nbsp;their&nbsp;scientific practices, I was excited and thankful to be chosen to fill the role!&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What is your role at the ALA, and what do you do?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Improving scientific practices can mean a number of things: facilitating&nbsp;that&nbsp;robust statistical methods&nbsp;are used, creating clear documentation&nbsp;of workflows, or&nbsp;even&nbsp;helping the ALA’s scientific outreach. Day-to-day, my role includes things like managing the latest {galah} R package, creating data visualisations&nbsp;for&nbsp;government-funded projects&nbsp;or social media, and providing advice on&nbsp;how ALA data can be used in&nbsp;high-quality, reproducible&nbsp;research.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Ideally, what I do helps to&nbsp;make the ALA closer and more supportive to the scientific research community, as well as&nbsp;more scientifically engaging&nbsp;to the&nbsp;broader&nbsp;userbase of the&nbsp;ALA.&nbsp;</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-1024x636.png" alt="chart showing occurrence data records per state of Australia" class="wp-image-45575" width="982" height="610" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-1024x636.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-300x186.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-768x477.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-1536x954.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-2048x1271.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Dax-seasonal-blobs-plot-1-1920x1192.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 982px) 100vw, 982px" /><figcaption>Figure: Time of the year that each state recorded the most species occurrence records, on average, from 2010 to 2021. For each state, the number of records are highest where the coloured shape reaches closest to the edge of the circle. Created by Dax Kellie.</figcaption></figure></div>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Is there something in particular at the ESA conference you’re looking forward to this year?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>There is a general push&nbsp;across&nbsp;Australia&nbsp;in research and industry&nbsp;to better understand the management of, and restoration&nbsp;after, bushfires. I&nbsp;am&nbsp;excited to hear more about what the scientific community has learned now that we are nearly two years on from the huge 2020 bushfires.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There are also several talks and a workshop on Indigenous ecological knowledge and improving work with Indigenous land managers. This kind of research is&nbsp;invaluable, both in the context of getting better data&nbsp;coverage on&nbsp;Australian&nbsp;wildlife, and in a broader context of understanding&nbsp;ecological interactions&nbsp;more holistically.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Could you please share one fun fact with our readers?&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Birds are the most&nbsp;well-recorded species across the board in the ALA – the top 10 species recorded in the ALA are all birds. The top 3 birds&nbsp;–&nbsp;Magpies, Ducks and Fairy-wrens – have had&nbsp;over 800,000 occurrence records added&nbsp;over the last decade.&nbsp;That’s a lot of records!&nbsp;</p>



<p>Even more impressive is that&nbsp;over 95% of the records added for birds last year were from eBird. That’s not a bad thing &#8211; recent research found that, compared to iNaturalist, eBird&nbsp;is less biased towards larger, more detectable bird species&nbsp;thanks to their use of a&nbsp;semi-structured data format.&nbsp;Thanks for all your hard work eBird users!&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:50px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/donald_hobern.webp" alt="Donald Hobern" class="wp-image-45695" width="200" height="200" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/donald_hobern.webp 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/donald_hobern-150x150.webp 150w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></figure></div>



<h2 id="donald-hobern-ala"><strong>Donald Hobern</strong> (ALA)</h2>



<h3 id="ecoassets-research-data-for-environmental-indicators"><strong>EcoAssets: Research data for environmental indicators</strong></h3>



<p>Presenting on Tuesday, 23 November 2021. </p>



<p><strong>How would you describe your work?</strong></p>



<p>My work is all about trying to make it easier for anyone (researchers, citizen scientists, policy-makers, etc.) to find quality data on biodiversity in ways that make their lives easier, help them to answer the questions they care about, and contribute to a more sustainable world. See this paper for the big picture:&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.7.e33679" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.7.e33679</a></p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What made you pursue this kind of work?</strong></p>



<p>I was always passionate about natural history and would probably have drifted into zoology if I hadn&#8217;t dropped chemistry early because my teacher graded exclusively on neatness and handwriting&#8230; As it was, I ended up becoming a software engineer. In my mid-30s, the establishment of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (<a href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF</a>) in Copenhagen gave me the chance to use my career skills to work with biodiversity data.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What is your role at the ALA, and what do you do?</strong></p>



<p>My current role with the ALA is as leader for a partnership project with some of the ALA&#8217;s sister infrastructures (the Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network, the Integrated Marine Observing System and the Australian Research Commons) to organise our data in ways that better support environmental assessment processes. We want our data to be easily accessible in ways that support indicators for tracking change.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Is there something in particular at the ESA conference you’re looking forward to this year?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>I&#8217;m looking forward to some of the big perspectives, particularly through the keynote presentations.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Could you please share one fun fact with our readers?&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>We are living on the brink of a new age for biodiversity monitoring – cheap cameras and computer hardware, open-source software, and machine learning will make automated field observations possible (<a href="https://amt.hobern.net/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://amt.hobern.net/</a>) and cheap high-speed DNA sequencing will help us understand the distribution and interactions of all species (<a href="https://araba.hobern.net/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://araba.hobern.net/</a>).&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:50px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="jessica-fenker-ala-ecocommons-jenna-wraith-ala-ecocommons"><strong>Jessica Fenker </strong>(ALA &amp;&nbsp;EcoCommons) &amp; <strong>Jenna Wraith </strong>(ALA &amp;&nbsp;EcoCommons) </h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ecocommons-logo.png" alt="EcoCommons logo" class="wp-image-45563" width="332" height="48" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ecocommons-logo.png 760w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ecocommons-logo-300x43.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 332px) 100vw, 332px" /></figure></div>



<p>At ESA2021, Jess and Jenna are hosting two workshops with Emilia Decker<strong> </strong>(EcoCommons)<strong>.</strong><br></p>



<h3 id="workshop-1-a-beginners-guide-to-data-analysis-and-visualisation-in-r-for-ecologists-in-the-ecocommons-cloud"><strong>Workshop 1. A&nbsp;beginners&nbsp;guide to Data Analysis and&nbsp;Visualisation&nbsp;in R for Ecologists in the&nbsp;EcoCommons’ cloud</strong></h3>



<h3 id="workshop-2-using-the-ecocommons-platform-to-run-species-distribution-models-and-make-climate-projections"><strong>Workshop 2. Using the&nbsp;EcoCommons&nbsp;platform to run species distribution models and make climate projections</strong></h3>



<p>Workshops will run on Wednesday, 24 November 2021.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>How would you describe your work?</strong></p>



<p>We will be hosting two introductory workshops on coding in R using EcoCommons’ coding environment, and a further workshop on species distribution modelling and climate projections using simple point-and-click tools. ESA2021 attendees will work through the improved functionality drawn from the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://ecocloud.org.au/">ecocloud</a>&nbsp;and the Biodiversity and Climate Change Virtual Laboratory (<a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://bccvl.org.au/">BCCVL</a>) platforms which are migrating to EcoCommons. There will be several additions to EcoCommons over the next 12 months, with the official launch on track for next year’s conference, ESA2022.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>What do you find most exciting about this kind of work?&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>The&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.ecocommons.org.au/">EcoCommons</a>&nbsp;online platform is a world-first! We are creating a collaborative space that’s highly-trusted; a single platform for environmental modelling and analysis needs. By doing so, we are aiming to empower researchers and practitioners with access to trusted datasets and high-quality modelling tools. Ultimately, this means better and faster conservation outcomes for our Aussie species.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Could you please share one fun fact with our readers?&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>Each EcoCommons team member has a superhero name and you can help these superheros develop EcoCommons over the next year.&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank" href="https://app.vision6.com.au/em/forms/subscribe.php?db=700840&amp;s=465756&amp;a=99641&amp;k=AqwBguvZDujLdAYLYZ3a52BVktepioIWo3_L0ocb-ms">Sign up</a>&nbsp;to become an EcoCommons Pioneer and help shape the platform as it evolves.</p>



<div style="height:57px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA update: Getting to know you better</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-update-getting-to-know-you-better/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 05:00:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45652</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In October 2021, we introduced a feature to the ALA that requests information from registered users about the type of organisation they’re affiliated with e.g. university, government, education etc. Now when new users first create their account with the ALA, they will be asked to pick the type of organisation they are affiliated with from [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-1024x1024.png" alt="ALA logo" class="wp-image-44280" width="258" height="258" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-150x150.png 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-768x768.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-1536x1536.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1-1920x1920.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/ALA_Logo_Stacked_RGB-2048x2048-1.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 258px) 100vw, 258px" /></figure></div>



<p>In October 2021, we introduced a feature to the ALA that requests information from registered users about the type of organisation they’re affiliated with e.g. university, government, education etc.</p>



<p>Now when new users first create their account with the ALA, they will be asked to pick the type of organisation they are affiliated with from a set list.</p>



<p>The list includes 18 options including University researcher, Museum/herbarium/library, Government, Industry, Volunteer, and more.</p>



<p>Options of&nbsp;<em>Other</em>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<em>Prefer not to say</em>&nbsp;are given if users either can’t find a category they fit into or don’t wish to divulge the information.</p>



<p>Returning users will be asked, just once when they next log in, to pick their organisation affiliation.</p>



<p>All users can edit their profile to update their institutional affiliation (and the other data) anytime they’re logged in. For more information on how to do this, read our help article <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000195200-how-do-i-manage-the-settings-for-my-account-">How do I manage the settings for my account?</a></p>



<h3 id="why-the-change"><strong>Why the change?</strong><strong></strong></h3>



<p>The ALA has been asked to gather this information by our principal funding body, <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS).</a></p>



<p>We will be asked to aggregate and report on the data every 6 months. The report won’t be associated at all with individual user logins and no personal information will be provided in the report – just a total count for each user type.</p>



<h3 id="more-information"><strong>More information</strong><strong></strong></h3>



<p>If you have any questions or would like more information please contact <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CoralWatch launches new database</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/coralwatch-launches-new-database/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 03:52:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45629</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Renowned citizen science program CoralWatch launched their new database using the ALA's Biocollect field data collection platform.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="321" height="157" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Coral-watch-logo.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45630" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Coral-watch-logo.jpg 321w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Coral-watch-logo-300x147.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 321px) 100vw, 321px" /></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p>CoralWatch is a not-for-profit organisation based at The University of Queensland. It is a globally significant citizen science program that started in 2002. It aims to involve anyone (divers, students, scientists and tourists) in monitoring coral colour to help us understand more about coral health and bleaching events.</p>



<p>CoralWatch creates simple and engaging tools to help citizen scientists monitor global coral health and raises awareness of our reefs via education and public outreach programs.</p>



<h3 id="collecting-valuable-data-about-coral-health"><strong>Collecting valuable data about coral health</strong> </h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002-1024x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45631" width="254" height="254" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002-150x150.png 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002-768x768.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002-1536x1536.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-health-chart-biocollect-and-ala-logos-002.png 1656w" sizes="(max-width: 254px) 100vw, 254px" /><figcaption>The CoralWatch Health Chart is a tool to help citizen scientists collect data about the colour and coral type.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Through CoralWatch people help collect scientific data on coral bleaching by using the Coral Health Chart. The chart is an easy-to-use tool to quantify changes in coral colour associated with coral bleaching on our reefs.</p>



<p>The colours on the Coral Health Chart are based on the actual colours of bleached and healthy corals. Each colour square corresponds to the concentration of symbiotic algae living in the coral tissue, which is directly linked to coral health. For more information, visit <a href="https://coralwatch.org/index.php/monitoring/using-the-chart/">Using the coral health chart</a></p>



<p>The chart is used in the field and classroom, is available in 12 languages and data on more than 2,500 reefs in 81 countries is publicly accessible.</p>



<h3 id="updating-the-coralwatch-database"><strong>Updating the CoralWatch database</strong></h3>



<p>After almost 20 years of operation the CoralWatch team needed to update the global database and partnered with the <a href="https://www.qcif.edu.au/about-us/who-we-are/">Queensland Cyber Infrastructure Foundation (QCIF)</a> and the Atlas of Living Australia to find a solution.</p>



<p>The BioCollect platform is a customisable field data collection tool and proved a good base to build the new CoralWatch database. The QCIF team developed new code to display graphs for the CoralWatch database and the ALA provided technical support and is hosting the database. The new graphs feature is now available to other users of the platform too.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45725" width="371" height="278" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/coral-watch-chart-in-water-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" /><figcaption>The CoralWatch Health Chart is used by citizen scientists around the world to collect data on the health of our reefs.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>All historical data (almost 15,000 reef visits and more than 320,000 coral observations) was imported to BioCollect. The new database can support images and record verification. It will also be able to cope with the growing data storage needs of the CoralWatch project.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Since the launch of the database (28 September 2021), already 223 surveys have been entered by divers and snorkelers all over the world, including 109 surveys in Australia and 114 surveys from Thailand, Honduras, Taiwan, Northern Mariana Islands, Indonesia, and Egypt.</p>



<h3 id="more-information"><strong>More information</strong></h3>



<ul><li>For more information on CoralWatch, visit <a href="https://coralwatch.org/">https://coralwatch.org/</a></li><li>For more details on our BioCollect data collection platform, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QEr6VULLZks">view our BioCollect video</a>.</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Australian Plant Pest Database (APPD) update</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/australian-plant-pest-database-appd-update/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 04 Nov 2021 03:02:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45535</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The&#160;Australian&#160;Plant&#160;Pest&#160;Database (APPD) will be transitioning to a new site (www.appd.net.au) on Monday 8 November 2021. &#160; &#160; Existing users must register on the new site to gain access to APPD. This document provides detailed instructions that will assist you when requesting access and logging into the site for the first time:  How to access the Australian Plant Pest [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Plant-Health-Australia.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45537" width="313" height="75"/></figure></div>



<p>The&nbsp;Australian&nbsp;Plant&nbsp;Pest&nbsp;Database (APPD) will be transitioning to a new site (<a href="http://www.appd.net.au/">www.appd.net.au</a>) on Monday 8 November 2021. &nbsp; &nbsp;</p>



<p>Existing users must register on the new site to gain access to APPD. This document provides detailed instructions that will assist you when requesting access and logging into the site for the first time: </p>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Requesting-access-to-APPD.pdf">How to access the Australian Plant Pest Database</a></p>



<p>To assist with using the site, a user guide is also provided on the <a href="http://www.appd.net.au/">APPD home page</a>. </p>



<p>APPD collates information on vouchered pest and plant pathogen specimens from herbaria and insect collections from across Australia. The purpose of APPD is to support market access and inform government policy decision making. Sensitive data is housed in APPD and the data is not to be shared with others.</p>



<p>If you have any queries about APPD, please email <a href="mailto:appd@phau.com.au?subject=APPD%20update">appd@phau.com.au</a>.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bushfire recovery projects: Increasing our understanding of how nature responds to fire</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/bushfire-recovery-projects-increasing-our-understanding-of-how-nature-responds-to-fire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:06:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45495</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and the Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (DAWE) are working together on three new innovative citizen projects to enhance our understanding of how Australia’s biodiversity responds to fire and supports bushfire recovery. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-Citizen-Science-V4.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45496" width="220" height="308" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail.png 644w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail-214x300.png 214w" sizes="(max-width: 220px) 100vw, 220px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-Citizen-Science-V4.pdf">View and print this impact case study as a pdf</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p><br>The citizen science bushfire recovery projects enable people to connect with nature and science while collecting and processing crucial data for scientists and governments to use in bushfire research and recovery. This work is supported by the Australian Government’s $200 million Bushfire Recovery Program for Wildlife and their Habitat.</p>



<p>“We were pleased to partner with the Atlas of Living Australia for this important community focused work. The three projects will support fire-affected communities to re-engage with nature and the science of recovery. Citizen scientists will be able to collect evidence on the impacts of large-scale fire on biodiversity.”</p>



<p class="has-text-align-right">Dr Fiona Fraser, acting Threatened Species Commissioner, DAWE.</p>



<h2 id="projects-in-focus">Projects in focus</h2>



<h3 id="1-bioblitzes-across-australia">1. BioBlitzes across Australia</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45506" width="294" height="220" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-640x480.jpg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 294px) 100vw, 294px" /><figcaption>Community members taking part in a water bug survey  during the Panboola BioBlitz Photo credit: <a href="https://atlasoflife.org.au">Atlas of Life </a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>We are enabling community participation in a series of BioBlitzes in fire affected areas across Australia. The BioBlitzes aim to discover, identify and record as many kinds of species present in a particular area over a 24-hour period. This work is in partnership with the Centre for  Ecosystem Science at UNSW, the Australian Citizen Science Association and Minderoo’s Fire and Flood Resilience initiative.</p>



<h3 id="2-bushfire-recovery-focus-on-flowers">2. Bushfire recovery: focus on flowers</h3>



<p>This project focuses on developing resources for flora-focused citizen science groups to monitor and record information about how flowers, trees and foliage recovery after a fire. This work is in partnership with the Hawkesbury Institute for the Environment at Western Sydney University.</p>



<h3 id="3-digitising-our-insect-collections">3. Digitising our insect collections</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45499" width="306" height="229" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 306px) 100vw, 306px" /><figcaption>Our National Insect Collection needs help to transcribe text in specimen labels</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>The insect digitisation project focuses on a list of priority insect species. Members of the public participate by using the DigiVol platform to transcribe insect specimen labels in CSIRO’s National Insect Collection. DigiVol is run by the Australian Museum and is supported by Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) infrastructure. Volunteers have already digitised and transcribed 1000s of specimens. Many of the insect specimens being digitised have few or no occurrence records in the ALA and some specimens date back nearly 100 years. This information will help us understand historical changes in insect distribution across space and time.</p>



<h3 id="the-atlas-of-living-australia-delivering-research-ready-data-for-bushfire-research-and-recovery">The Atlas of Living Australia delivering research-ready data for bushfire research and recovery</h3>



<p>This work builds on the lead role the ALA took after the 2019-20 bushfires to explore how the citizen science sector could be supported<br>and coordinated to help deliver research-ready data in the bushfire space. Products from this work included the Citizen Science Bushfire<br>Project Finder and tailored blogs highlighting projects to participate in pre and post disaster events.</p>



<p>IN PARTNERSHIP WITH: </p>



<ul><li>Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p>OUR COLLABORATORS:</p>



<ul><li>The Centre for Ecosystem Science at UNSW</li><li>Hawkesbury Institute for the Environment at</li><li>Western Sydney University</li><li>Australian Citizen Science Association</li><li>Minderoo’s Fire and Flood Resilience initiative</li><li>National Research Collections Australia, CSIRO</li></ul>



<h3 id="more-information">More information</h3>



<p>For more information, read Citizen science to boost existing bushfire recovery activities or contact us at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Echidna CSI: Using citizen science to track echidnas throughout Australia</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/echidna-csi-using-citizen-science-to-track-echidnas-throughout-australia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 01:34:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45443</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Echidna CSI is a research project run by the University of Adelaide using data collected by citizen scientists to study echidnas. The project has had a huge impact on echidna research and conservation. Using a bespoke mobile app, (which uses the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) BioCollect application as its database) and an army of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Echidna CSI is a research project run by the University of Adelaide using data collected by citizen scientists to study echidnas. The project has had a huge impact on echidna research and conservation.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Echidna-V2.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidna-csi-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45444" width="314" height="440" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidna-csi-thumbnail.png 644w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidna-csi-thumbnail-214x300.png 214w" sizes="(max-width: 314px) 100vw, 314px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Echidna-V2.pdf">View or print this impact story as a pdf</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Using a bespoke mobile app, (which uses the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) BioCollect application as its database) and an army of citizen scientists across the country, Echidna CSI has established an Australia-wide distribution map of Short-Beaked Echidnas (Tachyglossus  culeatus). The project has doubled the number of echidna records in the ALA and discovered new facts about echidna biology. Echidna CSI encourages the public to take photos of echidnas around Australia and collect their scats for DNA and hormone analysis. Over the past<br>three years, thousands of participants have recorded more than 12,000 echidna sightings. This is the largest dataset collected by any project for echidnas. The data is providing valuable information on wild populations’ habitat, diet and health including insights into the impact of  ushfires on echidna microbiomes.</p>



<h3 id="study-the-shy-echidna-challenge-accepted">Study the shy Echidna? Challenge accepted</h3>



<p>Echidnas are notoriously shy and difficult to see in the wild, and prior to Echidna CSI they were considered pretty difficult (and expensive) to  tudy. As a result, although echidnas are iconic  native species and threatened by feral animals, habitat loss and road collisions, many aspects of wild populations including their distribution, biology and population trends were largely unknown. The Echidna CSI project brought<br>together ecologists, molecular researchers and computer scientists from the University of Adelaide, the Atlas of Living Australia’s biodiversity data infrastructure, and Australia’s citizen science community to fill the gaps in our knowledge about echidnas. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1024x794.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45447" width="561" height="435" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1024x794.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-300x233.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-768x595.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1536x1191.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1920x1488.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster.jpg 2015w" sizes="(max-width: 561px) 100vw, 561px" /><figcaption>Using Echidna CSI citizen scientists can upload sightings of Echidnas <br>from all over Australia. Image credit: Cecilia Webster</figcaption></figure>



<h3 id="ala-tool-enables-scientists-to-tap-into-citizen-workforce">ALA tool enables scientists to tap into citizen workforce</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45446" width="248" height="246" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow.png 585w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow-300x297.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 248px) 100vw, 248px" /></figure></div>



<p>The research team developed their own custom mobile application for the collection of data and linked this to the  ALA’s BioCollect field data collection tool as the backend database and data access/visualisation tool, to enable citizen scientists to record echidna observations. All observations flow automatically into the ALA. The project has robust quality assurance processes built into it to ensure all records are verified, research-grade data points.  The research team also have access to all citizen scientist echidna observations in the ALA uploaded via other applications such as iNaturalist. The Echidna CSI app is customised to the project and designed to guide users into collecting information that will be of most use. It also includes fun facts about echidnas so users can learn more about this iconic Australian species.</p>



<h3 id="mobile-app-has-huge-impact-for-echidna-research-and-conservation">Mobile app has huge impact for echidna research and conservation</h3>



<p>By combining novel science with citizen science, the Echidna CSI citizen science project has highlighted the extraordinary power of the citizen<br>science approach. More than 11,000 people have contributed to the Echidna CSI project. These citizen scientists have eyes on the ground in<br>many locations and have contributed sightings and genetic material from all states and territories including throughout protected areas and remote places. The research team could never have surveyed such a large area without the help of the Echidna CSI community contributors.</p>



<p>ALA infrastructure has been crucial in advancing echidna research and making the data, and data visualisations, accessible and open. This has resulted in the ability to leverage translational research, such as examining the impact of fire on echidna populations and diet.</p>



<h3 id="assessing-echidna-populations-after-the-2019-20-bushfires">Assessing echidna populations after the 2019-20 bushfires</h3>



<p>All echidna records collected before the 2019-2020 bushfire season served as crucial baseline information to monitor and assess the health of echidna populations post fire. Echidna CSI has conducted some local scale research in fire impacted areas and is documenting a change in echidna microbiomes in areas such as Kangaroo Island in South Australia. This subspecies of echidnas is listed as endangered, so the more we can learn about their response to fire the better.</p>



<h3 id="research-impact">Research impact</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2351989421001761">Echidna CSI – Improving monitoring of a cryptic species at continental scale using Citizen Science</a>. Alan Stenhouse et al, Ecology and Conservation, Vol 28, Aug 2021</li></ul>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45448" width="445" height="297" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1920x1280.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" /><figcaption>Postdoctoral Researcher Dr Tahlia Perry from the University of Adelaide leads the Echidna CSI research project.</figcaption></figure></div>



<h3 id="echidna-csi-in-numbers">Echidna CSI in numbers</h3>



<ul><li>12,000 sightings</li><li>11,000 citizen scientists</li><li>700 scat samples</li><li>2017 Echidna CSI launched</li><li>7 states and territories</li><li>Doubled the number of echidna records in the ALA</li></ul>



<h3 id="awards-and-recognition">Awards and recognition</h3>



<ul><li>Finalist in the 2021 Department of Industry, Science, Energy and Resources Eureka Prize for Innovation in Citizen Science</li><li>Finalist for the 2021 South Australian Citizen Science Award</li><li>Finalist in the 2021 South Australian Science Excellence and Innovation for citizen science and PhD research excellence</li></ul>



<h3 id="for-more-information">For more information</h3>



<ul><li>Echidna CSI is available to download on both Android and Apple devices. </li><li>For more information on the ALA visit <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">ala.org.au</a> or contact <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></li></ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Advisory Board update</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-advisory-board-update/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2021 23:40:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45228</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Our Advisory Board is undergoing a reshuffle. We farewell and thank our Chair Dr Diana Day and welcome the new Chair, Dr Ian Cresswell, and a new member, Dr Manu Saunders, to guide us through the next few years. Welcome to Dr Ian Cresswell, Chair We are excited to announce that Dr Ian Cresswell will [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Our Advisory Board is undergoing a reshuffle. We farewell and thank our Chair Dr Diana Day and welcome the new Chair, Dr Ian Cresswell, and a new member, Dr Manu Saunders, to guide us through the next few years.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45234" width="318" height="285" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped.jpg 945w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped-300x269.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped-768x689.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 318px) 100vw, 318px" /><figcaption>Dr Ian Cresswell</figcaption></figure></div>



<h2 id="welcome-to-dr-ian-cresswell-chair"><strong>Welcome to Dr Ian Cresswell, Chair</strong></h2>



<p>We are excited to announce that Dr Ian Cresswell will take on the role of Chair from our October 2021 meeting.</p>



<p>Ian is well known to the ALA having played a significant role in the establishment of the ALA, and as a member of the Management Committee.</p>



<p>His background in conservation planning, biodiversity science and deep networks into Government through his more recent role with the National State of the Environment Report will be an asset to the Board and the ALA.</p>



<p>Ian has a long history of success in managing large scale, science-based government programs in natural resource management, with a strong focus on management to sustainably achieve economic, social and environmental benefits. He has extensive experience in providing high level advice to Government and Industry on environmental and sustainability issues. He brings national and international experience in protected areas spatial planning, fisheries and wildlife regulation, and biodiversity discovery/taxonomy. He has led major research programs in CSIRO in both terrestrial and marine domains, as well as Australian Government senior executive management roles in marine planning, sustainable fisheries, and wildlife management. Ian was the Director of the Australian Biological Resources Study and was instrumental in the development of Australia’s Virtual Herbarium and the Online Zoological Collections of Australian Museums.</p>



<h2 id="welcome-dr-manu-saunders"><strong>Welcome Dr Manu Saunders</strong></h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45232" width="336" height="253" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited.jpg 816w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" /><figcaption> Dr Manu Saunders is a popular and engaging ecological scientist and communicator. You can follow her on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/ManuSaunders">@ManuSaunders.</a> </figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Manu Saunders is a Lecturer in Ecology at the University of New England, Armidale. Her research and teaching focus on community ecology and ecosystem function and services, particularly related to plant-insect interactions. Prior to studying ecology and embarking on a research career, she completed a degree in English and print journalism and worked in corporate communications.</p>



<p>She is passionate about observing nature and ecological science communication. Manu has published her popular science blog <a href=":%20http:/ecologyisnotadirtyword.com/">Ecology is not a Dirty Word</a> for over 10 years and is an internationally-recognised expert on insect conservation and ecology. She also co-founded the Wild Pollinator Count, Australia’s national citizen science project engaging people with wild pollinator conservation and ecology.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="farewell-to-our-current-chair-dr-diana-day"><strong>Farewell to our current Chair, Dr Diana Day</strong></h2>



<p>We would like to sincerely thank Dr Diana Day for her contribution to the governance of the ALA. Diana has been instrumental in steering the board and the ALA through a challenging COVID period and preparing the ALA so effectively for its engagement with the National Research Infrastructure Roadmap process. Her role ensuring effective board oversight of some of ALAs recent significant transformations, including our cyber security review has been appreciated.</p>



<h2 id="ala-advisory-board-membership-september-2021"><strong>ALA Advisory Board membership September 2021</strong></h2>



<p>The ALA Advisory Board supports the high-level direction and delivery of the ALA by providing vision, advocacy and advice.</p>



<ul><li>Chair: Dr Ian Cresswell, Adjunct Professor, School of Biological, Earth and Environmental Sciences, UNSW at UNSW</li><li>Dr Bek Christensen, Programs Director of the Peter Cullen Trust and President, Ecological Society of Australia</li><li>Mr Matthew Miles, Principal for Environmental Information, South Australian Department for Environment and Water</li><li>Mr Brant Smith, Assistant Secretary, Geospatial and Information Analytics, Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment</li><li>Dr Stephen van Leeuwen, BHP/Curtin Indigenous Professor in Biodiversity &amp; Environmental Science, Curtin University</li><li>Dr Manu Saunders, Lecturer in Ecology and Biology, School of Environmental and Rural Science, University of New England</li><li>Professor David Cantrill (ex-officio), Executive Director Science, Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</li><li>Ms Toni Moate (ex-officio), Director, National Collections and Marine Infrastructure, CSIRO</li><li>Dr Andre Zerger (ex-officio), Director, Atlas of Living Australia</li></ul>



<h2 id="more-info">More info</h2>



<p>For more information about the ALA and our Advisory Board, visit <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/governance/">About us</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
