<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 04:53:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Biodiversity Heritage Library Australia: unlocking the treasures in Australia’s biodiversity literature</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/biodiversity-heritage-library-australia-unlocking-the-treasures-in-australias-biodiversity-literature/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 04:53:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44687</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[BHL Australia is a national project working to digitise Australia’s biodiversity heritage literature and make it freely accessible online.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-V3-lowres.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-case-study-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44691" width="238" height="336" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-case-study-thumbnail.png 642w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-case-study-thumbnail-212x300.png 212w" sizes="(max-width: 238px) 100vw, 238px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-V3-lowres.pdf">View or print this impact story as a PDF</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>The Biodiversity Heritage Library (BHL biodiversitylibrary.org) is the world’s largest online library of biodiversity literature and archival materials. The project is a global consortium of 523 contributing libraries who have together digitised over 59 million pages of the world’s biodiversity literature, all of which is freely accessible online, for everyone. </p>



<p>BHL Australia joined the global consortium in 2010.</p>



<h3 id="australian-biodiversity-literature">Australian biodiversity literature</h3>



<p>The BHL Australia project was one of the very first collaborative projects established by the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA ala.org.au). It is funded and operates as a co-investment between Museums Victoria and the ALA. </p>



<p>BHL Australia now supports 37 contributing organisations from every state and territory across the country. These include Australia’s state museums, herbaria and libraries, as well as smaller organisations such as royal societies, field naturalist clubs and other learned societies and community groups, who may never have had the resources to do this critical work without this support.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/duck-billed-platypus.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44689" width="328" height="271" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/duck-billed-platypus.png 743w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/duck-billed-platypus-300x248.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 328px) 100vw, 328px" /><figcaption>Digitised copies of Australia’s biodiversity literature are now available through the BHL website. Each publication is assigned a digital object identifier (DOI) so it can be easily referenced. Image credit: BHL Australia</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>This work has unlocked treasures such as the first published descriptions the Echidna <a href="https://doi.org/10.5962/p.304529">https://doi.org/10.5962/p.304529</a> (1792), and the Platypus <a href="https://doi.org/10.5962/p.304567 ">https://doi.org/10.5962/p.304567 </a>(1799). These descriptions are now freely accessible, easily discoverable and persistently citable (via DOIs) on the BHL website.</p>



<h3 id="making-our-biodiversity-literature-accessible-and-discoverable">Making our biodiversity literature accessible and discoverable</h3>



<p>The BHL Australia team prioritises the digitisation of Australian-published biodiversity literature. The literature scanning operation is housed  at Melbourne Museum, where journals, monographs, archival material and grey literature are digitised. A significant proportion of the  canning, post-processing and metadata addition is undertaken by a team of dedicated BHL volunteers, many of whom have been with the project since the very beginning.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44688" width="429" height="323" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/BHL-scanning-image-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /><figcaption>BHL Australia volunteers, Jim Healey and Sue Halliwell, scanning a book from Museums Victoria’s Collection. Image credit: Nicole Kearney, BHL Australia</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Providing free, online access to biodiversity literature greatly benefits researchers and decision makers working in the fields of taxonomy (naming and categorising species), ecology and conservation. In particular, providing access to the first descriptions of species greatly benefits the taxonomic community as all descriptions of new or revised species must be referenced to species concepts that have been put forward before. </p>



<p>Assigning DOIs (digital object identifiers) is an important component of BHL Australia’s work. DOIs make the historic literature discoverable; they provide a unique and permanent link to each scientific description online, enabling authors, publishers, and taxonomic databases (such as the ALA) to persistently link to (and find) that literature.</p>



<p>Historic literature is critical to our understanding of Australia’s biodiversity, particularly our understanding of changes in species distribution and  abundance. Since 2010, BHL Australia, and our evergrowing number of Australian contributors, have made almost 400,000 pages of Australia’s biodiversity literature openly accessible online. </p>



<h3 id="for-more-information">For more information:</h3>



<ul><li>You can access BHL Australia at <a href="http://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/collection/bhlau">www.biodiversitylibrary.org/collection/bhlau </a>or via Twitter<a href="https://twitter.com/bhl_au?lang=en"> @bhl_au </a></li><li><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-V3-lowres.pdf">View or print this impact story as a PDF</a></li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>International Living Atlases: Australian software used across the globe</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/international-living-atlases-australian-software-used-across-the-globe/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 04:57:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44677</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia is a world leader in biodiversity data infrastructure. Software code originally developed by our Australian team is now in use by countries around the world to help manage their national biodiversity databases.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheet-International-Living-Atlases-V3-004.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/Living-Atlases-case-study-thumbnail-727x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44678" width="306" height="431" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/Living-Atlases-case-study-thumbnail-727x1024.png 727w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/Living-Atlases-case-study-thumbnail-213x300.png 213w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/Living-Atlases-case-study-thumbnail-768x1082.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/Living-Atlases-case-study-thumbnail-1090x1536.png 1090w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/Living-Atlases-case-study-thumbnail.png 1349w" sizes="(max-width: 306px) 100vw, 306px" /></a><figcaption>View or print this impact story as a PDF</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>In 2010, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was established by the Australian Government’s National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) to provide researchers, decision makers and community groups a one-stop-shop for biodiversity data. There are now over 20 international Living Atlases based on the software platform originally developed by the ALA.</p>



<h2 id="the-ala-goes-global">The ALA goes global</h2>



<p>Within a few years of operation, the ALA rapidly established 100s of data partners across museums and herbaria, universities, government departments and community groups in Australia. Soon Australia’s biodiversity data were accessible online for ecoscience research, state and federal government environment and species conservation management programs. As the Australian node of GBIF – the Global Biodiversity Information Facility – the ALA supported the international community by sharing expertise and open software code.</p>



<p>In 2015, the ALA hosted the first international Living Atlases community meeting to respond to requests from countries around the world. This helped form the collaborative global community that now supports developers implementing the open source platform. The software code has been used to set up 27 installations around the world for national biodiversity databases as well as thematic, regional and institutional instances.</p>



<h2 id="the-international-living-atlases-community">The international Living Atlases community</h2>



<p>The Living Atlases platform enables countries to aggregate biodiversity data from multiple sources and supports integrated access to other biological and environmental information such as temperature, habitat etc.</p>



<p>Living Atlas community members continue to work collaboratively to share code and learn from experiences in establishing national biodiversity databases in their countries. They have organised technical training sessions and presented at numerous international meetings. As a result of these and other efforts, an increasing number of GBIF nodes and other organisations have implemented the platform. The Living Atlases community website offers full technical documentation, news from across the community and a current and complete list of participating countries.</p>



<h2 id="for-more-information">For more information:</h2>



<p><a href="https://living-atlases.gbif.org/">Living Atlases website</a></p>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheet-International-Living-Atlases-V3-004.pdf">View or print this impact story as a PDF</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Past, present and future: looking back to look forward</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/past-present-and-future-looking-back-to-look-forward/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 21:59:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44661</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia has been aggregating biodiversity data for over 10 years. But how did we come to be, what have we delivered to date, and what challenges are we tackling next?]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/BDJ.9.e65023">new paper released today in Biodiversity Data Journal </a>written by Lee Belbin, Ely Wallis, Donald Hobern and Andre Zerger maps out the ALA’s past, present and future.</p>



<p>“The ALA was really a front-runner in the biodiversity data space. Early and ongoing investment from the Australian Government National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy was timely and has had a lasting impact on how biodiversity data are managed and accessed on a global scale.” says ALA Director Dr Andre Zerger.</p>



<p>&nbsp;“We thought it was time to document this history and achievement and I believe this paper will become a critical reference for the international biodiversity data community.&#8221; </p>



<p><strong>Looking back – our origin story</strong></p>



<p>Let’s set the scene – it’s the late 1990s. You are a taxonomist&nbsp;trying to find specimen data for a research project. To find this information you must personally contact managers of collections, undertake formal loans of specimens from many museums, or travel across the country and internationally to get access to where specimens of interest have been recorded. After months of letters, emails and phone calls, you’re finally able to analyse the data and start your research.</p>



<p>This is a process that was kept on repeat for decades. Finding and accessing biodiversity data was a major challenge, it wasn’t accessible or shared between organisations.</p>



<p>By the mid-2000s, the research community saw opportunity in emerging digital technologies and significant collaborative initiatives were underway to start to share data. Cue the review of national research infrastructure. The findings of this review led to the Australian Government accepting the &nbsp;proposal of the natural history collections community &nbsp;– to build on the collaboration already well advanced to create a single online platform that would harmonises all existing databases.</p>



<p>In May 2006, 25 representatives from across biological collections met at the Australian Museum in Sydney. Here, the group identified the significant benefits of an aggregated database and the Atlas of Living Australia was formed.</p>



<p><strong>Here we are now – Australia’s national biodiversity database</strong></p>



<p>Flash forward to the present day, we now successfully aggregate and harmonise biodiversity data from not only museum and herbarium collections, but &nbsp;government departments, research institutions, Indigenous knowledge holders, community groups, universities, and individuals.</p>



<p>In 2020, we celebrated our 10 years of making biodiversity information accessible to all. Our celebrations were particularly focussed on thanking the founding partners and biodiversity data providers that helped us reach where we are today.</p>



<p>In the 10 years since our launch, we have achieved many milestones and enabled impact across the globe. There are now more than 90 million occurrence records of 110,000 species, 5000 species lists, 2000 biodiversity-related projects, 500 environmental layers. We have also enabled a number of biodiversity data portals by making the underlying ALA code openly available.</p>



<p>We have also taken a leadership role globally through the Living Atlases program. There are instances of ALA software delivering national biodiversity capabilities in 24 countries around the world.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="903" height="640" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/10-stats-for-10-years_image.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44393" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/10-stats-for-10-years_image.png 903w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/10-stats-for-10-years_image-300x213.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/10-stats-for-10-years_image-768x544.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 903px) 100vw, 903px" /></figure>



<p><strong>What does the future hold?</strong></p>



<p>Following our Future Directions National Consultation process in 2019, we began to shift our focus to the new challenges ahead.</p>



<p>The consultation process highlighted how far the ALA has come and the impact we have had on the way Australian biodiversity data are utilised. However, the consultation also highlighted some areas of improvement.</p>



<p>To reach our full potential and continue delivering innovative data solutions, the ALA will have a future focus on projects that aim to:</p>



<ul><li>increase data quality within the ALA</li><li>deliver a diverse range of data to support biodiversity reporting</li><li>harmonise industry data gathered through surveys with existing data available through museums, herbaria, and state data programmes</li><li>take a leadership role in facilitating cooperation and collaboration between institutions</li><li>integrate additional data streams, such as images, genomics, sounds recordings and environmental assessment data to paint a more extensive picture of Australian biodiversity.</li></ul>



<p>We have already embarked on several projects to transform the way people access biodiversity data through the ALA. These include our recently released <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/data-quality-project/">data profiles functionality</a> and a <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/core-infrastructure-upgrade-project/">core infrastructure upgrade project</a> that is being delivered in close partnership with GBIF, which will improve alignment between ALA and GBIF systems and data.</p>



<p>We are excited to see what the future holds and look forward to the continued relationship with our founding partners and others who have become part of the community along the way. These relationships allow us to tackle future challenges collaboratively, and to provide solutions with wide reaching benefit and impact.</p>



<p>Further information:</p>



<ul><li>Read the full article: <a href="https://bdj.pensoft.net/article/65023/">The Atlas of Living Australia: History, current state and future directions</a>. DOI: 10.3897/BDJ.9.e65023</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unlocking the mystery of the Regent Honeyeater</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/unlocking-the-mystery-of-the-regent-honeyeater/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 03:48:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44645</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A recent study by Ross Crates, a scientist at ANU’s Difficult Bird Research Group, explains why Regent Honeyeaters are changing their songs. More importantly, Ross wanted to find out what the change means for their future. Australia&#8217;s most endangered songbird Australia’s most threatened songbird, the Regent Honeyeater (Anthochaera (Xanthomyza) phrygia), is changing its bird call. A [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A recent study by Ross Crates, a scientist at ANU’s Difficult Bird Research Group, explains why Regent Honeyeaters are changing their songs. More importantly, Ross wanted to find out what the change means for their future.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Ross-Crates_Regent-Honeyeater.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44646" width="371" height="371" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Ross-Crates_Regent-Honeyeater.jpg 1000w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Ross-Crates_Regent-Honeyeater-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Ross-Crates_Regent-Honeyeater-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Ross-Crates_Regent-Honeyeater-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 371px) 100vw, 371px" /><figcaption>Ross Crates in the field with an endangered Regent Honeyeater.</figcaption></figure></div>



<h4 id="australias-most-endangered-songbird">Australia&#8217;s most endangered songbird</h4>



<p>Australia’s most threatened songbird, the Regent Honeyeater (<em><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:83225d29-264f-4236-9dda-32f7d60fb3af">Anthochaera (Xanthomyza) phrygia</a></em>), is changing its bird call.</p>



<p>A changing call makes it difficult for Regent Honeyeaters to find each other and breed. It also poses a particular challenge for the researchers like Ross and his team. The inconsistency in bird call means it is difficult to research these birds and protect them.</p>



<p>The Regent Honeyeater was commonly found throughout Australia’s south-east, but due to land clearing since the 1960s, it is now on the verge of extinction (critically endangered in NSW and QLD, endangered in ACT and SA). The most recent data suggests there are probably less than 350 individuals remaining. This makes it more important than ever for researchers to investigate ways to protect them.</p>



<h4 id="can-songs-provide-insights-into-species-decline">Can songs provide insights into species decline?</h4>



<p>To address the rapid decline in species numbers, Ross and his team are looking into many different factors affecting Regent Honeyeater populations. These include habitat requirements, the range of Eucalyptus trees they like to feed on, and genetic analysis. He has also been listening to the honeyeater’s bird songs.</p>



<p>“We wanted to investigate the impact of population decline on the songs they sing, the complexity of the song and also their individual fitness,” said Ross.</p>



<p>“We were particularly looking at the male birds because the song is a crucial tool to attract a mate.”</p>



<h4 id="finding-the-data-live-recordings-and-the-back-catalogue"><strong>Finding the data: live recordings and the back catalogue</strong></h4>



<p>Ross pulled together lots of Regent Honeyeater data from surveys and BirdLife Australia sightings. This data was used to assess distribution and density of the remaining wild populations. For the sound recordings of the honeyeaters’ contemporary songs, the research team recorded birds in the wild and in captivity. They then used the ALA to find historical song recordings of wild males from 1986 to 2011.</p>



<p>“The ALA provides access to over 5,200 sound files of bird songs. This was incredibly useful for us as we could make comparisons and work out how regent honeyeater songs have changed over time,” said Ross.</p>



<p>Then it was time for some easy listening – was their old stuff better than their new stuff?</p>



<h4 id="how-the-songs-of-the-regent-honeyeater-have-changed"><strong>How the songs of the Regent Honeyeater have changed</strong></h4>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Regent-Honeyeater-uploaded-to-iNaturalist-by-deborod-in-Canberra--1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44648" width="425" height="282" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Regent-Honeyeater-uploaded-to-iNaturalist-by-deborod-in-Canberra--1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Regent-Honeyeater-uploaded-to-iNaturalist-by-deborod-in-Canberra--300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Regent-Honeyeater-uploaded-to-iNaturalist-by-deborod-in-Canberra--768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Regent-Honeyeater-uploaded-to-iNaturalist-by-deborod-in-Canberra--1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Regent-Honeyeater-uploaded-to-iNaturalist-by-deborod-in-Canberra-.jpg 1800w" sizes="(max-width: 425px) 100vw, 425px" /><figcaption>Regent Honeyeater observation uploaded to iNaturalist by deborod in Canberra. (c) deborod</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Ross and his team listened to and coded over 228 songs. They found the two main groups of wild birds had their own distinct songs: The Blue Mountains song and the Northern Tablelands song.</p>



<p>They also found that some birds within each group sang different songs. Some sang a shortened version of their group’s song, but others copied the songs of much more abundant birds, such as the Little Wattlebird, Noisy Friarbird, Spiny-cheeked Honeyeater, Pied Currawong, and Eastern Rosella.</p>



<p>“We found that Regent Honeyeaters were copying other birds and singing atypical songs, if their population density was low in that area. Males that sang other species&#8217; songs had significantly fewer conspecifics (birds of the same species) living close by, than males that sang species-specific songs,” said Ross.</p>



<p>“We also found that birds that sang different songs were less likely to be paired with a female in that breeding season.”</p>



<h4 id="impact-of-this-research"><strong>Impact of this research</strong></h4>



<p>In this research paper, Ross’ team have come closer to understanding how animal cultures are maintained, the conditions under which they are lost, and the impact this has on both species’ evolution and conservation.</p>



<p>“We found rare evidence showing that a severe decline in population size and density is associated with the loss of vocal culture in a wild animal population. This is similar to the loss of human languages globally,” said Ross.</p>



<p>“Also, for the first time, we’ve shown that birds in very small groups in the wild suffer from significant changes that affect their fitness to reproduce. And these changes may speed up the decline in numbers.”</p>



<h4 id="changing-the-way-we-monitor-endangered-bird-populations"><strong>Changing the way we monitor endangered bird populations</strong></h4>



<p>By researching the endangered Regent Honeyeater and their changing songbook, Ross and his team have found that the birds are changing their songs to learn songs of more abundant species. This may be a precursor to extinction in already declining populations.</p>



<p>“This approach – where we monitor how birds are changing their songs – may provide a new way for assessing the trajectory of population decline, especially for species whose populations are very difficult to monitor in traditional ways,” said Ross.</p>



<h4 id="for-more-information"><strong>For more information:</strong></h4>



<ul><li>Read the full research paper (open access): <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rspb.2021.0225">Loss of vocal culture and fitness costs in a critically endangered songbird</a></li><li>Use the ALA to listen to other bird calls. To get started read <a href="https://confluence.csiro.au/pages/viewpage.action?pageId=1485242563">How do I find bird sounds in the ALA?</a></li><li>Read more about the <a href="https://www.difficultbirds.com/">Difficult Bird Research Group</a></li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>iNaturalist Australia makes huge contribution to biodiversity data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/inaturalist-australia-makes-huge-contribution-to-biodiversity-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 01:25:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44628</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A recent review of iNaturalist Australia highlights its success since launch in 2019.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Thomas-mesaglio_3_image-credit-Kate-Mesaglio_cropped.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44635" width="466" height="451" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Thomas-mesaglio_3_image-credit-Kate-Mesaglio_cropped.jpg 750w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Thomas-mesaglio_3_image-credit-Kate-Mesaglio_cropped-300x290.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 466px) 100vw, 466px" /><figcaption>Thomas Mesaglio in action recording a species observation for iNaturalist Australia. Image credit: Kate Mesaglio</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Thomas Mesaglio, an environmental scientist from the Centre for Ecosystem Science at the University of New South Wales, has a keen interest in how citizen scientists across Australia are helping large scale ecological studies.</p>



<p>In his recent review of iNaturalist Australia, Thomas measured a number of changes across the platform. He looked at the increase in the volume of data being uploaded, numbers of users and the different taxonomic and spatial data being recorded. He also showcased some applications of iNaturalist data for species conservation and monitoring.</p>



<p>“iNaturalist is an excellent platform for recording observations of species and it has contributed enormously to our biodiversity data holdings in Australia,” said Thomas.</p>



<p>“It’s a great platform to increase public participation in natural science.” he said.</p>



<p>The data collected by citizen scientists through iNaturalist is made available online through the Atlas of Living Australia and becomes part of the ever-increasing Australian biodiversity data repository. Researchers and people in government working on environment policy use biodiversity data in the ALA to inform many research studies and government programs in ecology, land management, species conservation and biosecurity measures.</p>



<p><strong>iNaturalist Australia in numbers</strong></p>



<p>iNaturalist is one of the most popular biodiversity citizen science platforms globally, with more than 1.4 million users having contributed over 54 million observations. Australia contributes the most observations in the southern hemisphere, and is in the top four contributing nations globally. &nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="949" height="534" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/iNat-infographic_2.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44638" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/iNat-infographic_2.png 949w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/iNat-infographic_2-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/iNat-infographic_2-768x432.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 949px) 100vw, 949px" /></figure>



<p>In 2019, the ALA collaborated with the global iNaturalist Network to set up iNaturalist Australia. In two years there has been a huge growth in the number of Australian users and in the number of species observations recorded through the platform.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="638" height="424" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Number-of-observers-and-species-iNat-since-2008.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44630" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Number-of-observers-and-species-iNat-since-2008.png 638w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Number-of-observers-and-species-iNat-since-2008-300x199.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 638px) 100vw, 638px" /><figcaption>The number of observers and observed species on iNaturalist Australia since 2008.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p><strong>Helping to protect our threatened species and manage invasive species</strong></p>



<p>Data collected through iNaturalist Australia is uploaded automatically to the ALA, where it is made accessible and usable by researchers and decision-makers. Citizen science data uploaded through iNaturalist (and other apps) are particularly useful for the monitoring and conservation of threatened species.</p>



<p>Citizen science data are also used to help model the distribution of invasive species and assess their impact on our ecology and economy. Alongside other apps like FeralScan and MyPestGuide, iNaturalist is well positioned to provide data to help with pest surveillance for biosecurity programs.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="667" height="543" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/Dwarf-spider-orchid-by-Reiner-Richter.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-44631"/><figcaption>A selection of species observations uploaded to iNaturalist Australia and featured in Thomas&#8217; recent paper <a href="https://www.publish.csiro.au/WR/fulltext/WR20154">An overview of the history, current contributions and future outlook of iNaturalist in Australia</a>. (<em>a</em>) Anthony Katon (@anthonykat); (<em>b</em>) Ákos Lumnitzer (@akoslumnitzer); (<em>c</em>) John Eichler (@johneichler); (<em>d</em>) Reiner Richter (@reiner)</figcaption></figure></div>



<p><strong>Citizens are our data collection powerhouse</strong></p>



<p>Thomas has used citizen science data in many of his research projects and sees wide ranging benefits of digital platforms such as iNaturalist Australia and national repositories like the ALA.</p>



<p>“Citizen scientists are able to observe species in locations not covered by research or government surveys such as on private land,</p>



<p>“The combination of a willing workforce of citizen scientists and the digital platforms that enable their contributions to be shared and utilised is of huge benefit to ecology researchers and government conservation, land management and biosecurity programs.&#8221;</p>



<p>Citizen science data are typically collected and verified at little or no cost. Thomas’ paper highlights that the iNaturalist model, where citizen science data is integrated with professional data collection, greatly reduces the costs of ecological monitoring and expedites scientific discoveries.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="602" height="576" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/04/iNat-infographic-data-collection.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-44632"/><figcaption>As more taxonomic experts join iNaturalist, more observations will increase the quality of the data, providing more data for ecological and conservation research questions in Australia.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>To find out more:</p>



<ul><li>Read Thomas’ full article <a href="https://www.publish.csiro.au/WR/fulltext/WR20154">An overview of the history, current contributions and future outlook of iNaturalist in Australia</a></li><li>Join <a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/">iNaturalist Australia</a> and start recording your species observations today!</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter February 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-february-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 05:15:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44610</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Atlas of Living Australian Newsletter February 2021]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Feb-2021-newsletter-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44611" width="275" height="418" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Feb-2021-newsletter-thumbnail.png 461w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Feb-2021-newsletter-thumbnail-198x300.png 198w" sizes="(max-width: 275px) 100vw, 275px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ALA-Newsletter-Feb-2021.pdf">Atlas of Living Australian Newsletter February 2021</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Helping you search and filter data in the ALA</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/helping-you-search-and-filter-data-in-the-ala/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 05:11:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44595</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Our new data quality filters, called Data Profiles, allow you to filter out incomplete or inconsistent records. This makes it easier to find the data you need. Since February 2020,&#160;we’ve been working with&#160;the ALA user community&#160;to identify&#160;data quality related issues and develop solutions.&#160; Thank you to everyone who completed our surveys,&#160;contributed to our understanding of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Our new data quality filters, called <strong><em>Data Profiles</em></strong>, allow you to filter out incomplete or inconsistent records. This makes it easier to find the data you need.</p>



<p>Since February 2020,&nbsp;we’ve been working with&nbsp;the ALA user community&nbsp;to identify&nbsp;data quality related issues and develop solutions.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Thank you to everyone who completed our surveys,&nbsp;contributed to our understanding of the baseline&nbsp;perceptions of data quality,&nbsp;helped to&nbsp;prioritise issues,&nbsp;and tested&nbsp;solutions.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Prioritisation survey results</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>After establishing a baseline of <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/data-quality-project-baseline-survey-results/">data quality perceptions</a> we conducted a&nbsp;prioritisation&nbsp;survey to&nbsp;identify&nbsp;which&nbsp;issues&nbsp;the data quality project&nbsp;would&nbsp;address&nbsp;first. The top two issues identified&nbsp;were:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>ALA users accessing data via the ALA without filtering out records that are not fit for their purpose.&nbsp;</li><li>Users did not&nbsp;know if records&nbsp;or datasets were suitable for&nbsp;their&nbsp;purpose because quality indicators were not visible. Additionally, many users didn’t understand what the indicators <a>information</a>&nbsp;meant.&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p><strong>Improvements to data filters</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>In response to these issues,&nbsp;the project developed a&nbsp;new&nbsp;capability&nbsp;to&nbsp;pre-filter search results so that lower quality records&nbsp;(e.g.&nbsp;incomplete or&nbsp;inconsistent)&nbsp;are not shown unless they are actively included.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The filters, called <strong><em>Data Profiles</em></strong>, can be seen in a new&nbsp;user interface&nbsp;element at the top of the search results webpage.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Data Profiles enable users to access quality data quickly. Filters can be switched on&nbsp;or&nbsp;off&nbsp;and managed as a group or individually.&nbsp;If you’d like more information about the fields and the data that contributes to them, you can mouse-over the text or&nbsp;click the info icons (<strong>i</strong>).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="697" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44596" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality-300x204.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality-768x523.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>ALA’s occurrence record search for <em>Acacia dealbata</em> records. The new data quality filters are highlighted by a red box.&nbsp;</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Data Profiles in the ALA</strong></p>



<p>Data Profiles provide a filtered view of data and give a curation capability not previously available to users of the ALA.</p>



<p>“We developed the Data Profiles functionality in response to users identifying data quality as a high priority issue,” said Miles Nicholls, ALA’s Data Quality Project Lead.</p>



<p>“Communities, jurisdictions, and expert groups will be able to develop and publish data profiles, making their expertise in data selection and curation available to the whole ALA user community. Ultimately this means better information will be available to support research, analysis and decision making as well as community engagement with the environment,” said Miles.</p>



<p><strong>Find out more</strong></p>



<p>For more information on the new data filter features, check out these support articles:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000240256-getting-started-with-the-data-profiles">Getting started with the data profiles</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241037-data-profiles-faqs">Data profiles FAQs&nbsp;</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241038-how-do-i-turnoff-or-modify-the-data-quality-filters-">How do I turn&nbsp;off or modify the data profile?&nbsp;</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241039-how-do-i-know-what-the-data-quality-filters-are-doing-">How do I know what the filters are doing?&nbsp;</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241055-what-do-i-do-about-my-records-being-filtered-out-">What do I do about my records being filtered out?</a>&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p>For more information on the project itself, visit the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/data-quality-project/">Data Quality project page</a> or contact us at <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="mailto:dataquality@ala.org.au" target="_blank">dataquality@ala.org.au</a>. </p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GBIF Young Researchers Award 2021 – Australian nominations</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/gbif-young-researchers-award-2021-australian-nominations/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 05:01:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44591</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are now open for the GBIF 2021 Young Researchers Award. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="210" height="100" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/GBIF-logo-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44593"/></figure></div>



<p>The GBIF Young Researchers Awards is an annual programme aimed at fostering innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics. The 2021 programme will provide a pair of prizes worth &nbsp;€5,000 (approx. AUD 7,700) each, recognising the work of two graduate students—preferably, one masters and one PhD candidate—nominated by&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network" target="_blank">GBIF Participant countries</a>.</p>



<p>This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p>Applications are due by 31 May 2021.</p>



<p><strong>How to submit a nomination (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol type="1"><li>Visit <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6SrTuANNJyRweO9c6lSx85/call-for-nominations-to-the-2021-gbif-young-researchers-award">the GBIF young researchers award website</a> and follow the instructions. </li><li>Submit your nominations to <a href="mailto:martin.westgate@csiro.au">Martin Westgate, ALA’s Science Advisor, </a>with ‘GBIF Young Researcher’ in the subject line by <strong>31 May 2021.</strong> </li></ol>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline.&nbsp; Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;for further information if required.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat. The winners will be announced in September/October 2021.</p>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6SrTuANNJyRweO9c6lSx85/call-for-nominations-to-the-2021-gbif-young-researchers-award" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF website.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s update &#8211; February 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-february-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 04:42:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44589</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the first of our 2021 ALA newsletters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I’d like to welcome you to the first of our 2021 ALA newsletters by thanking everyone who helped make our ten-year celebrations such a success.  We were particularly buoyed with how our community engaged with our science impact webinars and thank our presenters who made that experience so rewarding. The lessons we learnt last year will be used to deliver more regular virtual events through 2021 with the first to be held on Wednesday 3 March exploring <a href="https://events.csiro.au/Events/2021/February/18/Exploring-citizen-science-disaster-response-and-recovery">the role of citizen science in the context of disaster response and recovery</a>.</p>



<p>2021 will be an important year for the ALA and our partners in the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy program as this year is a ‘road mapping’ year. The 2021 National Research Infrastructure Roadmap will map out Australia’s research infrastructure capability and future areas of need for the coming five to ten years. A roadmap process is completed every five years to ensure Australia maintains its excellent research infrastructure, continues to support innovation and addresses emerging research challenges. The Department of Education, Skills and Employment will shortly announce the formation of an expert working group with membership agreed to by the Minister for Education and the Minister for Industry, Science and Technology with a planned delivery date of a draft towards the end of the 2021 calendar year. We feel well prepared heading into a roadmap process given the 2019 completion of the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-future-directions-national-consultation-findings-report/">ALA Future Directions National Consultation</a>. However, we also operate in a very dynamic space driven by digital transformation so 2021 will provide the ALA and our partners an opportunity to engage and shape future priorities.</p>



<p>Finally, 2021 also presents a rare opportunity to engage with an important commonwealth initiative focussed broadly on biodiversity data and information. Many in our sector will know that Professor Graeme Samuel recently released the final report of the <a href="https://epbcactreview.environment.gov.au/resources/final-report/foreword">Independent Review of the Environmental Protection and Biodiversity Conservation ACT 1999</a>. Importantly for the ALA, data, information and systems feature prominently in the review recommendations primarily with respect to developing improved data and information supply chains to support decision-making – Chapter 10 of the review is an important read if you have an interest in the criticality of data and information in supporting regulatory processes. Our recently announced partnership with the <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/news/improving-access-to-public-sector-data-strengthens-australian-research/">Australian Research Data Commons</a> and other partners around the Sensitive Species Data Pathways Project to develop the agreements, governance arrangements and frameworks to share sensitive species information further provides a unique opportunity to deliver a step-change in how Australia acquires, manages and delivers its biodiversity data.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy the February edition of our newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Andre Zerger</strong></p>



<p><strong>Director, Atlas of Living Australia</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Improving access to sensitive species data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/improving-access-to-sensitive-species-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 23:41:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44558</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In January 2021, we started a new collaborative project that aims to address some of the major challenges for people working with sensitive and threatened species data. Data for sensitive species is critical for researching and managing our threatened species and ecosystems. Currently, sensitive species data is hard to access, and the ways people access [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In January 2021, we started a new collaborative project that aims to address some of the major challenges for people working with sensitive and threatened species data.</p>



<p>Data for sensitive species is critical for researching and managing our threatened species and ecosystems. Currently, sensitive species data is hard to access, and the ways people access these data are different for all states and territories.</p>



<p>The Sensitive Species Data Pathways project (<a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027">https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027</a>), supported by ARDC, is the first project of its kind to involve every state and commonwealth jurisdiction, all relevant research infrastructures and data repositories, as well as peak community bodies working in the sector. </p>



<p>The project started in January 2021 and will continue through to December 2022.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44559" width="351" height="234" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188.jpg 1852w" sizes="(max-width: 351px) 100vw, 351px" /><figcaption>The Northern Quoll <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:5d7aeda8-2ec1-4111-830e-847f34321f88" target="_blank"><em>(Dasyurus hallucatus</em></a>) observed in in Western Australia where it is considered endangered. © dan_mckenzie (CC-BY-NC 4.0 (Int))</figcaption></figure></div>



<p><strong>What’s so special about sensitive species data?<br></strong>Threatened and sensitive species information and data are central to meaningful research efforts and government policies on biodiversity, ecological systems, and the effects of anthropogenic and climate changes on our environment. They underpin key jurisdictional policies, programs and regulations, including those under the EPBC Act 1999. <strong></strong></p>



<p>Sensitive species data also form a central component of biosecurity legislation (Biosecurity Act 2015) aimed at managing risk to human health, trade, agriculture and the environment from the introduction of exotic species, viruses and pathogens.</p>



<p>We know from recent experience during the Australian bushfires of 2019/20, that access to species data across jurisdictional boundaries is critical to understanding the impact of extreme events on our environment. It is also essential for mitigation, planning and recovery efforts. People working in this area require datasets that include the full spatial and temporal information about target species. These datasets often reside in jurisdictional data repositories and are hard to access.</p>



<p><strong>Current challenges in accessing data on threatened species<br></strong>There are many challenges facing people researching and managing sensitive and threatened species in Australia. Here we mention two key issues which the project team aims to address.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44560" width="346" height="346" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-768x769.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1534x1536.jpg 1534w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-2045x2048.jpg 2045w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1920x1923.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" /><figcaption>Gouldian Finch <em>(<a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:21dc0ca1-1639-496b-ba41-e2903491b666">Erythrura (Chloebia) gouldiae</a></em>) photographed in Queensland where it is listed as endangered. © Charmaine Thomas (CC-BY)</figcaption></figure></div>



<p><em>Access to data</em></p>



<p>At the moment sensitive species data is often managed locally without nationally consistent approaches to licensing and access. The data come from a range of sources that are public (primarily ALA) and restricted (jurisdictions, researchers, private). Access to restricted data can be sought, but the process is time consuming, and it’s not always clear who to approach, or how. A key focus for the project will be developing and implementing a National Framework to address issues such as licensing, access and authority, governance and programmatic standards.</p>



<p><em>Fuzzy wuzzy data</em></p>



<p>Obscuring or fuzzying threatened species data is a necessary practice to ensure vulnerable species are protected from poachers or habitat destruction and prevent unscrupulous researchers from accessing data. However, there is no nationally standardised way for obscuring precise location data. Each institution is reliant on internal or third party (state conservation agency or the Atlas of Living Australia) to fuzz data. Accidental data releases are an ever-present threat that manifests regularly. A national approach to fuzzing and un-fuzzing data will provide a vital risk-mitigation mechanism for protecting threatened species and research data.</p>



<p><strong>The Sensitive Species Data Pathways project partners</strong></p>



<p>We look forward to working with the following partners on this important project:</p>



<ol type="1"><li><strong>Australian Research Data Commons</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (Commonwealth)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Planning, Industry and Environment (NSW)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions (WA)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment and Water (SA)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Primary Industries, Parks, Water and Environment (TAS)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning (VIC)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment and Science (QLD)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment and Natural Resources (NT)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>The Environment, Planning and Sustainable Development Directorate (ACT)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Western Australian Biodiversity Research Institute (WABSI)</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia, CSIRO</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;EcoCommons Australia</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Pawsey Super Computing Centre</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Council of Heads of Australian Faunal Collections</strong></li></ol>



<p>For more information on this project, please contact <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<p>Sensitive Species Data Pathways project&nbsp; DOI <a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027">https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027</a></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><a href="https://ardc.edu.au/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-1024x334.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44562" width="254" height="83" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-1024x334.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-300x98.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-768x250.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB.png 1181w" sizes="(max-width: 254px) 100vw, 254px" /></a></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
