<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 03:13:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.6.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Helping you search and filter data in the ALA</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/helping-you-search-and-filter-data-in-the-ala/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 05:11:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Data]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44595</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Our new data quality filters, called Data Profiles, allow you to filter out incomplete or inconsistent records. This makes it easier to find the data you need. Since February 2020,&#160;we’ve been working with&#160;the ALA user community&#160;to identify&#160;data quality related issues and develop solutions.&#160; Thank you to everyone who completed our surveys,&#160;contributed to our understanding of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Our new data quality filters, called <strong><em>Data Profiles</em></strong>, allow you to filter out incomplete or inconsistent records. This makes it easier to find the data you need.</p>



<p>Since February 2020,&nbsp;we’ve been working with&nbsp;the ALA user community&nbsp;to identify&nbsp;data quality related issues and develop solutions.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Thank you to everyone who completed our surveys,&nbsp;contributed to our understanding of the baseline&nbsp;perceptions of data quality,&nbsp;helped to&nbsp;prioritise issues,&nbsp;and tested&nbsp;solutions.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Prioritisation survey results</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>After establishing a baseline of <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/data-quality-project-baseline-survey-results/">data quality perceptions</a> we conducted a&nbsp;prioritisation&nbsp;survey to&nbsp;identify&nbsp;which&nbsp;issues&nbsp;the data quality project&nbsp;would&nbsp;address&nbsp;first. The top two issues identified&nbsp;were:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>ALA users accessing data via the ALA without filtering out records that are not fit for their purpose.&nbsp;</li><li>Users did not&nbsp;know if records&nbsp;or datasets were suitable for&nbsp;their&nbsp;purpose because quality indicators were not visible. Additionally, many users didn’t understand what the indicators <a>information</a>&nbsp;meant.&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p><strong>Improvements to data filters</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>In response to these issues,&nbsp;the project developed a&nbsp;new&nbsp;capability&nbsp;to&nbsp;pre-filter search results so that lower quality records&nbsp;(e.g.&nbsp;incomplete or&nbsp;inconsistent)&nbsp;are not shown unless they are actively included.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The filters, called <strong><em>Data Profiles</em></strong>, can be seen in a new&nbsp;user interface&nbsp;element at the top of the search results webpage.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Data Profiles enable users to access quality data quickly. Filters can be switched on&nbsp;or&nbsp;off&nbsp;and managed as a group or individually.&nbsp;If you’d like more information about the fields and the data that contributes to them, you can mouse-over the text or&nbsp;click the info icons (<strong>i</strong>).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="697" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44596" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality-300x204.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Data-quality-768x523.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>ALA’s occurrence record search for <em>Acacia dealbata</em> records. The new data quality filters are highlighted by a red box.&nbsp;</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Data Profiles in the ALA</strong></p>



<p>Data Profiles provide a filtered view of data and give a curation capability not previously available to users of the ALA.</p>



<p>“We developed the Data Profiles functionality in response to users identifying data quality as a high priority issue,” said Miles Nicholls, ALA’s Data Quality Project Lead.</p>



<p>“Communities, jurisdictions, and expert groups will be able to develop and publish data profiles, making their expertise in data selection and curation available to the whole ALA user community. Ultimately this means better information will be available to support research, analysis and decision making as well as community engagement with the environment,” said Miles.</p>



<p><strong>Find out more</strong></p>



<p>For more information on the new data filter features, check out these support articles:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000240256-getting-started-with-the-data-profiles">Getting started with the data profiles</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241037-data-profiles-faqs">Data profiles FAQs&nbsp;</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241038-how-do-i-turnoff-or-modify-the-data-quality-filters-">How do I turn&nbsp;off or modify the data profile?&nbsp;</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241039-how-do-i-know-what-the-data-quality-filters-are-doing-">How do I know what the filters are doing?&nbsp;</a></li><li><a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000241055-what-do-i-do-about-my-records-being-filtered-out-">What do I do about my records being filtered out?</a>&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p>For more information on the project itself, visit the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/data-quality-project/">Data Quality project page</a> or contact us at <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="mailto:dataquality@ala.org.au" target="_blank">dataquality@ala.org.au</a>. </p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GBIF Young Researchers Award 2021 – Australian nominations</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/gbif-young-researchers-award-2021-australian-nominations/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 05:01:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44591</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are now open for the GBIF 2021 Young Researchers Award. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="210" height="100" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/GBIF-logo-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44593"/></figure></div>



<p>The GBIF Young Researchers Awards is an annual programme aimed at fostering innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics. The 2021 programme will provide a pair of prizes worth &nbsp;€5,000 (approx. AUD 7,700) each, recognising the work of two graduate students—preferably, one masters and one PhD candidate—nominated by&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network" target="_blank">GBIF Participant countries</a>.</p>



<p>This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p>Applications are due by 31 May 2021.</p>



<p><strong>How to submit a nomination (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol type="1"><li>Visit <a href="mailto:https://www.gbif.org/news/6SrTuANNJyRweO9c6lSx85/call-for-nominations-to-the-2021-gbif-young-researchers-award">the GBIF young researchers award website</a> and following the instructions.&nbsp;</li><li>Submit your nominations to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:martin.westgate@csiro.au">Martin Westgate, ALA’s Science Advisor,&nbsp;</a>with ‘GBIF Young Researcher’ in the subject line by&nbsp;<strong>31 May 2021.</strong>&nbsp;</li></ol>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline.&nbsp; Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;for further information if required.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat. The winners will be announced in September/October 2021.</p>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6SrTuANNJyRweO9c6lSx85/call-for-nominations-to-the-2021-gbif-young-researchers-award" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF website.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s update &#8211; February 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-february-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 04:42:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44589</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the first of our 2021 ALA newsletters.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>I’d like to welcome you to the first of our 2021 ALA newsletters by thanking everyone who helped make our ten-year celebrations such a success.  We were particularly buoyed with how our community engaged with our science impact webinars and thank our presenters who made that experience so rewarding. The lessons we learnt last year will be used to deliver more regular virtual events through 2021 with the first to be held on Wednesday 3 March exploring <a href="https://events.csiro.au/Events/2021/February/18/Exploring-citizen-science-disaster-response-and-recovery">the role of citizen science in the context of disaster response and recovery</a>.</p>



<p>2021 will be an important year for the ALA and our partners in the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy program as this year is a ‘road mapping’ year. The 2021 National Research Infrastructure Roadmap will map out Australia’s research infrastructure capability and future areas of need for the coming five to ten years. A roadmap process is completed every five years to ensure Australia maintains its excellent research infrastructure, continues to support innovation and addresses emerging research challenges. The Department of Education, Skills and Employment will shortly announce the formation of an expert working group with membership agreed to by the Minister for Education and the Minister for Industry, Science and Technology with a planned delivery date of a draft towards the end of the 2021 calendar year. We feel well prepared heading into a roadmap process given the 2019 completion of the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-future-directions-national-consultation-findings-report/">ALA Future Directions National Consultation</a>. However, we also operate in a very dynamic space driven by digital transformation so 2021 will provide the ALA and our partners an opportunity to engage and shape future priorities.</p>



<p>Finally, 2021 also presents a rare opportunity to engage with an important commonwealth initiative focussed broadly on biodiversity data and information. Many in our sector will know that Professor Graeme Samuel recently released the final report of the <a href="https://epbcactreview.environment.gov.au/resources/final-report/foreword">Independent Review of the Environmental Protection and Biodiversity Conservation ACT 1999</a>. Importantly for the ALA, data, information and systems feature prominently in the review recommendations primarily with respect to developing improved data and information supply chains to support decision-making – Chapter 10 of the review is an important read if you have an interest in the criticality of data and information in supporting regulatory processes. Our recently announced partnership with the <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/news/improving-access-to-public-sector-data-strengthens-australian-research/">Australian Research Data Commons</a> and other partners around the Sensitive Species Data Pathways Project to develop the agreements, governance arrangements and frameworks to share sensitive species information further provides a unique opportunity to deliver a step-change in how Australia acquires, manages and delivers its biodiversity data.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy the February edition of our newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Andre Zerger</strong></p>



<p><strong>Director, Atlas of Living Australia</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Improving access to sensitive species data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/improving-access-to-sensitive-species-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 23:41:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44558</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In January 2021, we started a new collaborative project that aims to address some of the major challenges for people working with sensitive and threatened species data. Data for sensitive species is critical for researching and managing our threatened species and ecosystems. Currently, sensitive species data is hard to access, and the ways people access [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In January 2021, we started a new collaborative project that aims to address some of the major challenges for people working with sensitive and threatened species data.</p>



<p>Data for sensitive species is critical for researching and managing our threatened species and ecosystems. Currently, sensitive species data is hard to access, and the ways people access these data are different for all states and territories.</p>



<p>The Sensitive Species Data Pathways project (<a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027">https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027</a>), supported by ARDC, is the first project of its kind to involve every state and commonwealth jurisdiction, all relevant research infrastructures and data repositories, as well as peak community bodies working in the sector. </p>



<p>The project started in January 2021 and will continue through to December 2022.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44559" width="351" height="234" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Northern-Quoll-by-dan_mckenzie_inaturalist_50377188.jpg 1852w" sizes="(max-width: 351px) 100vw, 351px" /><figcaption>The Northern Quoll <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:5d7aeda8-2ec1-4111-830e-847f34321f88" target="_blank"><em>(Dasyurus hallucatus</em></a>) observed in in Western Australia where it is considered endangered. © dan_mckenzie (CC-BY-NC 4.0 (Int))</figcaption></figure></div>



<p><strong>What’s so special about sensitive species data?<br></strong>Threatened and sensitive species information and data are central to meaningful research efforts and government policies on biodiversity, ecological systems, and the effects of anthropogenic and climate changes on our environment. They underpin key jurisdictional policies, programs and regulations, including those under the EPBC Act 1999. <strong></strong></p>



<p>Sensitive species data also form a central component of biosecurity legislation (Biosecurity Act 2015) aimed at managing risk to human health, trade, agriculture and the environment from the introduction of exotic species, viruses and pathogens.</p>



<p>We know from recent experience during the Australian bushfires of 2019/20, that access to species data across jurisdictional boundaries is critical to understanding the impact of extreme events on our environment. It is also essential for mitigation, planning and recovery efforts. People working in this area require datasets that include the full spatial and temporal information about target species. These datasets often reside in jurisdictional data repositories and are hard to access.</p>



<p><strong>Current challenges in accessing data on threatened species<br></strong>There are many challenges facing people researching and managing sensitive and threatened species in Australia. Here we mention two key issues which the project team aims to address.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44560" width="346" height="346" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-768x769.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1534x1536.jpg 1534w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-2045x2048.jpg 2045w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/Gouldian-finch-by-Charmaine-Thomas-CCBY-1920x1923.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 346px) 100vw, 346px" /><figcaption>Gouldian Finch <em>(<a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:21dc0ca1-1639-496b-ba41-e2903491b666">Erythrura (Chloebia) gouldiae</a></em>) photographed in Queensland where it is listed as endangered. © Charmaine Thomas (CC-BY)</figcaption></figure></div>



<p><em>Access to data</em></p>



<p>At the moment sensitive species data is often managed locally without nationally consistent approaches to licensing and access. The data come from a range of sources that are public (primarily ALA) and restricted (jurisdictions, researchers, private). Access to restricted data can be sought, but the process is time consuming, and it’s not always clear who to approach, or how. A key focus for the project will be developing and implementing a National Framework to address issues such as licensing, access and authority, governance and programmatic standards.</p>



<p><em>Fuzzy wuzzy data</em></p>



<p>Obscuring or fuzzying threatened species data is a necessary practice to ensure vulnerable species are protected from poachers or habitat destruction and prevent unscrupulous researchers from accessing data. However, there is no nationally standardised way for obscuring precise location data. Each institution is reliant on internal or third party (state conservation agency or the Atlas of Living Australia) to fuzz data. Accidental data releases are an ever-present threat that manifests regularly. A national approach to fuzzing and un-fuzzing data will provide a vital risk-mitigation mechanism for protecting threatened species and research data.</p>



<p><strong>The Sensitive Species Data Pathways project partners</strong></p>



<p>We look forward to working with the following partners on this important project:</p>



<ol type="1"><li><strong>Australian Research Data Commons</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (Commonwealth)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Planning, Industry and Environment (NSW)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions (WA)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment and Water (SA)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Primary Industries, Parks, Water and Environment (TAS)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment, Land, Water and Planning (VIC)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment and Science (QLD)</strong></li><li><strong>Department of Environment and Natural Resources (NT)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>The Environment, Planning and Sustainable Development Directorate (ACT)&nbsp;</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Western Australian Biodiversity Research Institute (WABSI)</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia, CSIRO</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;EcoCommons Australia</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Pawsey Super Computing Centre</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria</strong></li><li><strong>&nbsp;Council of Heads of Australian Faunal Collections</strong></li></ol>



<p>For more information on this project, please contact <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<p>Sensitive Species Data Pathways project&nbsp; DOI <a href="https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027">https://doi.org/10.47486/PS027</a></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><a href="https://ardc.edu.au/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-1024x334.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44562" width="254" height="83" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-1024x334.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-300x98.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB-768x250.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ARDC_logo_RGB.png 1181w" sizes="(max-width: 254px) 100vw, 254px" /></a></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>DNA key to identifying eggs in museum collections</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/dna-key-to-identifying-eggs-in-museum-collections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 15 Jan 2021 10:10:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Collections]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44527</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A new study shows how the scientific value of collections can be improved by DNA technologies that provide high-confidence taxonomic identifications of specimens.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-scaled.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44530" width="384" height="288" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-in-drawer-ANWC-CSIRO-edited-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 384px) 100vw, 384px" /><figcaption>There are 24,000 clutches of bird eggs from more than 1,000 species in the Australian National Wildlife Collection (ANWC).  Here are the eggs used in this study. Image credit: ANWC, CSIRO.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>In 2019 researchers at the Australian National Wildlife Collection (ANWC) at CSIRO and the Trace and Environmental DNA Laboratory at Curtin University extracted and sequenced DNA from three 50-year-old eggshells from the ANWC avian egg collection. They used it to reconstruct near-complete mitochondrial genomes, a first using eggshells of non-ratite birds.</p>



<p>Today, a team from ANWC and the Australian National University announced DNA can be extracted from very small eggshells held in museum collections without causing damage to the integrity or appearance of the specimen. The team demonstrated how their new sampling technique can be used to confirm the identity of unknown specimens.</p>



<p>Around the world there are nearly 5 million eggshell specimens held in natural history collections. Many were collected by hobbyists in the past, before egg collecting was made illegal in most countries.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-ANWC-CSIRO-1024x1007.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44538" width="309" height="304" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-ANWC-CSIRO-1024x1007.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-ANWC-CSIRO-300x295.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-ANWC-CSIRO-768x755.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Eggs-ANWC-CSIRO.png 1144w" sizes="(max-width: 309px) 100vw, 309px" /><figcaption>Eggs specimens shown before (left) and after (right) drilling to extract DNA for this study. Image credit: ANWC, CSIRO.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>“To be useful for scientific research, eggshells need to have accurate metadata, which includes information about when and where the specimen was collected and what species it belongs to. But bird eggshells often lack metadata because the eggs of different species can look very similar,” said lead author Alicia Grealy.</p>



<p>“In this study we examined 45 different eggshell specimens from ANWC that lacked metadata. We compared different sampling methods, such as swabbing the surface of eggshells, but ultimately optimised a drilling technique to retrieve eggshell powder. This provided us with sufficient DNA to identify the species while keeping the specimen intact,” Alicia said.</p>



<p>The team cross-checked the species IDs they generated by using the Atlas of Living Australia to compare the morphology of each egg specimen with published reference photographs of that taxon.</p>



<p>“We then put the method to the test on a clutch of eggs in ANWC that purportedly were of the extinct Paradise Parrot,” Alicia said.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:5cc6c8d2-50dc-4c9f-9b12-5423b6da6f18">Paradise Parrot (<em>Psephotellus pulcherrimus</em></a>) was listed as extinct in 1927. It lived in south-east Queensland and laid its nondescript white eggs inside termite mounds. Collected in 1967, the clutch of eggs had been identified as belonging to the Paradise Parrot and this has been contested for more than 50 years.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/01/Parrots_egg_ANWC-CSIRO.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44528" width="368" height="237"/><figcaption>Egg specimens are valuable records of where and when birds have bred in changing environments and can inform how their distributions are changing. This Paradise Parrot egg specimen from the Australian National Wildlife Collection was used in the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-79852-4">study published in Scientific Reports</a>.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>“Our study confirmed that this clutch belonged to the common and far from extinct <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/urn:lsid:biodiversity.org.au:afd.taxon:cb0bc816-19d5-4291-8f4f-006582bbdf50">Eastern Bluebonnet, <em>Northiella haematogaster</em></a>. Fraud and misidentifications like this can have serious implications for research that relies on accurate occurrence records for threatened and endangered species,” Alicia said.</p>



<p>“We hope our research will help egg collections in museums worldwide be better utilised for research that supports biodiversity and conservation management,” Alicia said.</p>



<p>For more information on this research:</p>



<ul><li>Read the full published article <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-79852-4">Genetic barcoding of museum eggshell improves data integrity of avian biological collections</a></li><li>Read <a href="https://blog.csiro.au/eggshell-forensics-solve-the-riddles-of-ancient-birds/">Eggshell forensics solve the riddles of ancient birds</a> on CSIROscope</li><li>Browse the <a href="https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/co16">Australian National Wildlife Collection on the ALA</a></li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Data partners</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/data-partners/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Dec 2020 06:07:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As part of our celebrations to mark 10 years of the ALA, we would like to thank all our data partners for all their contributions over the decade. Our data partners are the backbone of the ALA, providing species occurrence data as well as authoritative data for species names and classification, geospatial references, and environmental [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>As part of our celebrations to mark 10 years of the ALA, we would like to thank all our data partners for all their contributions over the decade.</p>



<p>Our data partners are the backbone of the ALA, providing species occurrence data as well as authoritative data for species names and classification, geospatial references, and environmental layers.</p>



<p>We now have over 700 data partners across research, government and citizen science and over 91 million biodiversity records.</p>



<p>Here are our top 10 data partners – in terms of number of occurrence records – in our plant, invertebrates, non-avian invertebrates and bird datasets.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="500" height="350" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-4.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44512" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-4.png 500w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-4-300x210.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="500" height="350" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-3.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44513" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-3.png 500w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-3-300x210.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="500" height="350" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44515" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-1.png 500w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-1-300x210.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="500" height="350" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-2.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44514" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-2.png 500w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/Top-10-ALA-data-partners-for-non-avian-vertebrates-2-300x210.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></figure></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Bubble bum: Rare bee wee caught on camera</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/bubble-bum-rare-bee-wee-caught-on-camera/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 05:34:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44478</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Amateur naturalist Liz Barratt caught this candid photo of a European Honey Bee on her property in Moffatdale, Queensland.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/bee-by-lizbarratt_iNaturalist-866x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44479" width="408" height="483" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/bee-by-lizbarratt_iNaturalist-866x1024.jpg 866w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/bee-by-lizbarratt_iNaturalist-254x300.jpg 254w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/bee-by-lizbarratt_iNaturalist-768x908.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/12/bee-by-lizbarratt_iNaturalist.jpg 1116w" sizes="(max-width: 408px) 100vw, 408px" /><figcaption>European Honey Bee (<a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/taxa/47219"><em>Apis mellifera</em></a>) caught on camera by Liz Barratt (All rights reserved © lizbarratt).</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>“This was the first year I’d seen our bottlebrush in full bloom and it had a lot of bees around it so I got my camera out.&nbsp; I sat there for several hours over several days just happily snapping away and watching them,” Liz said.</p>



<p>“When I downloaded the photos, I realised I had caught this shot and looked up ‘bee peeing’ on the internet. From there, I’ve been on this journey and found out more about bees than I ever expected!”&nbsp;</p>



<p>In her quest for more information, Liz contacted Entomologist Juanita Rodriguez at CSIRO’s Australian National Insect Collection, who confirmed the sighting was pretty rare.</p>



<p>“This is a rare event Liz captured and she took an excellent photo. &nbsp;Bees release liquid waste called uric acid, but they release it in such small amounts so it’s unusual to witness it – and images like this are rare,” said Juanita.</p>



<p>Uric acid is a liquid waste that is formed in a bees malpighian tubules – the insect equivalent of kidneys. Here, it’s mixed with other waste products before it is expelled out of the body. The amount of uric acid that’s released is very small. This makes an image capturing this moment very rare.</p>



<p>Because of this, Juanita encouraged Liz to upload the observation to iNaturalist Australia. This enabled the sighting to become a useful piece of biodiversity data accessible via the ALA. The <a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/observations/65599556">observation</a>, known as an occurrence record, contains useful data such as location, date, time as well as information about the species.</p>



<p>There are many different apps that feed data into the ALA. For a full list of apps and citizen science projects search the <a href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/acsa#isCitizenScience%3Dtrue%26isWorldWide%3Dfalse%26max%3D20%26sort%3DdateCreatedSort">Australian Citizen Science Project Finder</a>.</p>



<p>“I knew this was a rare photograph, and I thought there must be someone somewhere who can use this photo for bee education or similar. But I was at loss on where I could post it to share it properly,” said Liz.</p>



<p>“I was really grateful to learn about iNaturalist and am really happy to share it with others who also may find it interesting. I love my little bee photo – I’ve called him Bubble Bum due to the bubble on his bum!” </p>



<p>To upload your own observations, visit <a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/">https://inaturalist.ala.org.au</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2020</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2020/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 01:03:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44459</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter November 2020]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/ALA-Newsletter-November-2020.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-748x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44460" width="216" height="295" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-748x1024.png 748w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-219x300.png 219w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-768x1052.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image.png 891w" sizes="(max-width: 216px) 100vw, 216px" /></a></figure></div>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/ALA-Newsletter-November-2020.pdf">ALA Newsletter November 2020</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New improvements to ALA data quality filters</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-improvements-to-ala-data-quality-filters/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 22:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44445</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA Data Quality project has released its first product for beta testing. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/02/AcroRd32_2020-02-05_14-55-47.png" alt="ALA Data Quality Project icon" class="wp-image-43643" width="204" height="194"/></figure></div>



<p>Since the project launch in&nbsp;February this year the Data Quality project team has been working with&nbsp;the ALA user community&nbsp;to identify&nbsp;data quality related issues and develop solutions.&nbsp; Thank you to everyone who completed our surveys,&nbsp;contributed to our understanding of the baseline&nbsp;perceptions of data quality,&nbsp;helped to&nbsp;prioritise&nbsp;the issues,&nbsp;and tested&nbsp;solutions.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Prioritisation survey results</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>After establishing a baseline for perceptions of data quality (<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/data-quality-project-baseline-survey-results/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">see results</a>), we conducted a&nbsp;prioritisation&nbsp;survey to&nbsp;identify&nbsp;which&nbsp;issues&nbsp;the data quality project&nbsp;address&nbsp;first. The top two issues identified&nbsp;were:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>Users of the ALA are using data accessed via the ALA without filtering out records that are not fit for purpose.&nbsp;</li><li>I don’t know whether to use particular records or datasets for my purpose because quality indicators are not visible, or I don&#8217;t understand what the information means.&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p><strong>Data Quality project first release – improvements to data filters</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>In response to the issues above,&nbsp;the project developed a&nbsp;new&nbsp;capability&nbsp;to&nbsp;pre-filter search results so that lower quality records&nbsp;(such as&nbsp;those with incomplete or inconsistent data)&nbsp;are not shown unless they are actively included.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The filters can be seen in a new&nbsp;Data Profile&nbsp;section&nbsp;above the&nbsp;search results.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/image.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44446" width="680" height="147" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/image.png 602w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/image-300x65.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /></figure>



<p>The new release enables users to switch filters on&nbsp;or&nbsp;off&nbsp;and manage&nbsp;them&nbsp;as a group or individually.&nbsp;Information is available on the&nbsp;fields and data that make up the filters&nbsp;through mouse-over text and&nbsp;clickable info icons (i).&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>To get involved, <a href="https://biocache-dq-beta.ala.org.au/occurrences/search?q=">join beta testing of the new Data profiles</a> feature. &nbsp;</p>



<p>To learn more about the&nbsp;new data filter features,&nbsp;read&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000240256-getting-started-with-the-data-quality-filters" target="_blank">Getting started with the Data profiles</a>&nbsp;</p>



<p>For more information on the&nbsp;data quality project please visit the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/data-quality-project/" target="_blank">Data Quality&nbsp;project page</a>&nbsp;or&nbsp;contact us at&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="mailto:dataquality@ala.org.au" target="_blank">dataquality@ala.org.au</a>.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guest editorial: ALA newsletter November 2020</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/guest-editorial/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 22:42:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s a pleasure to be invited to provide this guest editorial to help celebrate the Atlas of Living Australia’s 10th anniversary. The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was developed in 2010 to support the needs of the national and international research community for timely access to Australian biodiversity data. In this time, it has grown [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It’s a pleasure to be invited to provide this guest editorial to help celebrate the Atlas of Living Australia’s 10<sup>th</sup> anniversary.</p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was developed in 2010 to support the needs of the national and international research community for timely access to Australian biodiversity data. In this time, it has grown into one of the world’s foremost biodiversity infrastructures and leads Australia’s commitment to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (<a href="https://www.gbif.org/">GBIF</a>).</p>



<p>The Australian biodiversity information community, partnering with the Australian Government through the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (<a href="https://www.education.gov.au/national-collaborative-research-infrastructure-strategy-ncris">NCRIS</a>), should be proud of our national and global achievements. One of many remarkable achievements is the <a href="https://living-atlases.gbif.org/">international Living Atlases</a> community. This now delivers science impact globally through 27 national atlases built on ALA-developed infrastructure, shared Australian capability and knowledge.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1024x682.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44450" width="380" height="253" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-2048x1363.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1920x1278.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" /><figcaption>The museum and herbaria communities were fundamental to the origins of the Atlas of Living Australia. Image: Australian Tree Seed Centre CSIRO Canberra</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>In this anniversary year, it’s timely to reflect on the history of the ALA. Its origins owe much to the vision, commitment and partnerships that were already in place in the museums, collections and herbaria sectors and we are proud to be part of this story. In the late 1990s, the peak body for herbaria in the region, the Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria (CHAH) formed a consortium with the Australian Biological Resources Study (ABRS) to digitise and database specimens resulting in the Australasian Virtual Herbarium (<a href="https://avh.ala.org.au/">AVH</a>).</p>



<p>The museum community has a similar story. The zoological collections formed the Council of Heads of Australian Faunal Collections (CHAFC) in 1992 with a national viewpoint on museum-held biodiversity data issues, an exchange of ideas and interactions with ABRS and Environmental Information Resources Network within what is now the Department of Agriculture, Water and Environment. Following the success of the AVH, CHAFC sought to improve the sharing of data through then newly evolving web technology. This resulted in the Online Zoological Collections of Australian Museums, or <a href="https://ozcam.org.au/">OZCAM</a> in 2002.</p>



<p>The establishment of the ALA owes its foundation to the prior existence of AVH and OZCAM and this history runs deep in the architecture of the ALA. More importantly the strength of these existing networks, partnerships and governance models provided a sound foundation for accelerating the vision under the newly formed NCRIS program in 2007.</p>



<p>From its origins in the collections sector, the ALA has astutely expanded its remit to broaden the portfolio of data and services it offers Australian science and decision-making. The inclusion of biodiversity data from state government agencies, major research programs and its support of the citizen sector has significantly improved our understanding of Australia’s biodiversity.</p>



<p>The events we’ve witnessed in 2020 provide a timely reminder of the criticality of maintaining a comprehensive, representative and adequate national biodiversity infrastructure. It is fundamental to improving our understanding of the impact of current and future bushfires and other environmental threats, on biodiversity and supporting ensuing restoration efforts. It provides fundamental data to help understand the global behaviour of zoonotic diseases and their role in future pandemics, and it can position Australia to more effectively deal with biosecurity risks that impact our environment and economy.</p>



<p>Reflecting on the strategic priorities for our sector – &nbsp;for example around higher throughput digitisation of our collections and the rapid growth in genomics-based methods in biodiversity sciences – &nbsp;we believe we are extremely well placed to grow and evolve to meet these challenges through our ongoing partnerships with the ALA.</p>



<p>In closing, we acknowledge the significant vision and contribution made through the Australian Government’s NCRIS program in realising the ALA vision, and the partnerships that have been so fundamental to its success. This includes the thought leaders, the data partners and ALA’s institutional supporters that can rightfully be proud of what Australia has achieved.</p>



<p><strong>Cameron Slatyer</strong><br>Branch Manager | Life and Geosciences<br>Australian Museum Research Institute, Science and Learning, Australian Museum&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Professor Darren Crayn</strong><br>Director<br>Australian Tropical Herbarium</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
