<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:31:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.4.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Transforming Australia’s biological collections to open data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-transforming-australias-biological-collections-to-open-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 23:40:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49259</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[View the recording from the ALA's first webinar of 2024.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) first webinar of 2024 showcased a selection of amazing projects from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>. This important initiative supports the mobilisation of Australia’s biodiversity data which may not yet be digital, making it available through the ALA, and internationally to the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a>. By improving digital access, the program delivers stronger research and conservation outcomes for Australia’s unique biodiversity.</p>



<p>Hear from three projects that were supported through the program. Learn about the transformative power of biodiversity data, and how previously inaccessible physical specimens in biological collections can be made available as open data.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by CSIRO.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar Transforming Australia’s biological collections to open data   Web" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/G7GIp7LTryk?start=111&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Weblink to recording: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7GIp7LTryk&amp;t=111s" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G7GIp7LTryk&amp;t=111s</a>. The event was hosted on 20 Feb 2024 at 11AM AEDT. It was attended by more than 400 live viewers on the day. </figcaption></figure>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<p><strong>Dr David Hocking</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/DavidHocking-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6ED9FEC654AB56C83666A26317AF962652BBB6F2" alt="Dr David Hocking"/></figure>



<p>Dr David Hocking is the Senior Curator of Vertebrate Zoology at the Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery (TMAG). TMAG houses the Tasmanian Devil Tissue Bioarchive and also curates a growing collection of frozen tissue specimens for a wide range of vertebrate wildlife. The 2023 Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program allowed TMAG to digitise a remaining bulk collection of devil tissues and establish a new TMAG Tissue Collection on the ALA providing a public portal into this growing resource of specimens for future research and analysis.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Mieke Strong</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/MiekeStrong-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=6C8427B3B9EB5A9979FE4527484D02147E28644D" alt="Dr Mieke Strong"/></figure>



<p>Mieke has over 15 years working and studying biological sciences and has a PhD in the taxonomy of fish parasites from the University of Queensland and the Queensland Museum. She has worked as a technical officer at the Department of Fisheries in Western Australia, as a researcher at the Western Australian Museum (terrestrial invertebrates), and as an environmental consultant at Biota Environmental Sciences. As part of her current role at Gaia Resources, Mieke interest is in determining data formatting and data requirements for natural sciences and collections projects, focusing on data standards.</p>



<p><strong>Dean Beasley</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/DeanBeasley-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=AAB8F0C1D16AA865B158CF43E4385C520DF0689E" alt="Dean Beasley"/></figure>



<p>Dean Beasley joined Queensland Museum in 2019, and administer the Vernon Collection Management System used to catalogue Biodiversity &amp; Geosciences specimens as well as Cultures &amp; Histories objects held by the museum. The Vernon database holds over 1.1 million records. Its functionality includes, but is not limited to, processes that assist with accessioning specimens and objects, managing incoming and outgoing loans, acquisition proposals, tracking specimen and object locations, valuations, managing exhibitions, storing associated images and documentation. Prior to QM, Dean worked for the Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries (DAF) within the Plant Pathology Herbarium (2000) and Insect Collection (2008), where he administered the KE EMu database, and developed Lucid keys to plant pathogens.</p>



<p><strong>Dr Kit Prendergast</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/KitPrendergast-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=FEF01E130CBAACECB8E5D599B69A0AF9759E27FB" alt="Dr Kit Prendergast"/></figure>



<p>Dr Kit Prendergast is a native bee researcher. She has conducted native bee biodiversity surveys across the Swan Coastal Plain and Jarrah forest of southwest of Western Australia, the wheatbelt, Gascoyne and Goldfields of WA, and Traditional landowner lands in northern Western Australia for her PhD, surveys for local and state government, land care groups, and communities. She has amassed an incredible collection of native bee specimens, which includes new range records, species not collected for decades, and many undescribed species. Thanks to the ALA Data Mobilisation Program, these specimens are finally making their way onto the map and being catalogued at the WA Museum, representing a rich dataset for researchers now and in the future.</p>



<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Call for applications – GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/call-for-applications-gbif-2024-graduate-researchers-award/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 22:15:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49206</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are open for the GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award! This award is an annual program aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics at the Masters and PhD student level.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="320" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1024x320.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49207" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1024x320.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-300x94.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-768x240.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1536x480.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15-1920x600.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/GRA-2024-hero4-15.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The 2024 programme will provide two €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD $8,200) recognising the work of two early-career researchers. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> (GBIF). The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA are also accessible via GBIF.</p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p><strong><em><mark>Australian applications to the ALA are due by 31st May 2024.</mark></em></strong></p>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;if you require further information.</p>



<p>A jury organised by <a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a> will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat.</p>



<p>Note: Awardees are expected to acknowledge GBIF support when disseminating research results via peer-reviewed publications, presentations at professional meetings, and other media.</p>



<p><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></p>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol start="1">
<li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)</li>



<li><strong>Project description</strong> (<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em> <em>font</em>) that describes:<br>a. How the research advances biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity.<br>b. <strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.</li>



<li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.</li>



<li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate program of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li>
</ol>



<p><strong>How to submit an application to the ALA (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol start="1">
<li>Visit the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/0YedTUAf3Nk14JKZqBn0a/call-opens-for-nominations-to-2024-gbif-graduate-researchers-award#_national-deadlines-for-2024">GBIF 2024 Graduate Researchers Award</a> page and follow the instructions. <br></li>



<li>Submit your nominations to <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a> with ‘2024 GBIF Graduate Researchers Application _YOUR NAME’ in the subject line by <strong>31st May 2024.</strong></li>
</ol>



<p>The criteria for the awards include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Originality and innovation</li>



<li>Use of and strategic significance for data accessed through GBIF</li>



<li>Measurable effectiveness and impact in advancing biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/0YedTUAf3Nk14JKZqBn0a/call-opens-for-nominations-to-2024-gbif-graduate-researchers-award#_national-deadlines-for-2024">GBIF</a> website.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blog/">&nbsp;Back to Articles</a></p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>International Day of Women and Girls in Science</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/international-day-of-women-and-girls-in-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 01:45:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49212</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[February 11th 2024 is the United Nations International Day of Women and Girls in Science. It’s an opportunity to celebrate the achievements of women and girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), whilst acknowledging the persistent gaps in representation and equality in these fields. We spoke to one of the Atlas of Living Australia’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>February 11th 2024 is the <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/women-and-girls-in-science-day">United Nations International Day of Women and Girls in Science</a>. It’s an opportunity to celebrate the achievements of women and girls in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM), whilst acknowledging the persistent gaps in representation and equality in these fields.</p>



<p>We spoke to one of the Atlas of Living Australia’s (ALA) current internship students Clara Peers Tejero about what motivated her to pursue higher education in STEM.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49213" style="width:365px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-2048x2048.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara-profile-pic-1920x1920.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Clara Peers Tejero</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Q: What degree are you currently studying?</strong></p>



<p>I’m currently studying at <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/">UNSW</a> and finishing a double degree in Bioinformatic Engineering and Science (Genetics).</p>



<p><strong>Q: What made you decide to study science?</strong></p>



<p>I decided to study science because it’s a way to learn more about how the world works. I love it because I’m constantly learning new things. Science gives us a much deeper understanding about <strong>everything</strong>: from the mechanisms of genomics and personalised medicine to the wonders of exoplanet exploration, and from the complexities of neuroscience and brain plasticity to the delicate balance of Earth&#8217;s biodiversity and the strategies for its conservation. The more you learn, the more amazed you are!</p>



<p><strong>Q: What’s your internship project at the ALA focused on?</strong></p>



<p>My project is focused on <a href="https://ecoassets.org.au/">EcoAssets</a> which combines environmental data collected from three national research infrastructures – the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">ALA</a>, the Integrated Marine Observing System (<a href="https://imos.org.au/">IMOS</a>) and the Terrestrial Ecosystem Research Network (<a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a>). I’m looking at ways to improve how people interact with this data, by revamping the website and exploring how to communicate the data. I have been learning so much about data visualisation and how to make it more interesting and interactive for users.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="943" height="911" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49214" style="width:499px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample.png 943w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample-300x290.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/02/Clara_EcoAssetsDataVizExample-768x742.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 943px) 100vw, 943px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Data visualisation created by Clara Peers Tejero using ALA&#8217;s galah coding package. </figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Q: Do you have any advice that you would give to somebody considering studying science?</strong></p>



<p>I would say: go for it! There are so many different fields of study in science that I would suggest exploring your areas of interest. Stay up to date on the latest breakthroughs and research happening and seek inspiration from scientists who are doing exciting work in that area.</p>



<p>And make sure to learn some basic coding/programming skills! This will be so useful (even essential) no matter what you end up studying or working in.</p>



<p><strong>Where to find Clara:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/clara-peers-tejero-7b7b30158/">LinkedIn</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protecting Australian biodiversity with data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/protecting-australian-biodiversity-with-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2024 22:03:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47966</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Meet our ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species. While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Meet our ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners</strong></p>



<p>As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species.</p>



<p>While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used to address specific research goals, these data often require additional resources to ensure they can be digitised and made available nationally as open data.</p>



<p>To improve data accessibility the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) launched the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a> in 2022. This program is designed to support Australian museums, biological collections, herbaria, and research teams to digitise their data, and making it available through the ALA, and internationally through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1024x577.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49179" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/01/Fungi-Friday-24.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program banner.</figcaption></figure>



<p class="has-text-align-left">Through a nationally competitive application process, projects were awarded grants to digitise their priority biodiversity data. The output from this program will enable data on rare and unique species to become open and accessible through the ALA. Using FAIR principles (findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable), this data will support research, decision-making and conservation efforts to better protect Australian biodiversity.</p>



<p><strong>Funded projects:</strong></p>



<p><strong>2022 projects</strong>:</p>



<ul type="1">
<li>New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, NSW – mobilising plant pest and disease data from the NSW Biosecurity Collections (~600,000 records).</li>



<li>South Australia Museum (SAM), SA– mobilise the SAM’s Australian Biological Tissues Collection of 39 donated frozen tissue collections of Australian freshwater fishes (around 90% of all known species and ~46,000 records).</li>



<li>Queensland Museum Network, QLD – mobilising and enhancing data from the Cribb Australian Fish Trematode Collection (&gt;20,000 records of &gt;1,000 fish species).</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery, TAS – mobilising wildlife molecular and tissue data (&gt; 8,500 sample vials and 1,650 formalin-fixed specimens in the histology collection).</li>



<li>Edith Cowan University, WA – mobilising plant and fungi data from the Robert Brown Herbarium.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and Parks Authority, WA – mobilising data in the Kings Park and Botanic Garden Herbarium collection (18,200 specimens).</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>2023 projects:</strong></p>



<ul type="1">
<li>National Herbarium of Victoria, Royal Botanic Gardens of Victoria – mobilising more than 5,000 specimen-based occurrence data records from Australian macroalgae.</li>



<li>Western Australian Museum – mobilising thousands of native bee data records from physical specimens collected southwestern WA, representing more than 200 bee species.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and State Herbarium, South Australia – making &gt;30,000 bryophyte and &gt;6,000 lichen records available to the ALA through digitisation of physical collection labels.</li>



<li>D’Estrees Entomology and Science Services – delivery of 7,000 -10,000 insect occurrence records from Kangaroo Island, focused on underrepresented taxa.</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery – mobilising more than 15,000 invertebrate species records representing Tasmanian spiders, echinoderms, cnidarians and annelids.</li>
</ul>



<p>Congratulations to the successful projects, we look forward to working with them to make their data available nationally. We’d like to also acknowledge the applications that were not successful as they were universally excellent making our assessment process very challenging. We are also grateful to the independent review panel for their work in reviewing proposals and selecting a fantastic suite of final recipients.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="200" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47969" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Leanne Wheaton working on collections specimens at South Australia Museum, Photo Credit Denis Smith, South Australia Museum. </figcaption></figure>



<p>The 2024 grant round for the Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program will open for applications in&nbsp;<strong>late autumn 2024</strong>. Keep an eye on the ALA website, social media channels and blogs for more information shortly.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA’s International Biodiversity Engagements</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/alas-international-biodiversity-engagements/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2023 22:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48981</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and CSIRO’s National Research Collections Australia were proud to host both the&#160;Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG) Annual Conference&#160;in Hobart and the&#160;30th Annual Governing Board Meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility&#160;(GBIF) in Canberra in October 2023. The CSIRO has had a long history of association with both organisations, having been [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and CSIRO’s National Research Collections Australia were proud to host both the&nbsp;Biodiversity Information Standards (<a href="https://www.tdwg.org/conferences/2023/">TDWG) Annual Conference</a>&nbsp;in Hobart and the&nbsp;<a href="https://gb30.gbif.org/">30th Annual Governing Board Meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility&nbsp;(GBIF)</a> in Canberra in October 2023. The CSIRO has had a long history of association with both organisations, having been involved with TDWG and GBIF since they were established in 1985 and 2001 respectively.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="452" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-1024x452.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48506" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-1024x452.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-300x132.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-768x339.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient.jpg 1478w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">TDWG 2023 logo</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p><strong>TDWG Annual Conference (9-13 October, Hobart)</strong></p>



<p>The TDWG Annual Conference is a major international event for the biodiversity informatics community. It is a forum for researchers and practitioners to share their latest work, discuss new developments in biodiversity informatics standards and network with colleagues from around the world.</p>



<p>The ALA and CSIRO were proud to host the TDWG 2023 conference in Hobart, having last hosted the conference in Australia in 2008 (in Fremantle). The conference covered a wide range of topics, including:</p>



<ul>
<li>Biodiversity data standards for documentation and data interchange</li>



<li>Data management tools and services</li>



<li>Data sharing and access</li>



<li>Data use in biodiversity research, policy, and practice.</li>
</ul>



<p>The TDWG 2023 Annual Conference was attended by 166 participants from 26 countries, with a further 143 participants joining virtually. The event was comprised of four days of symposium presentations and discussions and one day of excursions around Hobart. The ALA team presented&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/where-to-find-the-atlas-of-living-australia-this-year/">10 abstracts</a>&nbsp;across the conference and was involved in coordinating nine symposia and workshops.</p>



<p><em>“One foundation reason that the ALA and GBIF can exist is that, many years ago, the biodiversity community got together and created standards for how to record and share data. Those standards continue to be developed, refined and promoted through TDWG. And it all happens through people talking with each other. ALA and NRCA were proud to offer Hobart as a scenic backdrop to the vital networking, conversations and stimulating presentations that make TDWG a vibrant community of volunteers keeping biodiversity data being shared,” </em>said Dr Ely Wallis, Chair of the TDWG Executive.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-15-1024x577.png" alt="Collage of Australian animals on a cream coloured background" class="wp-image-48982" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-15-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-15-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-15-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-15-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-15.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>GB30 graphic</em></p>



<p><strong>GBIF and the Governing Board</strong></p>



<p>The Global Biodiversity Information Facility (<a href="http://www.gbif.org.au/">GBIF</a>) is an international network and data infrastructure funded by the world’s governments and aims at providing anyone, anywhere, open access to data about all types of life on Earth. The ALA is the Australian node of GBIF providing over 110,000 million biodiversity species occurrence records to GBIF annually.</p>



<p>The GBIF Governing Board are responsible for setting the organisation’s strategic direction and overseeing its operations. In accordance with the cadence of the Governing Board to meet once per year, the ALA and CSIRO were proud to host the 30th Annual Governing Board Meeting in Canberra.</p>



<p>The meeting discussed a range of topics, including:</p>



<ul>
<li>The GBIF 2030 Strategy</li>



<li>The GBIF Secretariat’s work plan for 2024-2025</li>



<li>The GBIF funding model</li>



<li>GBIF’s engagement with other international organisations.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Governing Board and associated events program (15- 20 October, Canberra)</strong></p>



<p>In addition to hosting the Annual Governing Board Meeting, the ALA and CSIRO facilitated several other events throughout the week, working closely with the GBIF Secretariat to develop the agenda, arrange the logistics, and promote the meeting to the international community.</p>



<p>The international GBIF delegation was welcomed to the Canberra CSIRO offices at Black Mountain on 15- 16 October for two days of Nodes training, followed by the Global GBIF Nodes Meeting on 17 October (also at CSIRO). We welcomed 45 participants in-person from 30 countries and nine organisations to the Nodes Meeting, with a further 28 individuals from 12 countries and 6 organisations participating online.</p>



<p>On 18 October, the GBIF 30<sup>th</sup>&nbsp;Annual Governing Board meeting (GB30) kicked off at the National Portrait Gallery with a gala dinner hosted at the National Museum of Australia where Minister for the Environment and Water the Hon Tanya Plibersek delivered an opening&nbsp;<a href="https://www.tanyaplibersek.com/media/speeches/speech-to-the-global-diversity-information-facility-gala-dinner/">speech</a>, affirming Australia’s commitment to collaboration on international biodiversity matters and informed by robust biodiversity data. The second day of GB30 continued at the National Portrait Gallery.</p>



<p>The week concluded on Friday, with the ALA and CSIRO hosting an international Symposium at CSIRO titled <em>The Changing Face of Biological Collections – data, science </em>and applications. This event involved GBIF delegates as well as a suite of national stakeholders to present, discuss and explore the increasingly important role of biological collections in supporting innovative biodiversity science.</p>



<p><em>“It was fantastic to see so many inspiring and passionate international delegates come together to advance discussions on global biodiversity data. The collective knowledge at an event such as the GBIF Governing Board Meeting is immeasurable. By connecting through such forums, we create pathways to further learn and collaborate, and by doing so make biodiversity data more accessible to everyone. We are particularly grateful to Australia for hosting such a marvellous event,”</em> said Dr Olaf Banki, Executive Secretary, Catalogue of Life.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="540" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-1024x540.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48983" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-1024x540.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-300x158.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-768x405.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-1536x810.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-2048x1080.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1-1920x1012.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Global Biodiversity Information Facility Governing Board international delegation at the National Portrait Gallery, Canberra.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Australian Virtual Seed Bank</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/australian-virtual-seed-bank/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Nov 2023 22:39:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48936</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 2023, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and the Australian Seed Bank Partnership (ASBP) collaborated to launch a new version of the Australian Seed Bank Online, the Australian Virtual Seed Bank&#160;(AVSB). &#160;The AVSB shares sustainable seed collecting and banking practices and provides open-access information about both seed collections and the germination protocols used across [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In 2023, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and the <a>Australian Seed Bank Partnership </a>(ASBP) collaborated to launch a new version of the Australian Seed Bank Online, the <a href="https://seedbank.ala.org.au/">Australian Virtual Seed Bank</a>&nbsp;(AVSB). &nbsp;The AVSB shares sustainable seed collecting and banking practices and provides open-access information about both seed collections and the germination protocols used across seed banks in Australia. Primarily used by seed curators, collectors, research community members, students, industry and government, the AVSB is an essential resource for preserving critical plant information on Australian plant biodiversity and is hosted by the ALA.</p>



<p>The ALA team has worked in <a>close collaboration</a> with the ASBP to develop this capability, bringing together subject matter experts and software developers to produce a world-class innovative digital platform. The AVSB is a refreshed digital open-access resource that has been designed to increase the accessibility and usability of information about Australian plants. It links seed bank data with images, taxonomic and occurrence data in the ALA and collection, trait and genomic data from other sources to be accessible via a single online platform. The AVSB is the first ALA application to implement a <a href="https://ala.org.au/current-projects/extended-data-model-project/">new </a><a>type of ALA database</a> which allows for complex relationships between different types of data and seed bank activities to be accurately represented and navigated. The AVSB was developed over two years, as part of an iterative process, continually testing and seeking feedback from the broader seed bank community.<a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="788" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-1200-×-924px-15-1024x788.png" alt="Golden wattle with the ALA and ASBP logos" class="wp-image-48937" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-1200-×-924px-15-1024x788.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-1200-×-924px-15-300x231.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-1200-×-924px-15-768x591.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/Fungi-Friday-1200-×-924px-15.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>‘The Australian Seed Bank Partnership is an alliance of 14 organisations, bringing together expertise from Australia’s leading botanic gardens, state environment agencies and NGOs. Developing and sharing knowledge is a high priority for us and working with the ALA on the new ASBO portal allows partners to share significantly more data than we have in the past. We can’t wait to share the portal with the conservation community’&nbsp;</em>said Dr Ameila Martyn Yenson A/g National Coordinator Australian Seed Bank Partnership.</p>



<p>The AVSB&#8217;s user-friendly format offers a unique opportunity to deep-dive into the world of ex-situ collections across Australia and shares hundreds of years of collective experience from seed experts across the topics of seed collection, storage, research, ecology, germination, and more. Access the AVSB here:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.seedpartnership.org.au/initiatives/australian-virtual-seed-bank/">https://www.seedpartnership.org.au/initiatives/australian-virtual-seed-bank/</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="772" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/11/AVSB-1024x772.jpg" alt="Black web interface with a picture of a watering can and pot plant. text reads open access to Australia's seed data." class="wp-image-49009" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/11/AVSB-1024x772.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/11/AVSB-300x226.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/11/AVSB-768x579.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/11/AVSB.jpg 1218w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Australian Virtual Seed Bank online portal.</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spooky Species</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/spooky-species/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 22:05:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47475</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Does it croak or growl, have fangs or howl? Does it scream at night or give you a fright? 🎃 Many iconic living (or dead) things that are seen around Halloween are inspired by species in the natural world! Check out some of the most spook-tacular Aussie species! Goblin Shark (Mitsukurina owstoni) Talk about a [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Does it croak or growl, have fangs or howl? Does it scream at night or give you a fright? <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f383.png" alt="🎃" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>



<p>Many iconic living (or dead) things that are seen around Halloween are inspired by species in the natural world! Check out some of the most spook-tacular Aussie species!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1009" height="541" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47481" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC.jpg 1009w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC-300x161.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC-768x412.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1009px) 100vw, 1009px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Goblin Shark (<em>Mitsukurina owstoni</em>) Museums Victoria CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/b1b5f1e3-1efa-4d18-b8f7-d26731b964cc#overview">Goblin Shark (<em>Mitsukurina owstoni</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>Talk about a creature from nightmares, the Goblin Shark is one of the most illusive deep-sea sharks known to scientists with a distinctive blade-like snout and pink skin. Specimens have been found along continental slopes at distances up to 1.3 km deep, measuring 3-4 metres in length. The Goblin Shark has distinctive mouthparts, specialised for rapid projection as their jaws can extend and retract to catch prey.</p>



<p>They are the only extant member of the&nbsp;<em>Mitsukurina</em>&nbsp;genus, often called a ‘living fossil’ as this genus traces back 125 million years. These sharks are incredibly illusive, with limited specimens recorded around NSW, Victoria and Tasmania in Australia, as well as Portugal and Japan. Not much is known about the reproductive life cycle of this species as a pregnant Goblin Shark has never been recorded.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47480" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1920x1440.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bronze Orange Bug (<em>Musgraveia sulciventris</em>) Erin Roger CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><u><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/201952">Bronze Orange Bug</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/201952"><em>Musgraveia sulciventris</em></a>)</u></strong></p>



<p>If the pumpkin-orange colour doesn’t scare you off, maybe its stench will! This stinkbug produces a rotten-smelling spray from the chemical ‘cimicine.’ This spray doesn’t just pack a pungent punch, its main function is to be a defensive mechanism against predators – most commonly other arthropods and birds – which can be lethal to these species. To humans, the spray can cause significant irritation. This is a classic case of ‘look but don’t touch’, no matter your species!</p>



<p>As eggs and nymphs, Bronze Orange Bugs are green in colour but as they mature through their five instar stages of development, they acquire their distinctive orange colour to resemble citrus leaves. They are considered pests in commercial citrus orchards across eastern Australia.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47482" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1920x1440.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Jimsonweed (<em>Datura stramonium)</em> Ecocentric_Consultulting CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/55854">Jimsonweed</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/55854"><em>Datura stramonium</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>It’s not just it’s physical appearance that’s scary, this plant’s impact on biosecurity is equally terrifying.</p>



<p>Also known as the ‘cemetery flower’ or ‘common thorn apple’, this plant is one of the most invasive noxious weeds around the world, including in Australia. It has been known to poison humans and animals, reduce pasture productivity and compete with native flora.</p>



<p>A member of the nightshade family, Jimsonweed was originally introduced in Australia in the 1800s for medicinal and ornamental purposes. The most toxic part of the plant are its black seeds which disperse through water, contaminated hay and mud stuck to vehicles.&nbsp;The spiny seed capsule is as aggressive as it looks and will injure those who dare to touch…</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-1024x683.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47478" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau.jpeg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Spectacled Flying Fox (<em>Pteropus conspicillatus</em>) Kcomeau CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/27d443cb-290b-4d53-8010-5e230f840d67">Spectacled Flying Fox (<em>Pteropus conspicillatus</em></a><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/5ff29bca-f02f-468f-9f96-9ae956015e01">)</a></strong></p>



<p>Australia is home to more than 90 species of bats including both mega bats and micro bats. Although some bat species around the world do feed on blood (and are most likely the inspiration for Halloween stories), the Spectacled Flying Fox is more likely bring you joy rather than terror!</p>



<p>These endangered fruit bats live in the northern tropics and feed on native fruits, flowers, and myrtle plants. They play a pivotal role in rainforest ecosystems as seed dispersers and pollinators. Aptly named, the Spectacled Flying Fox has light yellow fur around its eyes and snout giving the appearance that its wearing glasses. They typically live to be around 12 -15 years old in the wild but have been known to live up to 30 years old in captivity.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-1024x682.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47479" style="width:1000px;height:666px" width="1000" height="666" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-1536x1023.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC.jpg 1560w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Far Eastern Curlew (<em>Numenius madagascariensis</em>) Mark Ayres CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/3898">Far Eastern Curlew</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/3898"><em>Numenius madagascariensis</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>A shriek in the night, a blood curdling scream, you investigate the source only to find…a Far Eastern Curlew?</p>



<p>Known for making exceptionally long migratory travels to breed between northern and southern hemispheres, Far Eastern Curlews are also iconic for their scream-like vocalisation calls.&nbsp;They use their hauntingly beautiful calls as part of mating displays and to assert dominance over their territory.</p>



<p>With a long scimitar-shaped beak which can be more than 50% the length of their body and dark-streaked plumage, the Far Eastern Curlew is the largest shorebird in the world. This species is reliant on mudflats and mangrove swamps for feeding and breeding. Unfortunately, this species is listed as ‘endangered’ due to loss of habitat, causing population decline across their ranges.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="608" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1024x608.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47477" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1024x608.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-300x178.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-768x456.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1536x911.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1920x1139.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Speckled Orbweaver (<em>Araneus circulissparsus)</em> Jackie Lien CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/487451">Speckled Orbweaver</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/487451"><em>Araneus circulissparsus</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>Hairy, spotty and slime green! Could this spider be the ultimate creature for Halloween?</p>



<p>Orbweaver spiders are common across Australia, known for making intricate, sticky webs at night to catch prey. Orbweavers occupy crevices and leaves during the day, and if they feel significantly threatened, they will drop to the ground and ‘play dead.’</p>



<p>The Speckled Orbweaver prefers to occupy green foliage, to blend in with the surroundings. As with many spider species, females are larger than males at approximately 6mm in length, with males 3mm in length.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47526" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1920x1280.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Ghost Fungus (<em>Omphalotus nidiformis</em>) Monica Knipler CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><u><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/id.biodiversity.org.au/node/fungi/60094367">Ghost Fungus <em>(Omphalotus nidiformis</em></a></u></strong>)</p>



<p>Like something out of a fairy-tale, Ghost Fungi glow through their gills with a green-tinged light. They emit ‘cold light’ where less than 20% of light emitted is capable of radiating heat. Ghost Fungi, and other bioluminescent creatures, fluoresce using a compound called ‘luciferin’. They grow on dead or decaying wood and are commonly found across Australia in temperate areas. The exact reason this species uses bioluminescence is not known, however a theory is that by glowing the fungi attracts insects which disperse its spores.</p>



<p>Ghost Fungi are poisonous if consumed, however are often mistaken for Oyster Mushrooms due to their similar fan-like appearance and milky-white colouration in the daytime.</p>



<p>To learn how to upload species records and contribute to the Atlas of Living Australia, check our this <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/home/record-a-sighting/">link</a>.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter October 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-october-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2023 03:43:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48989</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out the ALA&#8217;s October 2023 Newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p id="block-e6556f64-c2e0-49e7-b903-7825bd5b688f">Check out the ALA&#8217;s <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://us14.campaign-archive.com/?u=b238aea31bbd4bd103ff7368c&amp;id=63540c5ced" target="_blank">October 2023 Newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://us14.campaign-archive.com/?u=b238aea31bbd4bd103ff7368c&amp;id=63540c5ced" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="657" height="1021" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/newsletter-oct23.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48990" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/newsletter-oct23.png 657w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/newsletter-oct23-193x300.png 193w" sizes="(max-width: 657px) 100vw, 657px" /></a></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; October 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-october-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 22:44:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48911</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the October 2023 edition of our ALA newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td>It’s been an exciting month for the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), CSIRO and our national partners as we welcomed the world’s biodiversity data community to Hobart and Canberra for a series of conferences, meetings and symposia. Our journey began by hosting this year’s annual meeting of the biodiversity data standards group <a href="https://tdwg2023.zohobackstage.com.au/TDWG2023">TDWG</a> in Hobart from October 9<sup>th</sup> to 13<sup>th</sup>. The event welcomed 166 participants from 26 countries (with 143 joining virtually) to present, learn and connect. We are grateful to those who continue the work of TDWG and biodiversity data standards. The TDWG-maintained Darwin Core standard has underpinned so many of the world&#8217;s biodiversity data systems, including the ALA, and ensures interoperable biodiversity data can move freely across platforms and borders. Events such as the TDWG annual meeting are fundamental in supporting the evolution of the standard and learning about the biodiversity science and applications it enables. <br><br>TDWG was a timely precursor to our next series of events hosted in Canberra and framed around the two-day Governing Board meeting of the <a href="https://gb30.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF).</a> Australia last hosted the fourth Governing Board meeting (GB04) in 2002 at the National Academy of Sciences and then welcomed 18 countries to Canberra. 21 years later, we hosted 45 people from 30 countries at the National Portrait Gallery and CSIRO (with a further 28 participants joining online from 12 countries) to govern, support and grow the GBIF network. We were pleased to be joined by the Honourable Minister for the Environment and Water Tanya Plibersek at the gala dinner hosted at the National Museum of Australia. <a href="https://minister.dcceew.gov.au/plibersek/speeches/speech-global-diversity-information-facility-gala-dinner" data-type="link" data-id="https://minister.dcceew.gov.au/plibersek/speeches/speech-global-diversity-information-facility-gala-dinner">The Minister&#8217;s address</a> affirmed the importance of data in supporting national and international biodiversity policy priorities and the ALA looks forward to working with our international and national partners to support these. <br><br>Hosting this series of international meetings highlights the leadership role that Australia plays, and the ALA is grateful to the individuals and teams that have put such a strong foundation in place over more than a decade. These partnerships also highlight the importance of international collaboration in improving the national biodiversity data landscape, and ultimately our ability to understand, conserve and enhance the world’s biodiversity. I’m grateful to our team and our fellow CSIRO colleagues who played such an important role in hosting and welcoming our international guests to Australia.</td></tr></tbody></table></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-1024x768.jpg" alt="group of 11 people standing in front of a TDWG banner in a conference room" class="wp-image-48959" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/20231013_085534-1-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The ALA&#8217;s delegation at the TDWG conference in Hobart.</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1024x540.jpg" alt="Large group of people in front of the National Portrait Gallery" class="wp-image-48960" style="width:836px;height:441px" width="836" height="441" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1024x540.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-300x158.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-768x405.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1536x810.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-2048x1080.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_0079-1920x1012.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 836px) 100vw, 836px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Global Biodiversity Information Facility Governing Board international delegation at the National Portrait Gallery.</figcaption></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://minister.dcceew.gov.au/plibersek/speeches/speech-global-diversity-information-facility-gala-dinner"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="660" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR-1024x660.jpg" alt="Hon Tanya Plibersek giving her speech" class="wp-image-48961" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR-1024x660.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR-300x193.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR-768x495.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR-1536x989.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR-1920x1237.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/10/R62_9968-Enhanced-NR.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Minister for the Environment and Water Hon Tanya Plibersek, giving her speech at the GBIF gala dinner. </figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Elevating ALA’s Data Security with OpenID Connect</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/elevating-alas-data-security-with-openid-connect/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 04:17:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48865</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Australia’s national biodiversity data infrastructure, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is committed to providing reliable and secure data access to our users. In line with this commitment, we are excited to announce our transition to OpenID Connect (OIDC) authentication, which will help to streamline the process for accessing data within the ALA across [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="223" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-1024x223.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48871" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-1024x223.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-300x65.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-768x167.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-1536x335.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner.png 1867w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>As Australia’s national biodiversity data infrastructure, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is committed to providing reliable and secure data access to our users. In line with this commitment, we are excited to announce our transition to OpenID Connect (OIDC) authentication, which will help to streamline the process for accessing data within the ALA across multiple platforms.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-oidc">What is OIDC?</h2>



<p>With OIDC, you can log in to multiple platforms using a single set of sign-in credentials while ensuring that your personal information is secure and private.</p>



<p>OIDC is an identity layer built on top of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://oauth.net/2/" target="_blank">OAuth 2.0</a> protocol. It&#8217;s designed to facilitate secure authentication and single sign-on (SSO) across different applications and services. If you’d like to read more about how OIDC works with OAuth 2.0, see OpenID Foundation&#8217;s article on <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://openid.net/developers/how-connect-works/" target="_blank">how OpenID Connect works</a><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://openid.net/developers/how-connect-works/" target="_blank">.</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="858" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-1024x858.png" alt="the layers of how OIDC works. when a HTTP request is sent, OAuth2.0 checks for authorisation access permissions, and OIDC checks for user identity" class="wp-image-48868" style="object-fit:contain;width:633px;height:531px" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-1024x858.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-300x251.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-768x644.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-1536x1288.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1.png 1880w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="why-oidc">Why OIDC?</h2>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="enhanced-security"><strong>Enhanced Security</strong></h3>



<p>One of the key drivers behind ALA&#8217;s adoption of OpenID Connect (OIDC) is its ability to enhance data security.</p>



<p>OIDC operates by employing secure tokens in the background to validate a user&#8217;s identity. These tokens are designed to be short-lived and encrypted, ensuring that your credentials remain protected and reducing the potential for unauthorised access or data breaches.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="seamless-user-experience"><strong>Seamless User Experience</strong></h3>



<p>We’re committed to improving your experience across the ALA site; while this includes features like navigation, readability and look and feel, it also relates to login experience and performance. OIDC enhances our current SSO capabilities, allowing you to log in once to access multiple services without repeatedly entering your credentials.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="federated-sign-in"><strong>Federated sign-in</strong></h3>



<p>OIDC also enhances federated identity services. This means that you can continue to leverage your existing accounts from trusted identity providers such as the <a href="https://aaf.edu.au/">Australian Access Federation</a> (AAF), eliminating the need to create another username and password – making it quicker and easier to access the ALA for existing AAF users.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="scalability-and-integration"><strong>Scalability and Integration</strong></h3>



<p>As the number of records in the ALA grows, we ensure that our systems are flexible and scalable. OIDC allows us to integrate with a variety of web applications and evolve alongside other technical advancements.</p>



<p>Collaboration is also a big part of what we do at the ALA, so we can continue to make even more data findable and accessible. With the growing adoption of OIDC, integration is made easier with our data partners and other collaborators. For example, we are working with <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a> to integrate OIDC, making it quicker and easier for our <a href="https://fieldcapture.ala.org.au/">MERIT</a> users to sign in and submit data to the MERIT system using the TERN Monitor application.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="summary">Summary</h2>



<p>The adoption of OIDC authentication represents a significant milestone in the ALA’s ongoing commitment to data security, performance, and user experience. We remain dedicated to staying at the forefront of technology to do so, and we look forward to continued growth and collaboration with our user community. The ALA has more exciting infrastructure and technology changes coming soon – watch this space!</p>



<p>If you would like to know more about how OIDC benefits your data access experience, please reach out at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<div style="height:17px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA adopts OpenID Connect (OIDC)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rIpy_f1pHtM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<div style="height:41px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
