<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 May 2022 02:54:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>BioCollect update: New look for our data collection tool</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/biocollect-update-new-look-for-our-data-collection-tool/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 23:26:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA’s field data collection system – BioCollect – is getting brand new look.    The look and feel will be fresher, cleaner and more intuitive. You can still design your own data collection projects, collect data, share your project with partners, and make the data accessible via the ALA – all in a new [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The ALA’s field data collection system – BioCollect – is getting brand new look.   </p>



<p>The look and feel will be fresher, cleaner and more intuitive. You can still design your own data collection projects, collect data, share your project with partners, and make the data accessible via the ALA – all in a new design.  The new design will be rolled out this May.</p>



<p>Visit <a href="http://https/:biocollect.ala.org.au" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https//:biocollect.ala.org.au</a> to get started.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>The BioCollect makeover – what’s new and what’s changed</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>The user interface design for BioCollect has not changed since it’s launch, so it was time for an uplift.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The update is mostly cosmetic, we simplified the interface without losing any of the great functionality. There are also some new features. You can now create projects in your own personal space and publish the project to the world only when you’re ready.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>There are also some improvements to the document search and view feature on the project resources page. Even more improvements will be coming in the near future too.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>BioCollect – a flexible biodiversity data collection tool</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>BioCollect can be used to meet the specific data collection needs of <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/acsa" target="_blank">citizen science project</a>s, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/ecoscience" target="_blank">non-citizen science projects</a> or <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/nrmworks" target="_blank">natural resource management projects</a>. It was first released in 2015, and is now widely used by researchers, industry ecologists, citizen scientists, non-government organisations and government organisations.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="BioCollect: ALA data collection tool" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QEr6VULLZks?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Echidna CSI – a BioCollect case study</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>A research project run by Dr Tahlia Perry at the University of Adelaide uses data collected by citizen scientists to study echidnas. The project has had a huge impact on echidna research and conservation. The research team developed a bespoke mobile app using BioCollect as its database.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The flexible data collection tool enabled the research team to ‘recruit’ an army of citizen scientists across the country and collect the data necessary to establish an Australia-wide distribution map of Short-Beaked Echidnas (<em>Tachyglossus culeatus</em>). The project has doubled the number of echidna records in the ALA and discovered new facts about echidna biology. <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/echidna-csi-using-citizen-science-to-track-echidnas-throughout-australia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read more about Echidna CSI.</a>&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Collect, store, manage and share with BioCollect</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you’re running a field data collection project, why not give BioCollect a try. You can collect data for your own project, store and manage the data, and, when you’re ready to share the data, it can go straight into the ALA automatically.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Visit <a href="http://https/:biocollect.ala.org.au" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https//:biocollect.ala.org.au</a> to get started.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s message May 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-message-may-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 23:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46838</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the May 2022 edition of our newsletter ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure/resources/2021-national-research-infrastructure-roadmap"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-719x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46839" width="152" height="217" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-719x1024.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-211x300.png 211w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-768x1094.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail.png 790w" sizes="(max-width: 152px) 100vw, 152px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure/resources/2021-national-research-infrastructure-roadmap">View the Australian Government&#8217;s 2021 National Research Infrastructure Roadmap</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p>We were pleased to recently see the Australian Government <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.minister.industry.gov.au/ministers/price/media-releases/morrison-government-launches-roadmap-900-million-spend-australias-research-infrastructure" target="_blank">release</a> the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.dese.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure/resources/2021-national-research-infrastructure-roadmap" target="_blank">2021 National Research Infrastructure Roadmap</a> which identifies future needs and priorities for research infrastructure investment in Australia. This is an important strategy setting document for the ALA, our partners in the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure program, and the many thousands of researchers and other users that benefit from this capability.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>We’d like to thank the ALA’s partners and stakeholders who made an important contribution to the roadmap development process through contributions to surveys, consultations, discussions, and formal submissions in response to the roadmap consultation draft. The roadmap is comprehensive, respects the existing NRI foundation and historical achievements, yet sets some ambitious goals for Australia to realise improvements.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<h3 id="ala-decadal-vision-growth-for-impact">ALA Decadal Vision: Growth for impact</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-Decadal-Vision-May-2022_v1.0.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/thumbnail-decadal-vision.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46833" width="147" height="207"/></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-Decadal-Vision-May-2022_v1.0.pdf">View ALA Decadal Vision: Growth for impact </a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>To support the ALA&#8217;s involvement and engagement to the roadmap process, we worked with our Advisory Board, peak bodies, and key stakeholders to develop the ALA&#8217;s own vision-setting piece. The <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-Decadal-Vision-May-2022_v1.0.pdf">ALA Decadal Vision: Growth for Impact</a> was also released this month, framed around an aspiration to <em>deliver trusted biodiversity data for Australia supporting world-class transformational research and more effective decision-making. </em>The vision has been developed to extend and grow the ALA’s impact beyond the current <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/publications/ala-strategy-2020-2025/">ALA Strategy 2020-2025</a> and is framed around a set of principles and growth opportunities, while respecting the importance of maintaining core ALA capability.  </p>



<h3 id="new-data-new-sectors-and-focus-on-collections">New data, new sectors, and focus on collections</h3>



<p>What’s new relative to what the ALA currently delivers? First, the vision commits to supporting new biodiversity data types, including from advances in genomics-based biodiversity identification, biodiversity survey data, and data emerging from sensor networks all of which are becoming increasingly important for our users. The ALA also recognises the fundamental role biological collections provide in supporting science and accelerating the digitisation of physical specimens to enable digital access. This aspiration aligns closely with the collections step change identified in the NRI roadmap around collections. Finally, the ALA Decadal Vision details the new sectors we will prioritise, and partnership models the ALA will adopt moving forward.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3 id="work-is-already-underway"><strong>Work is already underway</strong></h3>



<p>A decade may seem a long time but the ALA has already commenced pathfinder activities across several decadal priorities, a number of which appear on our <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/" target="_blank">current projects pages</a>. Our recently announced <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/" target="_blank">data mobilisation program</a> will also provide the foundation to support any further investment in accelerating the digitisation of Australia’s biological collections.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>We encourage you to read our decadal vision, particularly in the context of future science and decision-making drivers. I’d personally welcome feedback (<a href="mailto:ala@csiro.au">ala@csiro.au)</a> if you feel we’ve missed a driver or a future capability. The science we support is diverse and rapidly evolving so it’s important we adapt, evolve and continue to deliver impact.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy reading the decadal vision and this May edition of our newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Andre Zerger</strong></p>



<p><strong>Director, Atlas of Living Australia</strong></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Labs: new site offering technical solutions to scientific problems </title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-labs-new-site-offering-technical-solutions-to-scientific-problems/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 01:50:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46796</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Do you conduct research using Australian biodiversity data? Do you analyse data or make data visualisations? ALA’s newest website, ALA Labs, is here to help. ALA Labs provides technical know-how and detailed solutions to specific scientific problems using data in the ALA. Learn how with ALA Labs posts The main showcase of ALA Labs is [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46800" width="386" height="257" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16.png 783w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16-300x200.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16-768x511.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 386px) 100vw, 386px" /></figure></div>



<p>Do you conduct research using Australian biodiversity data? Do you analyse data or make data visualisations?</p>



<p>ALA’s newest website, <a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/">ALA Labs</a>, is here to help. ALA Labs provides technical know-how and detailed solutions to specific scientific problems using data in the ALA.</p>



<p><strong>Learn how with ALA Labs posts</strong></p>



<p>The main showcase of ALA Labs is the <strong>Posts </strong>section. Posts are “how-to” articles on how to conduct specific statistical analyses or how to create data visualisations. Each post provides step-by-step commentary on how to do a specific task along with code so you can reproduce the analysis.</p>



<p></p>



<p>ALA Labs is managed by <a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/about.html">our Science and Decision Support team</a>. Team members will share solutions to common problems for users, including those that they have used in their own work.</p>



<p>Solutions described in ALA Labs posts are not intended to be the “only” or “correct” way to solve a problem. Rather, each post offers one <em>possible</em> way to do or make something. The goal is to provide ALA users with working examples to implement in their own work, hopefully making everyone’s analyses and visualisations better!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="630" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-1024x630.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46797" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-1024x630.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-300x185.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-768x473.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot.png 1248w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Sunburst plots for taxonomic data. <br>This visualisation of ALA’s taxonomy was created by Dr Martin Westgate in R using {galah} and {ggplot2}. The <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://labs.ala.org.au/posts/2022-02-17_sunburst-plots-for-taxonomic-data/" target="_blank">full details of how to recreate this analysis and visualisation</a> are available on labs.ala.org.au. </figcaption></figure>



<p>“I always love hearing about the problems people are trying to solve using the biodiversity data in the ALA. We made ALA Labs to be a community space for people to share and learn about detailed solutions to data-related problems. I can’t wait to see how it grows,” said Dr Dax Kellie, evolutionary biologist, data analyst, and ALA Labs author.</p>



<p><strong>R – the language of ALA Labs</strong></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png" alt="logo for galah, ALA's R package" class="wp-image-44815" width="220" height="254" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png 434w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630-260x300.png 260w" sizes="(max-width: 220px) 100vw, 220px" /></figure></div>



<p>So far, posts on ALA Labs offer coding solutions for users of <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a> – a popular, free, open-access software for analysing and visualising data – and {<a href="https://atlasoflivingaustralia.github.io/galah/index.html">galah</a>} – the ALA’s R package to download information from the ALA. We intend to expand articles to explore other tools and coding languages in the near future.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>We want to hear from you</strong></p>



<p>Is there a statistical analysis you are wondering how to do in R? Would you like to make a new visualisation or map? Are you looking to use the {galah} package to filter and download information?</p>



<p>We would love to hear from you. Please send any suggestions for ALA Labs posts to <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA webinar: New Data From Historic Collections</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-new-data-from-historic-collections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 01:10:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46527</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Across Australia there are 60 million natural history specimens held at museums, universities, botanic gardens, herbaria, seed banks and at CSIRO. These collections are made up of whole organisms, skins, tissue samples, skeletons and DNA samples – plus data &#8230; a lot of data &#8230; even including data about that data (metadata). Collections metadata can [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Across Australia there are 60 million natural history specimens held at museums, universities, botanic gardens, herbaria, seed banks and at CSIRO. These collections are made up of whole organisms, skins, tissue samples, skeletons and DNA samples – plus data &#8230; a lot of data &#8230; even including data about that data (metadata).</p>



<p>Collections metadata can describe from as little as what species the sample or organism is, to when and where they were collected; to site descriptions, species associations, and much more. There is immense hidden value in metadata, and researchers are continually discovering new things about our historic collections.</p>



<p>In this webinar three researchers describe how they use the data &#8216;hidden&#8217; in our national collections.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar: New Data from Historic Collections – 16 Mar, 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8r3YLRcvnE8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEDT, Wednesday 16 March 2022, with 154 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALADHC-220316/RocioAguilar-135px.ashx?la=en&amp;hash=9C23ED7DBC59812F7486AA9C86D0412BACDE7F00" alt="Rocio Aguilar"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Rocío Aguilar | Monash University</h3>



<p>Rocío is an Argentinean herpetologist who has called Australia home for the past 12 years. She specialises in eco-physiology and morphology, thermal biology and CT scanning. She completed her Bachelor and Masters at Comahue National University (Argentina) on habitat use in geckos, and research at the National University of Cuyo (Argentina) on the thermal ecophysiology of iguanids. Rocío worked for 6 years as a Research Assistant with Mike Kearney (University of Melbourne) and Christy Hipsley (University of Melbourne/Museum Victoria) working on eco-physio-morphology and conservation of Australian lizards. As part of a Monash University ARC Linkage Project with Museums Victoria and other Australian Museums, she is currently CT scanning all Australian lizard species to understand the evolutionary morphology pathways that make Australia the most lizard-diverse country in the world!</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALADHC-220316/EmilyRoycroft-135px.ashx?la=en&amp;hash=25301C35B33F84634E9F1483BBADC82EF3A8C55E" alt="Dr Emily Roycroft"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Emily Roycroft | ANU</h3>



<p>Emily Roycroft is an evolutionary biologist and postdoctoral researcher at the Australian National University. Her research applies genomic approaches to questions about the evolutionary history of species, primarily focusing on the spectacular diversity of native Australian mammals and reptiles. Emily is especially interested in the ways that museum collections can be used as a genomic resource for understanding recent biodiversity loss in Australia.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALADHC-220316/OllyBerry-135px.ashx?la=en&amp;hash=550A9B5CFB482C6E05F2EA641B67D7E1D907E545" alt="Olly Berry"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="ana-belgun-data61">Olly Berry | CSIRO</h3>



<p>Olly has a background in spatial ecology and genomics, but currently leads CSIRO’s Environomics Future Science Platform. This is an R&amp;D program whose brief is to find new ways to support environmental management with DNA technologies. It’s a field full of opportunities, and some of the most useful involve accessing information contained in natural history specimens.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Webinar-moderator-Martin.png" alt="Martin Westgate" class="wp-image-45781"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin Westgate is Science Advisor to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">Atlas of Living Australia</a>&nbsp;and a visiting fellow at the&nbsp;<a href="https://fennerschool.anu.edu.au/">Fenner School of Environment &amp; Society</a>&nbsp;at the Australian National University. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="want-more">Want more?</h3>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter March 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-march-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 01:55:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46580</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter March 2022]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ALA-Newsletter-March-2022.pdf">ALA Newsletter March 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s message: ALA Newsletter March 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-message-ala-newsletter-march-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 22:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Launch of the ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program Welcome to the March 2022 edition of our newsletter, in which we launch the ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program. This new program will provide grants to institutions to mobilise their data to the ALA. This could include the transcription of historical field sheets, acquisition of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="launch-of-the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program">Launch of the ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46572" width="413" height="232" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 413px) 100vw, 413px" /></figure></div>



<p>Welcome to the March 2022 edition of our newsletter, in which we launch the <strong><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program.</a></strong></p>



<p>This new program will provide grants to institutions to mobilise their data to the ALA. This could include the transcription of historical field sheets, acquisition of contemporary digital scanning technology, or even the development or purchase of software to provide better approaches to biodiversity data management and delivery. The ‘how’ will be up to the successful grant recipients, hence the program will offer maximum flexibility for successful applicants. We plan to award 6 grants in the first year of the program across both small ($20K) and large grants ($50K).</p>



<h3 id="why-were-creating-this-grant-program">Why we&#8217;re creating this grant program</h3>



<p>The success of the ALA as Australia’s biodiversity data infrastructure rests so much on the contribution made by its data partners across multiple domains. Data in the ALA comes from biological collections, museum and herbaria, state government, major research programs, non-government organisations and increasingly citizen scientists.</p>



<p>We partner with over 900 of these groups and individuals to harmonise Australia’s biodiversity data. Despite these partner contributions we remain acutely aware that for small institutions, or where historical data remains in analogue format, providing biodiversity data to the ALA remains a challenge, and we encourage you to apply for assistance through this new program.</p>



<p>I’ve been reflecting on the ecological data I collected as a researcher working across the south west slopes of NSW and parts of Victoria some years ago. I spent a decade supporting the collection of fundamental data about Australia’s flora and fauna. Much of this made its way into digital databases, at the time in CSIRO and the University of Melbourne. However, the ALA did not exist so this record although digital, remains undiscoverable.&nbsp; I also saw first-hand the filing cabinets of paper field sheets from my predecessors that provide a fundamental record of our biodiversity and may never be digitised.</p>



<p>With this context in mind, I am &nbsp;very excited to be launching the <strong><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>.</strong></p>



<h3 id="program-details-application-and-assessment">Program details: application and assessment</h3>



<p>Clearly there’s a massive amount of biodiversity data that remains un-digitised and the job of the evaluation panel will be to make informed assessments against defined criteria. Detailed guidelines will be published shortly on the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blog/">ALA blog</a> and on our ALA social media channels &#8211; <a href="https://twitter.com/atlaslivingaust">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/atlasoflivingaustralia">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/1232460">LinkedIn</a>. Principles underpinning the program include alignment with national priorities and a focus on significant historical biodiversity information not currently available as FAIR data – findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable.</p>



<p>The program will be evaluated by an independent panel Chaired by Dr David Cantrill, one of the ALA Advisory Board’s longest serving members.</p>



<p>Our team is so excited by the opportunity this program will deliver Australia’s biodiversity community and already anticipates the legacy it will deliver. We look forward to seeing some fantastic applications.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy our March 2022 newsletter.</p>



<p>Dr. Andre Zerger </p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 23:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Do you work in an institution with historic biodiversity data? Our new grant program is designed to help you digitise, mobilise and share your biodiversity data via the Atlas of Living Australia. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/3-1-edited-1.png" alt="shelves full of folders" class="wp-image-46507" width="321" height="392"/><figcaption>Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">The <a href="https://ala.org.au/abdmp/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a> is a grant program to support people and institutions make their biodiversity data more accessible.</p>



<h3 id="accessible-data-is-better-data"><strong>Accessible data is better data</strong></h3>



<p>Making your data open and accessible makes it more valuable. FAIR data – findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable &#8211; can be shared with other researchers and people working in biodiversity policy.</p>



<p>High quality and accessible biodiversity data helps conservation efforts and informs decision-making and solutions for environmental challenges.</p>



<h3 id="funding-to-support-your-digitisation-efforts"><strong>Funding to support your digitisation efforts</strong></h3>



<p>We know that organising, standardising, and digitising data takes time and effort. The ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program is here to help. The grant program will award small (up to $20k) and large (up to $50k) grants to biodiversity data owners to support purchasing equipment (e.g. camera, scanner) or employing staff in order to mobilise data.</p>



<p>Applications for the 2022 round of the program have now closed.</p>



<h3 id="who-can-apply"><strong>Who can apply?</strong></h3>



<p>We’re looking for institutions or biodiversity researchers who need help digitising historic physical records and mobilising data into the ALA.</p>



<p>There’s no catch, as long as the records are biodiversity-related. This can be for any wild species in Australia – from koalas to cane toads, eucalypts to bioluminescent fungi, we want to know about it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The data might be in paper field notes, or species in physical collections. Whatever it is, we’ll be giving out grants to 6 institutions through both small ($20K) and large grants($50k).</p>



<p>You might be wondering why! Well, available data = useful data – so by making historical data accessible, it can be shared more widely and used by researchers to support biodiversity conservation efforts and decision-making.&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-1024x576.png" alt="colourful specimens in an insect collection" class="wp-image-46503" width="1005" height="565" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<h1 id="details-of-the-program"><strong>Details of the program</strong></h1>



<h3 id="how-to-apply">How to apply</h3>



<p>All applications must be sent using the program submission form. </p>



<h3 id="closing-date-for-applications">Closing date for applications</h3>



<p>Applications for 2022 have now closed.</p>



<h3 id="how-much-funding-can-i-apply-for">How much funding can I apply for? </h3>



<p>There are two funding amounts on offer, including:</p>



<ul><li>small grants up to $20,000</li><li>large grants up to $50,000</li></ul>



<h3 id="who-can-apply">Who can apply?</h3>



<p>This grant program is open to individuals or groups within an institution, excluding existing partners who already receive ALA or National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy support. </p>



<h3 id="what-data-are-suitable-for-the-grant">What data are suitable for the grant?</h3>



<ul id="block-72757bf6-1e52-42ba-81ff-c1d26286af64"><li>The program will target existing data. It cannot support new expeditions or field programs</li><li>Data mobilisation efforts should align to national priorities</li><li>Data should be in the form of biodiversity species occurrence records akin to what&#8217;s delivered through the ALA already</li><li>Emergent digital data must be mapped to the Darwin Core standard and able to be provided to the ALA as open data</li></ul>



<h3 id="what-can-i-use-the-funding-for">What can I use the funding for?</h3>



<p>Funding can be used to fund data mobilisation and/or infrastructure investments. </p>



<p>Data mobilisation investment could include:</p>



<ul><li>Staff time to digitise of specimens in physical collections including scanning</li><li>Conversion of existing analogue data, such as in field notes or other formats into the Darwin Core standard for provision to the ALA</li></ul>



<p>Infrastructure investment could include:</p>



<ul><li>Purchasing digital imaging equipment to create digital data from historic records</li><li>Purchasing software licences to improve the management and delivery of biodiversity data</li><li>Software development costs associated with the improve management and delivery of biodiversity data</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-1024x576.png" alt="assistant photographing a specimen" class="wp-image-46504" width="737" height="414" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 737px) 100vw, 737px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="selection-criteria">Selection criteria</h3>



<p>Applications will be assessed using an online form, in a single round and selected by an independent program evaluation panel. The submission form will be available from the 14th of March. It will contain all questions and a guide to the length of answers our panel is looking for. </p>



<p>Overall, we are looking to understand the details of the proposed activity, why it is important, and how you would allocate the funds if successful.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-1024x576.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46505" width="455" height="255" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<h3 id="more-information">More information</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://ala.org.au/abdmp/">About the program</a> </li><li><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp-faq/">FAQ&#8217;s page</a></li></ul>



<h3 id="any-other-questions">Any other questions?</h3>



<p>Please <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">email us</a> with any questions you have about the program.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GBIF Young Researchers Award 2022 – Call for Nominations</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/gbif-young-researchers-award-2022-call-for-nominations/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 03:35:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are now open for the GBIF 2022 Young Researchers Award. This award is an annual programme aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-background" style="background-color:#e7e6ea">Nominations are now open for the GBIF 2022 Young Researchers Award. This award is an annual program aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics. </p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="210" height="100" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/GBIF-logo-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44593"/></figure></div>



<p>The 2022 programme will provide a pair of €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD7,500) recognising the work of two early-career researchers — preferably, one Masters and one PhD candidate. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through GBIF. The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA is also accessible via GBIF. </p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p class="has-text-color" style="color:#c44d34"><strong><em>Applications to the ALA are due by 30 May 2022.</em></strong></p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p> </p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-662x1024.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46451" width="376" height="581" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-662x1024.jpg 662w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-194x300.jpg 194w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-768x1188.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-993x1536.jpg 993w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o.jpg 1170w" sizes="(max-width: 376px) 100vw, 376px" /><figcaption>Illustration of&nbsp;<em>Macrolepiota procera</em>&nbsp;(Scop.) Gray, from&nbsp;<a href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/1266181"><em>Führer für Pilzfreunde</em></a>&nbsp;(1821) via&nbsp;<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biodivlibrary/8509418243/in/album-72157632865665228/">Biodiversity Heritage Library</a>, no rights reserved under&nbsp;<a href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">CC0</a>.</figcaption></figure></div>



<h2 id="how-to-submit-an-application-australian-applicants"><strong>How to submit an application (Australian applicants)</strong></h2>



<ol type="1"><li>Visit&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6PzaBymtwAEvbpXYtb4d1y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2022-gbif-young-researchers-award">the GBIF young researchers award website</a>&nbsp;and follow the instructions.&nbsp;<br><br></li><li>Submit your nominations to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">Jenna Wraith, ALA&#8217;s Training and Outreach Coordinator</a>, with ‘GBIF Young Researcher’ in the subject line by&nbsp;<strong>30 May 2022.</strong> </li></ol>



<p> </p>



<p> </p>



<h2 id="nomination-process"><strong>Nomination process</strong></h2>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;for further information if required.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat. The winners will be announced in September/October 2022.</p>



<p></p>



<p> </p>



<p> </p>



<h2 id="award-nomination-packet"><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></h2>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol><li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)<br><br></li><li><strong>Project description</strong>&nbsp;(<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em>) that describes<br>a. The need for the research and the question(s) it addresses.<br>b.&nbsp;<strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.<br><br></li><li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.<br><br></li><li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate programme of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li></ol>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="further-information"><strong>Further information</strong></h2>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6PzaBymtwAEvbpXYtb4d1y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2022-gbif-young-researchers-award" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF website.</a></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>NCRIS: The power behind Australia’s science</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ncris-the-power-behind-australias-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 03:31:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46319</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Recently, a number of &#160;research infrastructure organisations from the NCRIS community, including the Atlas of Living Australia, commissioned Lateral Economics (LE) to assess the positive impacts of NCRIS for Australian society and the environment. The report identified ways in which NCRIS funding has and will continue to support the Australian community and economy. Powerful economic [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Recently, a number of &nbsp;research infrastructure organisations from the NCRIS community, including the Atlas of Living Australia, commissioned Lateral Economics (LE) to assess the positive impacts of <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> for Australian society and the environment. The report identified ways in which NCRIS funding has and will continue to support the Australian community and economy.</p>



<h3 id="powerful-economic-findings">Powerful economic findings</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/NCRIS-impact_Twitter-tiles_FA_PLANT_feature-image-blog.jpg" alt="NCRIS Lateral Economics report" class="wp-image-46416" width="429" height="334" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/NCRIS-impact_Twitter-tiles_FA_PLANT_feature-image-blog.jpg 900w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/NCRIS-impact_Twitter-tiles_FA_PLANT_feature-image-blog-300x233.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/NCRIS-impact_Twitter-tiles_FA_PLANT_feature-image-blog-768x597.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 429px) 100vw, 429px" /></figure></div>



<p><a href="https://www.phrn.org.au/media/82231/ncris-stimulus-report-updated-final-31-august-2021-002.pdf">National Collaborative Research<br>Infrastructure (NCRIS) spending<br>and economic growth</a> found the direct benefit of investment in <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> is calculated to be above a $7 return for every $1 invested, a return on investment (ROI) of 7.5:1. By 2022-23 the investment could support the employment of an additional 1,750 scientific and technical staff, support staff, and supply chain and industry staff -. These benefits along with others outlined in the report indicate the significant impact NCRIS has made on Australia’s economic security. The report concluded:</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p><em>“Based on economic theory and evidence from the time of the GFC to present, we can think of few approaches to providing additional stimulus to the Australian economy that are more cost effective than increasing investment in NCRIS.”</em></p></blockquote>



<h3 id="ncris-delivers">NCRIS delivers</h3>



<p>The impact of <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> is clear, however the program itself is not often centre stage. From supercomputers and microscopes, to data collection and software platforms NCRIS provides the infrastructure that supports Australia’s scientists.</p>



<p>The result is a network of world-class research facilities that are driving innovation and research in Australia and internationally. This network is made up of 22 NCRIS projects, which link over 200 institutions employing more than 1,900 highly skilled researchers and technical experts. This interconnected infrastructure and the specialist teams who run <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> programs allow Australia to meet the key challenges outlined in the UN sustainability goals and tackle some of the biggest scientific and societal challenges we face today. These have been highlighted in the Lateral Economics report as:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-table"><table><tbody><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="43" height="37" class="wp-image-46320" style="width: 200px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-1.png" alt="bushfire icon"></td><td><strong>Bushfire preparedness. </strong>With a range of sensors across Australia supported by NCRIS facilities such as <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a> and <a href="https://aurin.org.au/">AURIN</a>, Australia can be better prepared for bushfire threats in the future.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="60" height="60" class="wp-image-46321" style="width: 60px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-2.png" alt="cyclone icon"></td><td><strong>Cyclone warnings. </strong><a href="https://imos.org.au/">IMOS</a> is providing rich, high frequency data from Australia’s surrounding oceans which can provide early warning signs of cyclones, not to mention ocean acidification and sea level rise associated with climate change.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="54" height="54" class="wp-image-46322" style="width: 54px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-3.png" alt="Medicine icon"></td><td><strong>Population health. </strong>A range of <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> facilities (e.g., <a href="https://www.phrn.org.au/media/77248/phrn%20overview.pdf">PHRN</a>, <a href="https://phenomicsaustralia.org.au/">Phenomics Australia</a>, <a href="https://bioplatforms.com/">Bioplatforms Australia</a>, <a href="https://www.therapeuticinnovation.com.au/">Therapeutic Innovation Australia</a>) are helping to improve the health of Australia’s population.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="48" height="41" class="wp-image-46323" style="width: 48px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-4.png" alt="building blocks icon"></td><td><strong>Understanding the building blocks of reality. </strong><a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> facilities such as <a href="https://micro.org.au/">Microscopy Australia</a>, <a href="https://anif.org.au/">National Imaging Facility</a>, <a href="https://www.ansto.gov.au/">ANSTO</a>, and <a href="https://astronomyaustralia.org.au/">Astronomy Australia </a>are contributing to world leading research on the building blocks of the universe and of life.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="63" height="53" class="wp-image-46324" style="width: 63px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/Le-report-5.png" alt="biodiversity icon"></td><td><strong>Monitoring biodiversity.</strong> Australia’s unique biodiversity is being monitored, described and protected by the Atlas of Living Australia (<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">ALA</a>), <a href="https://bioplatforms.com/">BioPlatforms Australia</a>, <a href="https://imos.org.au/">IMOS</a> and <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a>. In particular, <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">ALA</a> is our national biodiversity data infrastructure. It integrates and delivers fundamental data on Australia’s plants, animals and fungi to support ecosystem assessment, monitoring and planning.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="64" height="52" class="wp-image-46325" style="width: 64px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-6.png" alt="crop icon"></td><td><strong>Boosting crop yields and resilience.</strong> The <a href="https://www.plantphenomics.org.au/">Australian Plant Phenomics Facility</a> contributes fundamental services in the effort to improve crop yields and crop resilience with genomic and molecular characterisation performed through <a href="https://bioplatforms.com/">Bioplatforms Australia</a>.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="52" height="43" class="wp-image-46326" style="width: 52px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-7.png" alt="data icon"></td><td><strong>Deriving value from data. </strong><a href="https://ardc.edu.au/">ARDC</a>, <a href="https://pawsey.org.au/">Pawsey Supercomputing Centre</a> and the <a href="https://nci.org.au/">National Computational Infrastructure</a> enable data from many fields of research across a wide range of scales to be stored, curated, managed and analysed.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="55" height="48" class="wp-image-46327" style="width: 55px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-8.png" alt="globe icon"></td><td><strong>Understanding the earth.</strong><a href="https://www.auscope.org.au/">AuScope</a> improves our understanding of fundamental earth science and enables a range of benefits including substantial reductions in the cost of and more effective resource exploration.</td></tr><tr><td><img loading="lazy" width="66" height="56" class="wp-image-46328" style="width: 66px;" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/LE-report-9.png" alt="Adv Manufacturing icon"></td><td><strong>Advanced manufacturing. </strong>The Australian National Fabrication Facility (<a href="https://www.anff.org.au/">ANFF</a>) and Therapeutic Innovation Australian (<a href="https://www.therapeuticinnovation.com.au/">TIA</a>) provide industry and the wider community with access to cutting-edge advanced manufacturing technologies. Furthermore, <a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/ncris">NCRIS</a> organisations such as <a href="https://astronomyaustralia.org.au/">Astronomy Australia</a> are involved in advanced manufacturing activities.</td></tr></tbody></table><figcaption><br>Selected examples of major benefits of NCRIS-supported infrastructure to the Australian community from the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure (NCRIS) spending and economic growth report, June 2021. <br>Icon credits: The Noun Project (top to bottom), Kevin, OCHA Visual, Nociconist, Sergey DemushkinImage, Felipe Perucho, Abdulloh Fauzan, Gregor Cresnar, Lluisa Iborra and iconcheese</figcaption></figure>



<p>This question highlights the direction in which Australia’s science must head.&nbsp; NCRIS will be a key driver of this interdisciplinary and impact driven future.</p>



<h3 id="ncris-as-an-enabler-of-international-collaborations-and-science-diplomacy">NCRIS as an enabler of international collaborations and science diplomacy</h3>



<p>The report describes how NCRIS also provides opportunities for international engagement and cooperation delivering &#8216;science diplomacy&#8217;.</p>



<p>The ALA is an excellent example of this. In its role as the Australian node of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility, the ALA helped to establish the Living Atlases program in 2016, by which other nations (now 24) can establish their own biodiversity data systems.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Software originally developed by our Australian team is now in use by countries around the world to help manage their national biodiversity databases,” said Dr Andre Zerger, Director, Atlas of Living Australia.&nbsp;</p></blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Our international collaborations increase the extent to which foreign researchers include Australia in their research. This generates better knowledge about Australia, including where it ensures Australia is included in cross-country science.” </p></blockquote>



<h3 id="blog-authors">Blog authors</h3>



<p>On behalf of the NCRIS Communications Network, thank you to Philomena Manifold (<a href="https://www.auscope.org.au">AuScope</a>), Jo Curkpatrick (<a href="https://www.plantphenomics.org.au/">Australian Plant Phenomics Facility</a>) Romy Pearse (<a href="https://astronomyaustralia.org.au/">Astronomy Australia</a>), Nicola Tew (<a href="https://www.phrn.org.au/">Population Health Research Network</a>) and Karina Nunez Machado (<a href="https://pawsey.org.au/">Pawsey</a>).</p>



<h3 id="more-information">More information</h3>



<p>If you would like to know more about the Lateral Economics report, please contact <a href="mailto:Meryn.smith@uwa.edu.au">Dr Merran Smith</a> (University of Western Australia).</p>



<h3 id="further-reading">Further reading</h3>



<p>Download the report: <a href="https://www.phrn.org.au/media/82231/ncris-stimulus-report-updated-final-31-august-2021-002.pdf">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure (NCRIS) spending and economic growth by Lateral Economics, 2021</a></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Celebrating Women in Science this #February11</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/celebrating-women-in-science-this-february11/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 00:00:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46334</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[#February11 is the International Day of Women and Girls in Science, a UN day declared in 2015 to empower, celebrate and champion women and girls in scientific disciplines. Despite the growth of women and gender-diverse people in STEM in recent years, a significant gender gap still remains. In Australia, less than one quarter of STEM [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>#February11 is the <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/women-and-girls-in-science-day" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">International Day of Women and Girls in Science</a>, a UN day declared in 2015 to empower, celebrate and champion women and girls in scientific disciplines. Despite the growth of women and gender-diverse people in STEM in recent years, a significant gender gap still remains.</p>



<p>In Australia, less than one quarter of STEM students at university and VET level are women, and five years after graduation, men with STEM qualifications are almost twice as likely to be working in a STEM-qualified occupation. Across all STEM industries, only 28% of workers are women, and even fewer are managers – just 23% of management positions are held by women (source: <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.industry.gov.au/news/second-national-data-report-on-girls-and-women-in-stem" target="_blank">STEM Equity Monitor 2021</a>).</p>



<p>To celebrate #February11 in our own ALA way, we asked our team to share about a woman in science they find inspiring. We discussed the work of so many brilliant women – sharing links, books, podcasts and research papers around the office. Here is a small selection. Blog compiled and edited by Kylie Morrow, Digital Content Coordinator.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="karlie-noon"><strong>Karlie Noon</strong></h2>



<p>By Olivia Torresan, Support Officer</p>



<p>Karlie Noon is a Gamillaraay / Kamilaroi / Gomeroi woman from Tamworth, NSW. Her current research looks at investigating how the Milky Way galaxy finds new sources of hydrogen gas (which drives star formation). This research could potentially help inform us about the longevity of the galaxy we live within. In her spare time, Karlie has also contributed to researching Indigenous knowledge on moon halos – a light refraction phenomena that can aid in predicting rain events.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/karlie2.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46371" width="975" height="541" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/karlie2.png 700w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/karlie2-300x166.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 975px) 100vw, 975px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Photo: ABC Me and SBS</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Karlie is the first Aboriginal woman to attain a double degree in mathematics and physics. She has since pursued a Masters of Astronomy (Advanced) and is currently undertaking a PhD at the Australian National University. She credits her drive to learn maths not to school, but to one of the many strong women in her life: her Aunty.</p>



<p>I first came across Karlie in my early undergraduate years when studying a joint philosophy and maths unit in Cosmology. My undergraduate was a double degree in philosophy and environmental science. Though the class didn’t have an explicit focus on the connections between astronomy and ecology, I read about some of Karlie’s work (some which did just that) when doing some research. It fascinated me. It’s crazy to think that it wasn’t until I arrived at university that I felt I resonated with a female figure in STEM. Like Karlie, I’m a first-generation student. That said, I can only really imagine how further inspiring her work is for Indigenous women in STEM. She’s carried on from her elders; her family – who have thousands of years of intricate astronomical knowledge, precursing the likes of Galileo and Newton. That, of which, Western science still struggles to acknowledge.</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.sbs.com.au/topics/voices/culture/article/2020/11/05/astronomer-and-astrophysicist-karlie-noon-opening-educational-pathways-aboriginal" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SBS Voices article</a> on Karlie and her work</li><li>A short <a href="https://youtu.be/buqMoaLrs0A" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">video about Karlie’s work</a> by the Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute</li><li><a href="https://rsaa.anu.edu.au/study/student-profiles/karlie-noon" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Karlie’s ANU profile</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="fernanda-werneck"><strong>Fernanda Werneck</strong></h2>



<p>By Jessica Fenker Antunes, Data Analyst/R Programmer</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/fernanda-1-768x1024.jpeg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46424" width="475" height="626"/><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Photo: Werneck Lab</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Dr Fernanda Werneck works in the heart of the Amazon Forest (Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas Amazônicas, Brazil), investigating how climate change can affect biodiversity, and the implications for conservation. Besides that, Fernanda promotes and values Women in Science, having published many articles and presented at conferences about the feminine presence in biology. Fernanda is affiliated with the Brazilian Academy of Science, and a member of the “<a href="https://www.parentinscience.com/english">Parent in Science Brazil</a>” movement. In 2016 she won the “L’Oreal-Unesco-ABC prize for Woman in Science,” and the “L’Oreal-Unesco International Rising Talents For Women in Science” in the following year.</p>



<p>One of Dr Werneck’s recent projects that I find inspiring involves popularising the knowledge of the impact of climate change on Amazon biodiversity within Amazon traditional communities and schools. It involves experiences of immersion in the forest, hoping to raise awareness and awaken feelings of environmental citizenship in favour of simply preserving biodiversity.</p>



<p>I met Dr Werneck during my Master at Universidade de Brasília. At that time, she had just finished her PhD in the US and was moving back to Brazil. She taught me a lot about phylogenetic analyses and motivated me to pursue my research in biogeography and evolution. More than that, Fernanda is keen to support and discuss research and life with any student in the lab and maintain contact over the years. Personally, I find Fernanda inspiring as a Latina/Brazilian woman to reach a prestigious position while supporting many other women and girls to pursue the same. She is very approachable, curious, and talking with her you can see how much she loves what she does.</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://sites.google.com/site/fewerneck/research" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Werneck Lab</a> website</li><li>Fernanda’s <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8779-2607" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ORCID</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="mibu-fischer"><strong>Mibu Fischer</strong></h2>



<p>By Jenna Wraith, Training and Outreach Officer</p>



<p>Mibu Fischer is a Quandamooka saltwater scientist&nbsp;and Marine Ethnoecologist at CSIRO. Her work aims to link Traditional Knowledge (science) with modern fishing practices. Mibu works on exciting projects that improve coastal conservation and management, for example, creating an interactive map to show fishing pressure on species.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/mibu.jpg" alt="Mibu beside a quote of hers &quot;I'm most proud of the fact that I am here, as a woman in a minority group and that I get to push the stereotypes of what a scientist is and that I continue to be here&quot;" class="wp-image-46345" width="1003" height="564" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/mibu.jpg 904w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/mibu-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/mibu-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1003px) 100vw, 1003px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Photo: That’s What I Call Science</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Her work strengthens the global Indigenous voice in marine research, especially on the impacts of climate change on coastal Indigenous communities. Mibu is also a mentor and advocate for Indigenous women in STEM.</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li>Read more about Mibu’s work on the <a href="https://blog.csiro.au/indigenous-saltwater-science-and-sea-country-research/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CSIRO blog</a></li><li>Mibu’s profile on <a href="https://people.csiro.au/F/M/Mibu-Fischer" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CSIRO</a> and the <a href="https://marinesocioecology.org/team/mibu-fischer/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Centre for Marine Socioecology</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/shelley-1.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46370" width="159" height="159"/><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Photo: Dr Shelley James</figcaption></figure></div>



<h2 id="shelley-james"><strong>Shelley James</strong></h2>



<p>By Ely Wallis, Collections Community Engagement Manager; Projects Team Lead</p>



<p>Collection managers working in herbaria and museum natural history collections bring a breadth of scientific knowledge to their task – from a deep understanding of taxonomy to identification techniques and tools, from specimen preservation and documentation to international science policy, collecting permit requirements and ethics. Australia boasts outstanding, highly skilled and knowledgeable collection managers. One of them is Dr Shelley James of the Western Australian Herbarium.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Shelley has been a botanical research scientist for more than two decades, studying and working in Australia and the USA.&nbsp;<em><a href="https://bionomia.net/0000-0003-1105-1850" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Bionomia</a></em>, a website that gives scientists credit for their collections work, shows that Shelley has collected over 4,400 specimens from at least four countries and has identified over 4,100 specimens from over 26 countries.</p>



<p>Not only does Shelley maintain an active research career but also gives back to the global community through her tireless efforts sitting on committees and volunteering her time to improve biodiversity science. Her service includes being the Oceania representative on the Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG) executive, Member at Large for the Society for the Preservation of Natural History Collections, and Chair of the Managers of Australasian Herbarium Collections. Her recent work has focused on the expansion and improvement of herbarium collections and biodiversity data and ways to best analyse, contribute to, understand, and better our conservation efforts in Western Australia, Australia and around the world.</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li>You can read <a href="https://bionomia.net/0000-0003-1105-1850" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Shelley’s profile in Bionomia</a>, or view her <a href="https://orcid.org/0000-0003-1105-1850" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ORCID</a>.</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="corrie-moreau"><strong>Corrie Moreau</strong></h2>



<p>By Dax Kellie, Data Analyst</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/corrie-1.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46369" width="442" height="507" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/corrie-1.jpg 312w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/corrie-1-261x300.jpg 261w" sizes="(max-width: 442px) 100vw, 442px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Photo: Cornell University</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Dr Corrie Moreau is a Professor at Cornell University and the Director &amp; Curator of the Cornell University Insect Collection. She loves ants. She researches them and the symbiotic diversity of bacteria in their guts to understand broad evolutionary patterns of life.</p>



<p>Over her PhD, Dr Moreau ambitiously undertook a massive project to use DNA sequencing to construct a family tree of all the major groups of ants in the world. Impressively, she did this work independently of several leading experts (who had just been funded millions of dollars to do the same) after she had asked permission to try to decode a small chunk of the tree and they turned her down. It was a gutsy move for a PhD candidate to take on a project that was eventually compared directly to that of leading experts, but when the two final phylogenies were compared, they “matched almost perfectly”! (quote from E. O. Wilson’s <em>Letters to a Young Scientist</em>)</p>



<p>I was lucky enough to meet Dr Moreau when she gave an invited talk at UNSW, Sydney early on in my PhD. At the time, I had no idea who she was. I had just joined my centre’s social committee, and so I was responsible for organising events and attending to invitees. My own research had nothing to do with ants, gut bacteria, or phylogenomics. Yet Corrie was an enigmatic speaker and a friendly presence. She was especially warm to students and gave some of the best advice I have received to this day on how to advocate and support gender and cultural diversity in STEM. Importantly, she showed me that you don’t have to be a stereotypical academic scientist to succeed – one can still be exceptional while being fun, supportive, and very much themselves.</p>



<p>Edward O. Wilson, Corrie’s PhD supervisor explains Corrie’s disposition perfectly in his book <em>Letters to a Young Scientist</em>:</p>



<p>“There was no bravado in Corrie, no trace of overweening pride, no pretension. She was a quiet, serene enthusiast. As it turned out, she was also an open, helpful friend to fellow students and others around her.”</p>



<p>Hilariously, I was reading this book when I met Corrie and told her about this amazing PhD student in the book who independently created a phylogeny of all the ants…not realising it was her!</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li>You can read Corrie’s profile on the <a href="https://www.moreaulab.entomology.cornell.edu/people/corrie-moreau/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Moreau Lab</a> website, and also on the <a href="https://ecologyandevolution.cornell.edu/corrie-moreau" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cornell</a> website.</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="elinor-ostrom"><strong>Elinor Ostrom</strong></h2>



<p>By Peggy Newman, Team Lead &amp; Data Manager</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/ostrom-15149-portrait-mini-2x-1.jpeg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46367" width="436" height="656"/><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Photo: U. Montan, source: The Nobel Foundation</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>My current STEM hero is Elinor Ostrom, the only woman to have ever won a Nobel Prize for Economic Sciences. I’m fascinated that her research delved into solutions for the “tragedy of the commons,” and found that there are ways communities can&nbsp;successfully care&nbsp;for common property like land and natural resources without exploiting&nbsp;and destroying&nbsp;them. She found a happy medium between privatisation and state&nbsp;regulation&nbsp;to effectively and efficiently manage natural resources, whereby the community that uses the resource manages it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>I’m extremely moved by her work&nbsp;because the popular discourse of blaming our current environmental and social problems on human greed tends to point fingers at individuals without&nbsp;examining the systems that enable the problems. Through real examples, Ostrom’s work&nbsp;examines how those systems can work better through community governance. Coming from a family of primary producers who rely heavily on environmental resources, I am unbelievably excited about this. In 2012, Time magazine named her as one of the most 100 influential people in the world. Sure we’re not there yet, but Ostrom undoubtedly worked to make the world a better place.</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/economic-sciences/2009/ostrom/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read more about Elinor’s work in detail, and watch one of her lectures</a></li><li>If you’re after a quick read, <a href="http://content.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2111975_2111976_2111960,00.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Time</a> has a great page about Elinor</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="spotlight-on-a-girls-in-stem-initiative-robogals"><strong>Spotlight on a girls in STEM initiative: Robogals</strong></h2>



<p>Robogals is an international student-led organisation that hosts engineering and technology workshops in local communities, with a focus on girls in primary and secondary school. This fantastic initiative provides female role models for young girls and cultivates an interest in STEM. With a vision to inspire, engage and empower young women into STEM, Robogals has reached over 130,000 students globally, many here in Australia.</p>



<p>This week, Robogals launched their global Science Challenge for 2022: an online STEM competition for girls and gender diverse students aged 5-15. The challenge prompts students to explore innovation and design through guided hands-on projects which can be completed with a friend, parent, or mentor.</p>



<p>More information:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://robogals.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://robogals.org/</a></li><li>To explore the Science Challenge:&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://sciencechallenge.org.au/" target="_blank">https://sciencechallenge.org.au/</a></li></ul>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/robogals-412x1024.png" alt="Robogirls how to participate graphic - sign up, complete 2 minor challenges, complete major challenge, submit major challenge for judging" class="wp-image-46368" width="385" height="957" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/robogals-412x1024.png 412w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/robogals-121x300.png 121w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/robogals.png 528w" sizes="(max-width: 385px) 100vw, 385px" /></figure></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
