<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.6</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter July 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-july-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 00:00:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49683</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out the ALA&#8217;s July 2024 Newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p id="block-e6556f64-c2e0-49e7-b903-7825bd5b688f">Check out the ALA&#8217;s <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/july-2024-newsletter-9577615">July 2024 Newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="658" height="918" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ala-newsletter-july-24-thumbnail.png" alt="ALA's July 2024 newsletter header banner - it includes the ALA logo and a frog, and a welcome message" class="wp-image-49685" style="width:590px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ala-newsletter-july-24-thumbnail.png 658w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ala-newsletter-july-24-thumbnail-215x300.png 215w" sizes="(max-width: 658px) 100vw, 658px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; July 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-july-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 01:35:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49626</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the July 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter. In this issue, we are excited to release our 2024-25 ALA Annual Workplan which is a key element of our strategic and operational planning process. Priorities in the workplan are informed by ALA’s Strategy 2020–2025, operational priorities that may emerge in [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Welcome to the July 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>In this issue, we are excited to release our <a href="https://ala.org.au/publications/ala-annual-work-plan-2024-2025/">2024-25 ALA Annual Workplan</a> which is a key element of our strategic and operational planning process. Priorities in the workplan are informed by<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/publications/ala-strategy-2020-2025/"> ALA’s Strategy 2020–2025</a>, operational priorities that may emerge in any year, and partnerships that the ALA has commenced establishing. The workplan acts as both an internal planning tool to guide team priorities, and for external communication purposes to provide our stakeholders with greater visibility into ALA operations.</p>



<p>2024-25 will be the fifth year of delivery under the ALA’s current strategy. Priorities will include the production release of several important initiatives that commenced 2023-24, including the (a) operational national biosecurity alerts service, (b) new ALA home page, species pages and global search interface under the UX/UI project, and (c) stage two of the taxonomic architecture project which will include improved species names matching. Collectively, these capabilities will be transformational for Australia’s biodiversity data community, and we look forward to their release. &nbsp;</p>



<p>As a national research infrastructure supported under the NCRIS program, partnerships are fundamental to how the ALA benefits Australia’s researchers, decision-makers and community. In 2024-25, the ALA will further partner with Australia’s biological collections sector and to develop a case to support a <a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Accelerating_Discovery_and_Access_to_Australias_Biological_Collections_2024_June.pdf">national approach to biological collections</a> akin to the major programs currently underway in Europe and the United States. Beyond the biological collections sector, the ALA will improve the reach and depth of its partnerships with Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander People, working more closely with Indigenous ranger programs to co-design and deliver training programs to enhance the utility of the ALA. Similarly, this year we established a number of partnerships with the environmental consulting sector given the critical role they play in assessing and monitoring Australia’s biodiversity, and we plan to extend these partnerships to support improved translation of research infrastructure to industry.</p>



<p>Our workplan also identifies project leads from the ALA, and we encourage you to reach out to our team to learn more or to collaborate. I hope you enjoy reading our July 2024 Newsletter. </p>



<p><strong>Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director.</strong></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New ALA data mobilisation projects</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-ala-data-mobilisation-projects/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 02:16:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49618</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program (ABDMP) was developed to promote and improve the scientific understanding of Australia’s rare and remarkable biodiversity. In our third year of the program, the ABDMP was expanded to include both a ‘general’ funding stream and a ‘biosecurity-specific’ funding stream. Through a competitive application process, we are pleased to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="341" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/Landscape-banner-headings-40-1024x341.png" alt="Banner with invasive Mediterranean Rye Grass and the ALA logo" class="wp-image-49622" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/Landscape-banner-headings-40-1024x341.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/Landscape-banner-headings-40-300x100.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/Landscape-banner-headings-40-768x256.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/Landscape-banner-headings-40.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>The <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a> (ABDMP) was developed to promote and improve the scientific understanding of Australia’s rare and remarkable biodiversity. In our third year of the program, the ABDMP was expanded to include both a ‘general’ funding stream and a ‘biosecurity-specific’ funding stream. Through a competitive application process, we are pleased to announce the successful biosecurity projects for 2024. The general round of projects will be announced shortly.</p>



<p><strong>Successful Biosecurity Projects:</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong><a href="https://nre.tas.gov.au/biosecurity-tasmania">Biosecurity Tasmania</a>:</strong> This project will mobilise more than 73,000 invertebrate specimen records from the Tasmanian Agriculture Invertebrate Collection (TAIC). This includes more than 450 type specimens and unique records from Macquarie Island.  Cumulatively these records will provide a significant increase in spatial areas of many Tasmanian species not currently represented in the ALA, accelerating the documentation of Australia’s invertebrate fauna.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.dbca.wa.gov.au/science/research-tools-and-repositories/western-australian-herbarium"><strong>Western Australian Herbarium –</strong> <strong>Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions</strong></a><strong>.</strong> To improve the detection of invasive plants across Western Australia, this project will capture high-resolution images of herbarium specimens and mobilise this information to the ALA.  These images, along with existing data for 36,700 specimens and an additional 800 to be digitised, will be made publicly available. This will greatly improve the ability of land managers and biosecurity groups to identify and manage invasive species.</li>
</ul>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong><a href="https://pir.sa.gov.au/research">Primary Industries and Regions South Australia- South Australia Research and Development Institute (SARDI)- Aquatic and Livestock Sciences</a>.</strong> SARDI holds valuable data on invasive, introduced, and native marine species collected in South Australia and beyond. Currently, these records (particularly those for invasive species) are inaccessible to the public. This project will mobilise this data by extracting it from SARDI databases, ensuring quality control, and making it open access through the ALA.</li>
</ul>



<p>We congratulate the successful biosecurity projects for 2024 and thank our review panel for their time and expertise in evaluating many high-calibre applications for this funding stream.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Where to find the ALA</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/where-to-find-the-ala/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Jul 2024 00:51:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49594</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) champions open science and fosters collaboration with data providers, users, and the broader biodiversity community. We actively connect with researchers, policymakers, and the public through engaging outreach programs and external events. With many exciting domestic and international events in the second half of 2024 on the horizon, here’s a [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) champions open science and fosters collaboration with data providers, users, and the broader biodiversity community. We actively connect with researchers, policymakers, and the public through engaging outreach programs and external events. With many exciting domestic and international events in the second half of 2024 on the horizon, here’s a list of where you’ll be able to find the ALA team!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://avpc.net.au/"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="353" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/AVPC_2-1024x353.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49603" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/AVPC_2-1024x353.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/AVPC_2-300x103.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/AVPC_2-768x265.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/AVPC_2.jpg 1372w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>29 July – 1 August – <a href="https://avpc.net.au/">Australasian Vertebrate Pest Conference</a></strong></p>



<p>Hosted in Sydney, this event is a keystone conference for discussing the latest innovation and research in the vertebrate pest management sector. This conference is delivered in partnership with the NSW Department of Primary Industries, NSW Local Land Service and NSW National Parks and Wildlife Service.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://icebergevents.eventsair.com/awc24/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="307" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference-1024x307.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49596" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference-1024x307.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference-300x90.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference-768x230.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference-1536x461.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference-1920x576.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Weeds-conference.png 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>25 – 29 August –</strong> <strong><a href="https://icebergevents.eventsair.com/awc24/">Australasian Weeds Conference</a></strong></p>



<p>Invasive Species Queensland is collaborating with the Council of Australasian Weed Societies (CAWS) in hosting the 23rd Australasian Weeds Conference at the Brisbane Convention and Exhibition Centre.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.biosym.com.au/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="299" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/BioSym-1024x299.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49597" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/BioSym-1024x299.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/BioSym-300x88.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/BioSym-768x224.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/BioSym.jpg 1124w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>27-29 August –</strong> <strong><a href="https://www.biosym.com.au/">Biosecurity Symposium</a></strong></p>



<p>The ALA is a co-session sponsor at this event. This symposium is a flagship event of the Biosecurity Collective – a shared initiative consisting of Animal Health Australia (AHA), Invasive Species Council (ISC), Centre for Invasive Species Solutions (CISS) and Plant Health Australia (PHA) intended to influence the direction of Australia’s biosecurity system towards 2030, particularly in engaging all Australians in building a stronger biosecurity system and building a mass biosecurity movement. This event will be hosted at Sea World on the Gold Coast.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://33creative.eventsair.com/land-and-water-forum-2024/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="254" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-1024x254.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49598" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-1024x254.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-300x75.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-768x191.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-1536x382.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-2048x509.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/First-ntions-1920x477.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>27-29 August – <a href="https://33creative.eventsair.com/land-and-water-forum-2024/">Dangkal Gwo&#8217;yal-wa First Nations Land and Water Forum</a></strong></p>



<p>The Australian Government is pleased to present the 2024 First Nations Land and Water Management Forum (Dangkal Gwo&#8217;yal-wa) Forum to be held on Larrakia Country (Darwin), bringing together First Nations land and water managers from across Australia to celebrate and showcase their achievements looking after Country.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.tdwg.org/conferences/2024/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="472" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/spnhc-tdwg-2024-logo-w-credit-line-1024x472.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49599" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/spnhc-tdwg-2024-logo-w-credit-line-1024x472.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/spnhc-tdwg-2024-logo-w-credit-line-300x138.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/spnhc-tdwg-2024-logo-w-credit-line-768x354.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/spnhc-tdwg-2024-logo-w-credit-line.png 1388w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>2-6 September – <a href="https://www.tdwg.org/conferences/2024/">SPNHC and TDWG joint conference</a></strong></p>



<p>The Society for the Preservation of Natural History Collections (SPNHC) and the Biodiversity information Standards (TDWG) conference will be held in Okinawa, Japan this year.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><a href="https://www.spnhc.org/">SPNHC</a> is an international organisation devoted to the preservation, conservation and management of natural history collections.</li>



<li>Biodiversity Information Standards (<a href="https://www.tdwg.org/">TDWG</a>) develops and maintains data standards that support the integration of primary biodiversity information across disciplines, organizations, and nations. Its annual conference has become a preeminent forum for advancing biodiversity informatics.</li>
</ul>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://www.trematodes2024.com/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="470" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Trematodes.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49600" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Trematodes.png 1000w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Trematodes-300x141.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/Trematodes-768x361.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>8-13 September – <a href="https://www.trematodes2024.com/">Trematodes 2024</a></strong></p>



<p>The ALA is a sponsor of this event. This inaugural international meeting for the trematodology community brings together trematode researchers from around the world to discuss taxonomy, evolution, life cycles, physiology, ecology and biogeography. This event will be hosted at the Queensland Museum, Brisbane.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://gb31.gbif.org/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="956" height="332" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/GB31.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49601" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/GB31.jpg 956w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/GB31-300x104.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/GB31-768x267.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 956px) 100vw, 956px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>30 September – 4 October – <a href="https://gb31.gbif.org/">GB31</a></strong></p>



<p>The 31<sup>st</sup> meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) Governing Board will be held in Portugal.</p>



<p>The GBIF Governing Board meets in a different Participant country each year. The meeting is organised by the GBIF Secretariat in collaboration with the hosting country. The formal proceedings of the Board are associated with several other events at the same location, including meetings of nodes, standing committees, training events and the annual Science Symposium.&#8217;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="174" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ALCA-1024x174.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49620" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ALCA-1024x174.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ALCA-300x51.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ALCA-768x130.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/07/ALCA.jpg 1031w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong>10 &#8211; 11 October &#8211; Australian Land Conservation Alliance (ALCA) <a href="https://alca.org.au/alca_event/private-land-conservation-conference-2024/">Private Land Conservation Conference </a></strong></p>



<p>The ALA is a sponsor of this event. Now in its 8th year, ALCA’s annual Private Land Conservation Conference (PLC24) is Australia’s premier land conservation event. This year’s theme is Nature Now: Action for People and Planet and will be a vital platform for exploring barriers and opportunities to accelerate and expand nature action and finance. PLC24 is a two-day program of workshops, plenaries and concurrent sessions with an exciting line-up of Australian and international speakers.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://conference.eresearch.edu.au/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="449" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/eresearch-1024x449.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49604" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/eresearch-1024x449.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/eresearch-300x131.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/eresearch-768x336.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/eresearch-1536x673.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/eresearch.jpg 1810w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>28 October &#8211; 1 November &#8211; <a href="https://conference.eresearch.edu.au/">eResearch Australasia</a></strong></p>



<p>Hosted by Australasian eResearch Organisations (AeRO) Inc., the conference (hosted in Melbourne this year), is for those interested in eResearch and actively transforming research via information technology. The conference provides an exciting opportunity for delegates to engage, connect and share their ideas and exemplars concerning new information-centric research capabilities, and how ICT technologies can help researchers to collaborate, collect, manage, share, process, analyse, find, understand, and reuse information.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://esa2024.org.au/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="312" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/ESA2024-graphic-07-01-1024x312.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49602" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/ESA2024-graphic-07-01-1024x312.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/ESA2024-graphic-07-01-300x91.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/ESA2024-graphic-07-01-768x234.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/ESA2024-graphic-07-01.jpg 1162w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>9-13 December – <a href="https://esa2024.org.au/">Ecological Society of Australia (ESA)</a></strong></p>



<p>The ALA is a sponsor of this event. The conference of the Ecological Society of Australia (ESA 2024) will be held at the Melbourne Convention and Exhibition Centre. ESA 2024 will be an in-person conference but a limited number of online options will be offered, including live-streamed plenaries, some live-streamed symposia and some of the presentations being made available online after the conference.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Beyond the cityscapes: How a new tool values urban wetlands</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/beyond-the-cityscapes-how-a-new-tool-values-urban-wetlands/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 23:06:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49503</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Did you know that small bodies of water in your city, like ponds or retention basins, play a crucial role in the environment? These urban wetlands are vital for supporting clean water, healthy ecosystems, and even bird migration. However, urban wetlands are often highly modified or constructed bodies of water, and are therefore seen as [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Did you know that small bodies of water in your city, like ponds or retention basins, play a crucial role in the environment? These urban wetlands are vital for supporting clean water, healthy ecosystems, and even bird migration. However, urban wetlands are often highly modified or constructed bodies of water, and are therefore seen as less “valuable” from an urban planning lens in terms of biodiversity conservation and ecosystem outcomes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In a partnership between the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), the <a href="https://aurin.org.au/">Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network (AURIN)</a>, <a href="https://birdlife.org.au/">BirdLife Australia</a> and <a href="https://federation.edu.au/">Federation University</a>, a tool was created to raise awareness of the importance of wetlands in urban environments. The team used open-source citizen-science data to quantify the values of urban wetlands across Victoria, including those that have previously been overlooked. This information was collated into a publicly available online mapping tool, ‘<ins><a href="https://www.valuingurbanwetlands.org.au/">Valuing Urban Wetlands</a></ins>’.</p>



<p><strong>The online tool</strong></p>



<p>The tool integrates waterbird and landscape data through an online portal called ‘<a href="https://www.valuingurbanwetlands.org.au/"><em>Valuing Urban Wetlands</em></a><em>.</em>’ Waterbird data collected through citizen science and professional science was accessed via the ALA, <a href="https://birdlife.org.au/">BirdLife Australia</a> and <a href="https://ebird.org/region/AU">eBird</a> and overlayed with open landscape data to create metrics for assessing wetland health and importance. The tool focuses on the Greater Melbourne region, but the methodology can be applied to other regions in the future</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="506" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-1024x506.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49504" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-1024x506.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-300x148.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-768x379.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-1536x759.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-2048x1012.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Valuing-Urban-wetlands-1920x949.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.valuingurbanwetlands.org.au/" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.valuingurbanwetlands.org.au/">Valuing Urban Wetlands</a> online tool interface.</p>



<p>Anyone can access the <ins><a href="https://www.valuingurbanwetlands.org.au/">Valuing Urban Wetlands</a></ins> online portal. You can enter a wetland name or scroll across the map to zoom into an area and click on a wetland of interest to generate an area report. The report will provide a list of all frog and waterbird species present at this wetland (based on the data sources listed above) as well as the number of threatened species for these taxa.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Lathams-Snipe-Gallinago-hardwickii-Photo-Credit-Allan-Lugg-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-49505" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Lathams-Snipe-Gallinago-hardwickii-Photo-Credit-Allan-Lugg-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Lathams-Snipe-Gallinago-hardwickii-Photo-Credit-Allan-Lugg-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Lathams-Snipe-Gallinago-hardwickii-Photo-Credit-Allan-Lugg-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Lathams-Snipe-Gallinago-hardwickii-Photo-Credit-Allan-Lugg-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Lathams-Snipe-Gallinago-hardwickii-Photo-Credit-Allan-Lugg-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Latham&#8217;s Snipe <em>(Gallinago hardwickii</em>) Photo Credit Allan Lugg CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Case study: Latham’s Snipe <em>(<a href="https://www.birdsinbackyards.net/Charadriiformes/Scolopacidae/Gallinago/Gallinago-hardwickii">Gallinago hardwickii</a>)</em></strong></p>



<p>Latham&#8217;s Snipe is a migratory shorebird that relies on wetland habitats. It breeds in Japan and migrates to Australia for the non-breeding season. It is a cryptic bird and difficult to observe, but research has revealed very high numbers of snipe in some Victorian urban wetlands. Through the online tool developed through this project, wetlands important to support Latham’s Snipe are identified and annual numbers recorded at these wetlands are included in wetland report.</p>



<p><strong>Project Impacts</strong></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li><strong>Raise awareness of urban wetlands:</strong> The project has created a publicly accessible online system that highlights the importance of urban wetlands for biodiversity conservation. This can raise awareness among policymakers, planners, and the general public to give greater consideration to urban wetlands are resources of high biodiversity value. </li>



<li><strong>Improved decision-making:</strong> By providing quantitative data on the value of urban wetlands, the project can inform better decision-making related to land use and development. This ultimately is aimed to lead to better protection of these crucial habitats.</li>



<li><strong>Standardised metrics</strong>: The project has developed a standardised metrics based on citizen-science data for assessing urban wetland value. These metrics can facilitate comparisons across different wetlands and regions.</li>



<li><strong>Citizen science integration: </strong>The project incorporates data from citizen science initiatives like the ALA, Birdlife Australia and eBird. This can empower citizen scientists and contribute valuable data for conservation efforts.</li>



<li><strong>Improved monitoring of key bird species:</strong> Using the Latham&#8217;s Snipe as a case study, this project demonstrates the potential for improving understanding of declining species&#8217; distribution and habitat use in urban areas.</li>
</ul>



<p><em>”Wetlands in urban areas are often overlooked in protection efforts due to a misconception that they are weedy, littered swamps that have low conservation value. However, they provide important refuge habitat for a range of species in our cities, including the Vulnerable Latham’s Snipe. We developed this tool to help raise awareness of the biodiversity value of small urban wetlands by presenting snapshots of data recorded by citizen scientists,</em>” said Dr Birgita Hansen, Project Lead and Senior Research Fellow at Federation University. </p>



<p>Check out the online tool <a href="https://www.valuingurbanwetlands.org.au/">here</a>. For more information about this project, please reach out to <a>support@ala.org.au or to </a><a href="mailto:b.hansen@federation.edu.au">b.hansen@federation.edu.au</a>.</p>



<p><a id="_msocom_1"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Understanding Australian Biodiversity with Technology</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-understanding-australian-biodiversity-with-technology/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 06:20:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49513</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As a mega-diverse continent, Australia is home to hundreds of thousands of species, with more being discovered every year. Despite this, Australia faces one of the highest species extinction rates, meaning that innovative methods to detect and understand our biodiversity are becoming increasingly important. Advancing technologies like genomics, advanced imaging and machine learning are changing [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>As a mega-diverse continent, Australia is home to hundreds of thousands of species, with more being discovered every year. Despite this, Australia faces one of the highest species extinction rates, meaning that innovative methods to detect and understand our biodiversity are becoming increasingly important.</p>



<p>Advancing technologies like genomics, advanced imaging and machine learning are changing the way that researchers and policymakers respond to climate risks, species conservation and protection, biosecurity and decision-making.</p>



<p>In this webinar hosted by the <a href="https://ala.us14.list-manage.com/track/click?u=b238aea31bbd4bd103ff7368c&amp;id=43167d8001&amp;e=3629824322" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Atlas of Living Australia,</a> hear from three of our partners to explore how they’ve applied next-generation technology to support Australian biodiversity research.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by <a href="https://www.csiro.au/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Atlas of Living Australia Webinar: Understanding Australian Biodiversity with Technology" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1mU1bUfR5xE?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Weblink to recording: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1mU1bUfR5xE">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1mU1bUfR5xE</a>. The event was hosted on 3 June 2024 at 11AM AEST.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-1 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://bioplatforms.com/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="70" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/image.png" alt="Bioplatforms Australia" class="wp-image-49516"/></a></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://www.plantphenomics.org.au/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="428" height="110" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/appn-logo.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49522" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/appn-logo.jpg 428w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/appn-logo-300x77.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 428px) 100vw, 428px" /></a></figure>
</div>



<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow">
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://anif.org.au/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="250" height="102" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/06/image-1.png" alt="National Imaging Facility" class="wp-image-49517"/></a></figure>
</div>
</div>



<p>The ALA was grateful to be joined by the following speakers for this webinar: </p>



<p> Sophie Mazard &amp; Alistair McTaggart from <a href="https://bioplatforms.com/" data-type="link" data-id="https://bioplatforms.com/">Bioplatforms Australia</a>, Donald Hobern from <a href="https://www.plantphenomics.org.au/">Australian Plant Phenomics Network</a>, and Diana Patalwala from <a href="https://anif.org.au/">National Imaging Facility</a>.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft"><img decoding="async" src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALATAB-240220/alamoderator-martin-westgate-135px.jpg?la=en&amp;hash=000621C778F9C3B05D12070053119AA1E746D4F9" alt="Dr Martin Westgate"/></figure></div>


<p><strong>Facilitator: Dr Martin Westgate</strong></p>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Fostering next-gen talent &#8211; life after a CSIRO internship with Caitlin</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/fostering-next-gen-talent-life-after-a-csiro-internship-with-caitlin/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 21:53:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49483</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Caitlin Ramsay completed the CSIRO National Collections and Marine Infrastructure Indigenous Scholarship Program (NISP) in 2022-23. In that time Caitlin worked with the Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) Science and Decision Support team on a project focused on mapping invasive species and how they have moved across Australia over time. Since then, Caitlin has come [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Caitlin Ramsay completed the <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO </a>National Collections and Marine Infrastructure Indigenous Scholarship Program (NISP) in 2022-23. In that time Caitlin worked with the Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) Science and Decision Support team on a project focused on mapping invasive species and how they have moved across Australia over time. Since then, Caitlin has come full circle, joining the <a href="https://arga.org.au/">Australian Reference Genome Atlas</a> (ARGA) team hosted by the ALA.  </p>



<p>We chatted with Caitlin to learn more about her experiences in participating in the NISP internship program and what she&#8217;s working on today.</p>



<p><strong>What initially drew you to participate in the CSIRO NISP program?</strong></p>



<p>When I first stumbled upon the CSIRO NISP program, I was studying a dual degree of bioinformatics engineering and ecology and up until that time had only very basic exposure to using my data analysis skills on environmental data. The description of the CSIRO NISP program through the ALA promoted using data analysis and producing data visualisations using biodiversity data and I immediately thought this would be the perfect opportunity to combine my two passions and learn how to make some cool graphs.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1024x768.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48092" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1024x768.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-300x225.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-768x576.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1536x1152.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-2048x1536.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1920x1440.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-640x480.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Data visualisation produced by Caitlin in her NISP internship with the ALA using galah-python. </figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>How did participating in the program help prepare you for your current role within the ARGA team? What are you currently working on?</strong></p>



<p>Currently I’m working with the ARGA team to help design and implement the user interface of the app’s website. Although this is quite different to the work that I was originally carrying out in the NISP program, learning how to work collaboratively in a team environment and achieve various goals under the guidance and support of my supervisors proved valuable in preparing me for my current role. I was also able to work on a few different tasks for the duration of the NISP program such as assisting in the development of <a href="https://galah.ala.org.au/Python/">galah-python</a> which improved upon my software development skills. The NISP program also allowed me to become more confident in my skillset and learn how to approach and solve novel problems, which are all useful in helping me to complete my day-to-day tasks within the ARGA team.</p>



<p><strong>What made you want to come back to CSIRO as a full-time employee after your internship?</strong></p>



<p>I had an absolute deadly time during my internship mainly due to the stimulating and rewarding work I was undertaking but even more so because of the friendly and welcoming people I got to work with. The culture that the ALA and CSIRO foster is unmatched, and I definitely grew to miss the company of the people I worked alongside which is why I reached out to see if there were any opportunities available after I had graduated!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Square-posts-59-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49485" style="width:496px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Square-posts-59-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Square-posts-59-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Square-posts-59-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Square-posts-59-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Square-posts-59.jpg 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Caitlin after graduating from her double degree from UNSW.</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>What advice would you give to other students considering undertaking a CSIRO NISP internship?</strong></p>



<p>If you’re thinking about applying, just do it! I almost didn’t apply because I didn’t believe I had enough experience, or a developed enough skillset but I’m so glad that I ended up applying in the end. It’s such an amazing learning opportunity and super cool experience being able to work alongside experts and hone your skills; so why try it out!</p>



<p>Applications for the 2024-25 CSIRO NISP program will open in August. Keep an eye out on <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/internships/">ALA Internship Opportunities page</a> for further details and updates. </p>



<p>For more information, contact <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Shell Yeah! Citizen Science Saves Turtles with the 1 Million Turtles Project</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/shell-yeah-citizen-science-saves-turtles-with-the-1-million-turtles-project/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 May 2024 21:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49462</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Today is World Turtle Day! Australia is home to 23 species of freshwater turtles which you can discover through the ALA! We’re celebrating the day by chatting to Dr Ricky Spencer &#8211; Associate Professor from Western Sydney University who co-leads the 1 Million Turtles (1MT) citizen science project. Q: Where did the idea for the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Today is World Turtle Day! Australia is home to 23 species of freshwater turtles which you can discover through the <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/ef8440de-c558-4fdf-9e4c-635a7871f01b#overview" data-type="link" data-id="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/ef8440de-c558-4fdf-9e4c-635a7871f01b#overview">ALA</a>! We’re celebrating the day by chatting to Dr Ricky Spencer &#8211; Associate Professor from <a href="https://www.westernsydney.edu.au/schools/sosc/research/zoological_sciences">Western Sydney University</a> who co-leads the <a href="https://1millionturtles.com/">1 Million Turtles</a> (1MT) citizen science project.</p>



<p><strong>Q: Where did the idea for the 1 Million Turtles project come from?</strong></p>



<p>The story starts with a stark realisation. In 2015, a mysterious virus swept through the Bellinger River in northern New South Wales, wiping out a staggering 90% of the critically endangered <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/e8b0899e-0148-45ba-b2eb-2c42c3ad3d96">Bellinger River Snapping Turtle (</a><em><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/e8b0899e-0148-45ba-b2eb-2c42c3ad3d96">Myuchelys georgesi)</a> </em>population. This devastating event highlighted the urgent need for large-scale freshwater turtle conservation efforts. Researchers from leading Australian universities knew traditional methods wouldn&#8217;t suffice. They needed a way to harness the power of the public, a way to give everyone a voice in turtle conservation. Enter citizen science, and the innovative 1MT project was born.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49463" style="width:1001px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Bellinger-River-Saw-shelled-Turtle-Myuchelys-georgesi-Photo-Credit-Darren-Fielder-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bellinger River Snapping Turtle (<em>Myuchelys georgesi)</em> Photo Credit Darren Fielder CC BY NC.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Q: What role does citizen science play in this project?</strong></p>



<p>Citizen science is at the very core of 1MT. Why? Because freshwater turtles are shy and elusive creatures. Traditional research methods often lack the necessary scope to track their populations effectively. Imagine the difference millions of eyes across the country can make! Through the user-friendly <a href="https://turtlesat.org.au/turtlesat/default.aspx">TurtleSAT app</a>, citizen scientists become data collection heroes.</p>



<p><strong>Q: What kind of turtle data are you interested in collecting through the TurtleSAT app?</strong></p>



<p>TurtleSAT is more than just a reporting tool. Inspired by the Bellinger River crisis, the app is designed to capture a wide range of turtle data. See a healthy turtle basking on a log? Snap a picture and submit it through TurtleSAT. Witness a turtle struggling to cross a busy road? Report the location and type of road within the app. Notice unusual behaviour, like a turtle with lesions or difficulty moving? Document your observations with photos or videos and submit them through TurtleSAT. This detailed data allows researchers to identify threats, track populations, and understand the overall health of freshwater turtle populations.</p>



<p>But 1MT goes beyond mere data collection. The program is passionate about transforming participants from observers to active conservation partners. This is where the exciting turtle data comes in. Citizen scientists are trained to collect information beyond sightings. They learn nest monitoring and protection protocols, conduct standardised surveys for invasive species like foxes (think National Nest Predation Survey), and even analyse data through TurtleSAT. This fosters a sense of ownership and empowers communities to become active conservation stewards.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="392" height="839" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Turtlesatbbb.png" alt="" class="wp-image-49477" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Turtlesatbbb.png 392w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/Turtlesatbbb-140x300.png 140w" sizes="(max-width: 392px) 100vw, 392px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Q: What impacts have you seen from the 1MT project so far?</strong></p>



<p>The impact of the 1MT project has been truly shell-ebrating! Winning the prestigious <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RNR4EqScorM">Eureka Prize for Innovation in Citizen Science in 2023</a> served as a major validation and a springboard for further growth. The recognition brought well-deserved attention to the project&#8217;s innovative approach and its crucial role in turtle conservation.</p>



<p>Another exciting aspect of 1MT is the collaboration with the <a href="https://www.nativetitlesa.org/pbcs/ngarrindjeri-aboriginal-corporation-rntbc/">Ngarrindjeri Aboriginal Corporation</a>. This partnership aims to record the rich knowledge and history of turtles held by the Ngarrindjeri people, the Traditional Owners of the land. Integrating Indigenous knowledge systems with scientific research offers invaluable insights into turtle ecology and conservation practices.</p>



<p>So, what exciting discoveries have emerged from the mountains of data collected so far? Well, the results are nothing short of fascinating! Citizen science data has played a key role in identifying hotspots of turtle mortality on roads. This has led to targeted signage, infrastructure improvements, and the creation of &#8220;Turtle-Safe&#8221; roads. Additionally, the data has informed conservation advice documents for numerous turtle species under the <em>EPBC Act</em>, a critical step towards their protection.</p>



<p>Beyond scientific advancements, the program has fostered a positive shift in public attitudes and behaviours towards turtles. Community initiatives like Turtle Islands – safe havens built by local communities for nesting turtles – showcase the power of collective action.</p>



<p><strong>Q: How can the public get involved?</strong></p>



<p>The 1MT project is actively seeking new citizen scientists to join the movement. How can you get involved? Download the <a href="https://turtlesat.org.au/turtlesat/default.aspx">TurtleSAT app</a>, report your turtle sightings, and participate in data collection efforts. You can also spread awareness about the project, support fundraising initiatives, or even explore volunteering opportunities with local turtle conservation groups. Become a champion for freshwater turtles!</p>



<p>To learn more about the 1 Million Turtles project, visit the website <a href="https://1millionturtles.com/">here</a>, and download the <a href="https://turtlesat.org.au/turtlesat/default.aspx">TurtleSAT App</a>.</p>



<p>View the records of this project on the ALA <a href="https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dr26141">here</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="842" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown--1024x842.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-49465" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown--1024x842.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown--300x247.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown--768x632.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown--1536x1263.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown--1920x1579.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/05/South-Western-Snake-Necked-Turtle-Chelodina-oblonga-via-iNaturalist-Grover-J-Brown-.jpg 2004w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Northern Snake Necked Turtle <em>(Chelodina oblonga) </em>Photo Credit Grover J Brown CC BY NC.</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter March 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-march-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 00:48:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49356</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out the ALA&#8217;s March 2024 Newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p id="block-e6556f64-c2e0-49e7-b903-7825bd5b688f">Check out the ALA&#8217;s <a href="https://us14.campaign-archive.com/?u=b238aea31bbd4bd103ff7368c&amp;id=3b73febd33" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">March 2024 Newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="692" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24-692x1024.png" alt="ALA's March 2024 newsletter header banner - it includes the ALA logo and a waratah, a large red flower" class="wp-image-49359" style="width:519px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24-692x1024.png 692w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24-203x300.png 203w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2024/03/newsletter-march24.png 724w" sizes="(max-width: 692px) 100vw, 692px" /></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; March 2024</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-march-2024/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 23:45:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=49342</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the March 2024 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In this issue we are proud to be launching Round 3 of the ALA Australian Biodiversity Mobilisation Program. This is one of ALA’s flagship programs that was designed three years ago to provide a mechanism to support the digitisation and provision of important biodiversity that may otherwise not be provided to the ALA. In the first two years the program has supported 12 remarkable teams to digitally enable their data and make it available to the ALA as open data, and through that effort internationally to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility. These <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">12 current projects </a>span a range of incredible institutions, species, and provide important geographic coverage. This year we are excited to have secured additional support from <a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/about/challenges-missions/biosecurity">CSIRO’s Catalysing Australia’s Biosecurity initiative</a>. This will provide additional focus on species of biosecurity concern which we know will generate additional excitement around the program, and deliver data to the ALA that assists Australia’s biosecurity sector to better assess risk, and mitigations.</p>



<p>ALA’s <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA-Strategy-2020-2025.pdf">Strategy 2020-2025</a> has an action to ‘establish data priorities to ensure Australia has a nationally comprehensive, representative and adequate biodiversity data infrastructure’. In addition to supporting those parts of the biodiversity data sector that may be resource constrained, the Data Mobilisation Program has become an important mechanism for independently identifying data priorities, whether geographic or taxonomic and starting to fill these gaps in our national biodiversity data system. The existing 12 projects, and approximately nine projects we expect to fund in 2024 will play a fundamental role in ensuring the Australian biodiversity research, management and policy landscape has access to the best available data. The launch of Round 3 also provides a timely reminder that we are keen to grow this important national program through <a href="https://ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/ALA-Australian-Biodiversity-Data-Mobilisation-Program-Prospectus-December-2022.pdf">partnerships</a> with government, industry and the research sector so please do reach out if you’d like to play a supporting role in future years.</p>



<p>We hope you enjoy our March Newsletter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
