<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:07:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Bushfire recovery projects: Increasing our understanding of how nature responds to fire</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/bushfire-recovery-projects-increasing-our-understanding-of-how-nature-responds-to-fire/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:06:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45495</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and the Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (DAWE) are working together on three new innovative citizen projects to enhance our understanding of how Australia’s biodiversity responds to fire and supports bushfire recovery. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-Citizen-Science-V4.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45496" width="220" height="308" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail.png 644w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Bushifre-recovery-projects_thumbnail-214x300.png 214w" sizes="(max-width: 220px) 100vw, 220px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-Citizen-Science-V4.pdf">View and print this impact case study as a pdf</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p><br>The citizen science bushfire recovery projects enable people to connect with nature and science while collecting and processing crucial data for scientists and governments to use in bushfire research and recovery. This work is supported by the Australian Government’s $200 million Bushfire Recovery Program for Wildlife and their Habitat.</p>



<p>“We were pleased to partner with the Atlas of Living Australia for this important community focused work. The three projects will support fire-affected communities to re-engage with nature and the science of recovery. Citizen scientists will be able to collect evidence on the impacts of large-scale fire on biodiversity.”</p>



<p class="has-text-align-right">Dr Fiona Fraser, acting Threatened Species Commissioner, DAWE.</p>



<h2 id="projects-in-focus">Projects in focus</h2>



<h3 id="1-bioblitzes-across-australia">1. BioBlitzes across Australia</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45506" width="294" height="220" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe-640x480.jpg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Waterbug-survey-at-Panboola-BioBlitz_Credit_Atlas-of-LIfe.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 294px) 100vw, 294px" /><figcaption>Community members taking part in a water bug survey  during the Panboola BioBlitz Photo credit: <a href="https://atlasoflife.org.au">Atlas of Life </a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>We are enabling community participation in a series of BioBlitzes in fire affected areas across Australia. The BioBlitzes aim to discover, identify and record as many kinds of species present in a particular area over a 24-hour period. This work is in partnership with the Centre for  Ecosystem Science at UNSW, the Australian Citizen Science Association and Minderoo’s Fire and Flood Resilience initiative.</p>



<h3 id="2-bushfire-recovery-focus-on-flowers">2. Bushfire recovery: focus on flowers</h3>



<p>This project focuses on developing resources for flora-focused citizen science groups to monitor and record information about how flowers, trees and foliage recovery after a fire. This work is in partnership with the Hawkesbury Institute for the Environment at Western Sydney University.</p>



<h3 id="3-digitising-our-insect-collections">3. Digitising our insect collections</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45499" width="306" height="229" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-2048x1536.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-1920x1440.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/ANIC-image-Credit_Nicole-Fisher-NRCA-CSIRO-2-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 306px) 100vw, 306px" /><figcaption>Our National Insect Collection needs help to transcribe text in specimen labels</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>The insect digitisation project focuses on a list of priority insect species. Members of the public participate by using the DigiVol platform to transcribe insect specimen labels in CSIRO’s National Insect Collection. DigiVol is run by the Australian Museum and is supported by Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) infrastructure. Volunteers have already digitised and transcribed 1000s of specimens. Many of the insect specimens being digitised have few or no occurrence records in the ALA and some specimens date back nearly 100 years. This information will help us understand historical changes in insect distribution across space and time.</p>



<h3 id="the-atlas-of-living-australia-delivering-research-ready-data-for-bushfire-research-and-recovery">The Atlas of Living Australia delivering research-ready data for bushfire research and recovery</h3>



<p>This work builds on the lead role the ALA took after the 2019-20 bushfires to explore how the citizen science sector could be supported<br>and coordinated to help deliver research-ready data in the bushfire space. Products from this work included the Citizen Science Bushfire<br>Project Finder and tailored blogs highlighting projects to participate in pre and post disaster events.</p>



<p>IN PARTNERSHIP WITH: </p>



<ul><li>Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p>OUR COLLABORATORS:</p>



<ul><li>The Centre for Ecosystem Science at UNSW</li><li>Hawkesbury Institute for the Environment at</li><li>Western Sydney University</li><li>Australian Citizen Science Association</li><li>Minderoo’s Fire and Flood Resilience initiative</li><li>National Research Collections Australia, CSIRO</li></ul>



<h3 id="more-information">More information</h3>



<p>For more information, read Citizen science to boost existing bushfire recovery activities or contact us at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Echidna CSI: Using citizen science to track echidnas throughout Australia</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/echidna-csi-using-citizen-science-to-track-echidnas-throughout-australia/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 01:34:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45443</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Echidna CSI is a research project run by the University of Adelaide using data collected by citizen scientists to study echidnas. The project has had a huge impact on echidna research and conservation. Using a bespoke mobile app, (which uses the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) BioCollect application as its database) and an army of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Echidna CSI is a research project run by the University of Adelaide using data collected by citizen scientists to study echidnas. The project has had a huge impact on echidna research and conservation.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Echidna-V2.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidna-csi-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45444" width="314" height="440" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidna-csi-thumbnail.png 644w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidna-csi-thumbnail-214x300.png 214w" sizes="(max-width: 314px) 100vw, 314px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/21280-Case-Study-Fact-Sheets-–-Echidna-V2.pdf">View or print this impact story as a pdf</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Using a bespoke mobile app, (which uses the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) BioCollect application as its database) and an army of citizen scientists across the country, Echidna CSI has established an Australia-wide distribution map of Short-Beaked Echidnas (Tachyglossus  culeatus). The project has doubled the number of echidna records in the ALA and discovered new facts about echidna biology. Echidna CSI encourages the public to take photos of echidnas around Australia and collect their scats for DNA and hormone analysis. Over the past<br>three years, thousands of participants have recorded more than 12,000 echidna sightings. This is the largest dataset collected by any project for echidnas. The data is providing valuable information on wild populations’ habitat, diet and health including insights into the impact of  ushfires on echidna microbiomes.</p>



<h3 id="study-the-shy-echidna-challenge-accepted">Study the shy Echidna? Challenge accepted</h3>



<p>Echidnas are notoriously shy and difficult to see in the wild, and prior to Echidna CSI they were considered pretty difficult (and expensive) to  tudy. As a result, although echidnas are iconic  native species and threatened by feral animals, habitat loss and road collisions, many aspects of wild populations including their distribution, biology and population trends were largely unknown. The Echidna CSI project brought<br>together ecologists, molecular researchers and computer scientists from the University of Adelaide, the Atlas of Living Australia’s biodiversity data infrastructure, and Australia’s citizen science community to fill the gaps in our knowledge about echidnas. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1024x794.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45447" width="561" height="435" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1024x794.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-300x233.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-768x595.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1536x1191.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster-1920x1488.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Echidna-CSI_image-by-Cecilia_webster.jpg 2015w" sizes="(max-width: 561px) 100vw, 561px" /><figcaption>Using Echidna CSI citizen scientists can upload sightings of Echidnas <br>from all over Australia. Image credit: Cecilia Webster</figcaption></figure>



<h3 id="ala-tool-enables-scientists-to-tap-into-citizen-workforce">ALA tool enables scientists to tap into citizen workforce</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow.png" alt="" class="wp-image-45446" width="248" height="246" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow.png 585w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow-300x297.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/echidnaCSI_logo_yellow-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 248px) 100vw, 248px" /></figure></div>



<p>The research team developed their own custom mobile application for the collection of data and linked this to the  ALA’s BioCollect field data collection tool as the backend database and data access/visualisation tool, to enable citizen scientists to record echidna observations. All observations flow automatically into the ALA. The project has robust quality assurance processes built into it to ensure all records are verified, research-grade data points.  The research team also have access to all citizen scientist echidna observations in the ALA uploaded via other applications such as iNaturalist. The Echidna CSI app is customised to the project and designed to guide users into collecting information that will be of most use. It also includes fun facts about echidnas so users can learn more about this iconic Australian species.</p>



<h3 id="mobile-app-has-huge-impact-for-echidna-research-and-conservation">Mobile app has huge impact for echidna research and conservation</h3>



<p>By combining novel science with citizen science, the Echidna CSI citizen science project has highlighted the extraordinary power of the citizen<br>science approach. More than 11,000 people have contributed to the Echidna CSI project. These citizen scientists have eyes on the ground in<br>many locations and have contributed sightings and genetic material from all states and territories including throughout protected areas and remote places. The research team could never have surveyed such a large area without the help of the Echidna CSI community contributors.</p>



<p>ALA infrastructure has been crucial in advancing echidna research and making the data, and data visualisations, accessible and open. This has resulted in the ability to leverage translational research, such as examining the impact of fire on echidna populations and diet.</p>



<h3 id="assessing-echidna-populations-after-the-2019-20-bushfires">Assessing echidna populations after the 2019-20 bushfires</h3>



<p>All echidna records collected before the 2019-2020 bushfire season served as crucial baseline information to monitor and assess the health of echidna populations post fire. Echidna CSI has conducted some local scale research in fire impacted areas and is documenting a change in echidna microbiomes in areas such as Kangaroo Island in South Australia. This subspecies of echidnas is listed as endangered, so the more we can learn about their response to fire the better.</p>



<h3 id="research-impact">Research impact</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2351989421001761">Echidna CSI – Improving monitoring of a cryptic species at continental scale using Citizen Science</a>. Alan Stenhouse et al, Ecology and Conservation, Vol 28, Aug 2021</li></ul>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45448" width="445" height="297" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-2048x1365.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Headshot_Tahlia-1920x1280.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 445px) 100vw, 445px" /><figcaption>Postdoctoral Researcher Dr Tahlia Perry from the University of Adelaide leads the Echidna CSI research project.</figcaption></figure></div>



<h3 id="echidna-csi-in-numbers">Echidna CSI in numbers</h3>



<ul><li>12,000 sightings</li><li>11,000 citizen scientists</li><li>700 scat samples</li><li>2017 Echidna CSI launched</li><li>7 states and territories</li><li>Doubled the number of echidna records in the ALA</li></ul>



<h3 id="awards-and-recognition">Awards and recognition</h3>



<ul><li>Finalist in the 2021 Department of Industry, Science, Energy and Resources Eureka Prize for Innovation in Citizen Science</li><li>Finalist for the 2021 South Australian Citizen Science Award</li><li>Finalist in the 2021 South Australian Science Excellence and Innovation for citizen science and PhD research excellence</li></ul>



<h3 id="for-more-information">For more information</h3>



<ul><li>Echidna CSI is available to download on both Android and Apple devices. </li><li>For more information on the ALA visit <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">ala.org.au</a> or contact <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></li></ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Advisory Board update</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-advisory-board-update/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Sep 2021 23:40:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45228</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Our Advisory Board is undergoing a reshuffle. We farewell and thank our Chair Dr Diana Day and welcome the new Chair, Dr Ian Cresswell, and a new member, Dr Manu Saunders, to guide us through the next few years. Welcome to Dr Ian Cresswell, Chair We are excited to announce that Dr Ian Cresswell will [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Our Advisory Board is undergoing a reshuffle. We farewell and thank our Chair Dr Diana Day and welcome the new Chair, Dr Ian Cresswell, and a new member, Dr Manu Saunders, to guide us through the next few years.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45234" width="318" height="285" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped.jpg 945w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped-300x269.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Photo-Ian-Cresswell_Cropped-768x689.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 318px) 100vw, 318px" /><figcaption>Dr Ian Cresswell</figcaption></figure></div>



<h2 id="welcome-to-dr-ian-cresswell-chair"><strong>Welcome to Dr Ian Cresswell, Chair</strong></h2>



<p>We are excited to announce that Dr Ian Cresswell will take on the role of Chair from our October 2021 meeting.</p>



<p>Ian is well known to the ALA having played a significant role in the establishment of the ALA, and as a member of the Management Committee.</p>



<p>His background in conservation planning, biodiversity science and deep networks into Government through his more recent role with the National State of the Environment Report will be an asset to the Board and the ALA.</p>



<p>Ian has a long history of success in managing large scale, science-based government programs in natural resource management, with a strong focus on management to sustainably achieve economic, social and environmental benefits. He has extensive experience in providing high level advice to Government and Industry on environmental and sustainability issues. He brings national and international experience in protected areas spatial planning, fisheries and wildlife regulation, and biodiversity discovery/taxonomy. He has led major research programs in CSIRO in both terrestrial and marine domains, as well as Australian Government senior executive management roles in marine planning, sustainable fisheries, and wildlife management. Ian was the Director of the Australian Biological Resources Study and was instrumental in the development of Australia’s Virtual Herbarium and the Online Zoological Collections of Australian Museums.</p>



<h2 id="welcome-dr-manu-saunders"><strong>Welcome Dr Manu Saunders</strong></h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-45232" width="336" height="253" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited.jpg 816w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/Manu-saunders_Cathedral-rock-edited-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 336px) 100vw, 336px" /><figcaption> Dr Manu Saunders is a popular and engaging ecological scientist and communicator. You can follow her on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/ManuSaunders">@ManuSaunders.</a> </figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Manu Saunders is a Lecturer in Ecology at the University of New England, Armidale. Her research and teaching focus on community ecology and ecosystem function and services, particularly related to plant-insect interactions. Prior to studying ecology and embarking on a research career, she completed a degree in English and print journalism and worked in corporate communications.</p>



<p>She is passionate about observing nature and ecological science communication. Manu has published her popular science blog <a href=":%20http:/ecologyisnotadirtyword.com/">Ecology is not a Dirty Word</a> for over 10 years and is an internationally-recognised expert on insect conservation and ecology. She also co-founded the Wild Pollinator Count, Australia’s national citizen science project engaging people with wild pollinator conservation and ecology.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="farewell-to-our-current-chair-dr-diana-day"><strong>Farewell to our current Chair, Dr Diana Day</strong></h2>



<p>We would like to sincerely thank Dr Diana Day for her contribution to the governance of the ALA. Diana has been instrumental in steering the board and the ALA through a challenging COVID period and preparing the ALA so effectively for its engagement with the National Research Infrastructure Roadmap process. Her role ensuring effective board oversight of some of ALAs recent significant transformations, including our cyber security review has been appreciated.</p>



<h2 id="ala-advisory-board-membership-september-2021"><strong>ALA Advisory Board membership September 2021</strong></h2>



<p>The ALA Advisory Board supports the high-level direction and delivery of the ALA by providing vision, advocacy and advice.</p>



<ul><li>Chair: Dr Ian Cresswell, Adjunct Professor, School of Biological, Earth and Environmental Sciences, UNSW at UNSW</li><li>Dr Bek Christensen, Programs Director of the Peter Cullen Trust and President, Ecological Society of Australia</li><li>Mr Matthew Miles, Principal for Environmental Information, South Australian Department for Environment and Water</li><li>Mr Brant Smith, Assistant Secretary, Geospatial and Information Analytics, Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment</li><li>Dr Stephen van Leeuwen, BHP/Curtin Indigenous Professor in Biodiversity &amp; Environmental Science, Curtin University</li><li>Dr Manu Saunders, Lecturer in Ecology and Biology, School of Environmental and Rural Science, University of New England</li><li>Professor David Cantrill (ex-officio), Executive Director Science, Royal Botanic Gardens Victoria</li><li>Ms Toni Moate (ex-officio), Director, National Collections and Marine Infrastructure, CSIRO</li><li>Dr Andre Zerger (ex-officio), Director, Atlas of Living Australia</li></ul>



<h2 id="more-info">More info</h2>



<p>For more information about the ALA and our Advisory Board, visit <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/governance/">About us</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA webinar: Saving species at speed – Conservation and the science of animal movement</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-saving-species-at-speed-conservation-and-the-science-of-animal-movement/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 00:38:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=45001</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Australian animals show an enormous diversity of movement behaviour, due to a long evolutionary history of adaptation to highly variable – and occasionally extreme – environmental conditions. In this webinar, you will hear from three researchers investigating animal movement over different spatial and temporal scales, from individual habitat patches in our cities; to nomadic movements [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Australian animals show an enormous diversity of movement behaviour, due to a long evolutionary history of adaptation to highly variable – and occasionally extreme – environmental conditions. In this webinar, you will hear from three researchers investigating animal movement over different spatial and temporal scales, from individual habitat patches in our cities; to nomadic movements spanning millions of hectares; to shifts in species distributions across geological timescales. Join us to hear more about our amazing fauna and how science is shedding light on ways to conserve Australia’s biodiversity.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA webinar series Saving species at speed Conservation and the science of animal movement 9 21 2021" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1wmq4dp3ldU?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEST, Tuesday 21 September 2021, with 274 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="holly-kirk-rmit">Holly Kirk | RMIT</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/HollyKirk-135px.jpg" alt="Holly Kirk" class="wp-image-45003"/></figure></div>



<p>Holly is a member of the Interdisciplinary Conservation Science Group at RMIT University, and the Clean Air and Urban Landscapes NESP Hub. She specialises in understanding how animals move around their environments, and is passionate about translating scientific theory into positive on-ground action for people and nature. As an expert in ecology and spatial modelling, Holly has been using this knowledge to plan cities that support and enhance urban biodiversity. Most recently, she has been developing a tool to quantify ecological connectivity and applying this within the Biodiversity Sensitive Urban Design framework to several development projects, including the renewal of Fisherman’s Bend (Melbourne).</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="julia-ryeland-university-of-western-sydney">Julia Ryeland | University of Western Sydney</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image is-style-default"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/JuliaRyeland-135px.jpg" alt="Julia Ryeland" class="wp-image-45004"/></figure></div>



<p>Julia is an ecological consultant, focused primarily on management of microbats in urban environments. She has broad interests in applying behavioural ecology research to conservation and management problems. This has predominately involved research on avian systems, including understanding behavioural thermoregulatory adaptation in a wetland context and sensitivity of birds under climate change, and more recently, management of emus in urbanising areas. Julia completed her PhD on male reproductive behaviour and success in emus in 2020, and has worked with governmental bodies to determine best-practice management of emus across the east coast of Australia, where they are known to be disappearing.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="ross-crates-anu">Ross Crates | ANU</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/RossCrates-135px.jpg" alt="Ross Crates" class="wp-image-45005"/></figure></div>



<p>Ross is a postdoctoral research fellow with the Difficult Bird Research Group at the Fenner School, ANU. His work is broadly related to woodland bird conservation, with a particular focus on the regent honeyeater. His recent research on regent honeyeaters has explored the loss of song culture, quantifying megafire impacts, population genetics, management of the Noisy Miner, and population viability analysis.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin Westgate is Science Advisor to the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">Atlas of Living Australia</a> and a visiting fellow at the <a href="https://fennerschool.anu.edu.au/">Fenner School of Environment &amp; Society</a> at the Australian National University. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:60px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="want-more">Want more?</h2>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a> along with other video content.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter September 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-september-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 01:19:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44950</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Atlas of Living Australian Newsletter February 2021]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/10/ALA-Newsletter-September-2021-.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/newsletter-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44951" width="308" height="412" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/newsletter-thumbnail.png 486w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/newsletter-thumbnail-224x300.png 224w" sizes="(max-width: 308px) 100vw, 308px" /></a></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/ALA-Newsletter-Feb-2021.pdf">Atlas of Living Australian Newsletter February 20</a><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/10/ALA-Newsletter-September-2021-.pdf">21</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Message from our Director &#8211; September 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/newsletter/message-from-our-director-september-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 06:32:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44932</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the September 2021 edition of our newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/Andre-Zerger-portrait-2019-1-300x300-2.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44152" width="179" height="179" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/Andre-Zerger-portrait-2019-1-300x300-2.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/Andre-Zerger-portrait-2019-1-300x300-2-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 179px) 100vw, 179px" /></figure></div>



<p>The critical importance of identifying, describing, conserving and restoring biodiversity is receiving increasing recognition due to the cumulative impacts of species loss (Woinarski et al 2019), climate change (Hoffman et al 2015), summer bushfires (Godfrey et al, 2021, Saunders et al 2021) and increasing biosecurity threats in Australia (Dodd et al 2020). Understanding the role of biodiversity plays in human health (Bratman et al. 2019) and the provision of ecosystem services to support a more sustainable agricultural sector, continues to demand innovative research solutions.</p>



<p>In parallel, Australia’s environmental policy and management landscape invests significant resources into biodiversity conservation, restoration and planning, in addition to supporting a world-class national biosecurity system that aims to maintain the health of our natural, agricultural and economic systems. This includes Commonwealth Government programs such as Agriculture Stewardship Package to promote biodiversity stewardship, wildlife and habitat funding totalling $200 million in response to 2019-20 bushfires, and the Regional Land Partnership program that is investing $450 million in species recovery and protecting threatened ecological communities.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA_Year_in_Review_2020-21_web5MB.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA-Year-in-Review-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44933" width="328" height="329" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA-Year-in-Review-thumbnail.png 710w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA-Year-in-Review-thumbnail-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA-Year-in-Review-thumbnail-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 328px) 100vw, 328px" /></a><figcaption>Our<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA_Year_in_Review_2020-21_web5MB.pdf"> ALA Year in Review 2020-21</a> highlights our achievements over the past year and the fundamental contributions from our data partners.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Collectively these research, policy and management programs demand continued access to the world-class sovereign biodiversity data infrastructure provided by the Atlas of Living Australia and our partners. We are proud to be playing an important role in ensuring research and decision-making is informed by the best available biodiversity data.</p>



<p>With this context in mind, in this issue of our newsletter we reflect on ALA’s fundamental role with the release of <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/09/ALA_Year_in_Review_2020-21_web5MB.pdf">our first Year-in-Review 2020-21</a>.  The year-in-review showcases our last year and reflects on the fundamental contribution made by our partners in supporting the mission of the ALA. Importantly it recognises the criticality of the Australian Government’s National Collaborative Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) program in shaping and supporting world-class national research infrastructure.</p>



<p>Which leads me to our future and the National Research Infrastructure (NRI) Roadmap process that is currently being led by the Department of Education, Skills and Employment, and the <a href="https://2021nriroadmap.dese.gov.au/about/expert-working-group/">NRI Expert Working Group</a> which will steer the development of the Roadmap. For our stakeholders with an interest in the future of NRIs such as the ALA we encourage you to visit <a href="https://2021nriroadmap.dese.gov.au/">https://2021nriroadmap.dese.gov.au/</a> to learn how you can get more involved.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy the September 2021 issue of our newsletter and look forward to seeing you in our upcoming science webinars.</p>



<p>Dr Andre Zerger</p>



<p>Director, Atlas of Living Australia</p>



<p><strong>References</strong></p>



<ul><li>Deloitte Access Economics (2021) Cost benefit analysis of a mission to discovery and document Australia’s species, prepared for the Australian Academy of Sciences, October 2020, pp. 57.</li><li>Dodd, A, Stoeckl, N, Baumgartner, J, Kompas, T. (2020) Key Result Summary: Valuing Australia’s biosecurity system, Centre of Excellent for Biosecurity Risk Analysis, pp. 41.</li><li>Godfree, R.C., Knerr, N., Encinas-Viso, F.&nbsp;<em>et al.</em>&nbsp;Implications of the 2019–2020 megafires for the biogeography and conservation of Australian vegetation.&nbsp;<em>Nat Commun</em>&nbsp;<strong>12,&nbsp;</strong>1023 (2021). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21266-5">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-21266-5</a></li><li>Hoffmann, A.A., Rymer, P.D., Byrne, M., Ruthrof, K.X., Whinam, J., McGeoch, M., Bergstrom, D.M., Guerin, G.R., Sparrow, B., Joseph, L., Hill, S.J., Andrew, N.R., Camac, J., Bell, N., Riegler, M., Gardner, J.L. and Williams, S.E. (2019), Impacts of recent climate change on terrestrial flora and fauna: Some emerging Australian examples. <em>Austral Ecology</em>, 44: 3-27.&nbsp;<a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/aec.12674">https://doi.org/10.1111/aec.12674</a></li><li>Saunders, M.E., Barton, P.S., Bickerstaff, J.R.M., Frost, L., Latty, T., Lessard, B.D., Lowe, E.C., Rodriguez, J., White, T.E. and Umbers, K.D.L. (2021), Limited understanding of bushfire impacts on Australian invertebrates. <em>Insect Conserv Divers</em>, 14: 285-293. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1111/icad.12493">https://doi.org/10.1111/icad.12493</a></li><li>Woinarski, J.C.Z., M.F. Braby, A.A. Burbidge, D. Coates, S.T. Garnett, R.J. Fensham, S.M. Legge, N.L. McKenzie, J.L. Silcock, B.P. Murphy (2019) Reading the black book: The number, timing, distribution and causes of listed extinctions in Australia, <em>Biological Conservation</em>, Volume 239, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.biocon.2019.108261.</li></ul>



<p></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A new version of galah available now</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/tools-apps/a-new-version-of-galah-available-now/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 26 Aug 2021 00:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tools & Apps]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44916</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’ve released an updated version of galah, our R package for acquiring data from the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA). ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44815" width="231" height="266" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png 434w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630-260x300.png 260w" sizes="(max-width: 231px) 100vw, 231px" /></figure></div>



<p><strong>galah </strong>makes it easier to find, download and analyse data on Australian biodiversity using R, an open-source coding software. Since its initial release in July, thousands of download requests have been made using <strong>galah</strong>.</p>



<p>The new version (1.3.1) brings two exciting features to <strong>galah </strong>for the first time.</p>



<h2 id="range-queries-now-possible"><strong>Range queries now possible</strong></h2>



<p>First, this version supports ‘range queries’; that is, the capacity to state that you want values that are above or below a particular value. This makes it simple to state that you want all records after a particular year, or above a particular elevation. Combined with the ability to specify Boolean queries (such as AND, OR, NOT), this version of <strong>galah </strong>is a major upgrade. See the ‘<a href="https://atlasoflivingaustralia.github.io/galah/reference/select_filters.html">select_filters</a>’ page for more information.</p>



<h2 id="search-taxonomic-data-stored-by-the-ala"><strong>Search taxonomic data stored by the ALA</strong></h2>



<p>Second, and more importantly, version 1.3.1 introduces the <strong>ala_taxonomy() </strong>function. This function provides a new way to search through the taxonomic hierarchy within the ALA.</p>



<p>Taxonomic information downloaded using <strong>ala_taxonomy()</strong> is now returned as a taxonomic tree. This capability enables users to search for which lower clades are contained within a specified taxon. For example, users can find all clades at the family rank that stem from the class “Mammalia”. They can also search down to a number of other less formal taxonomic sub-ranks.</p>



<p>Taxonomic trees preserve ranks within their data structure, offering new opportunities to create data visualisations that harness this information. For a more detailed look at using <strong>ala_taxonomy()</strong>, see the <a href="https://atlasoflivingaustralia.github.io/galah/articles/taxonomic_information.html">Taxonomic Information page</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="872" height="872" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/galah-blog-new-release-1.3.1-taxonomic-visualisation.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44917" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/galah-blog-new-release-1.3.1-taxonomic-visualisation.png 872w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/galah-blog-new-release-1.3.1-taxonomic-visualisation-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/galah-blog-new-release-1.3.1-taxonomic-visualisation-150x150.png 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/galah-blog-new-release-1.3.1-taxonomic-visualisation-768x768.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 872px) 100vw, 872px" /><figcaption>This hierarchy diagram shows Taxonomic Orders within the Phylum Chordata as retrieved from the ALA using the <strong>ala_taxonomy() </strong>function in <strong>galah</strong>.</figcaption></figure>



<h2 id="need-help-or-more-information"><strong>Need help or more information?</strong></h2>



<p>We’ll keep working on ways to make <strong>galah </strong>better over the coming months, so if you have any questions, comments, or spot any bugs, <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">email us</a> or <a href="https://github.com/AtlasOfLivingAustralia/galah/issues">report an issue</a> on our github page.</p>



<p>You can find more information on how to use <strong>galah </strong>on the <a href="https://atlasoflivingaustralia.github.io/galah/index.html">galah R package website</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Global partnership paves way for ALA system upgrade</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/global-partnership-paves-way-for-ala-system-upgrade/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 05:48:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44907</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In June this year we upgraded our ALA systems to make them more reliable, more robust, and equipped to manage increasing amounts of biodiversity data. The major upgrade was possible due to our close partnership with GBIF – the Global Biodiversity Information Facility. The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, an [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/GBIF-logo-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44593" width="323" height="154"/></figure></div>



<p>In June this year we upgraded our ALA systems to make them more reliable, more robust, and equipped to manage increasing amounts of biodiversity data. The major upgrade was possible due to our close partnership with GBIF – the Global Biodiversity Information Facility.</p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, an international network and data infrastructure funded by the world&#8217;s governments and aimed at providing anyone, anywhere, open access to biodiversity data.</p>



<h2 id="collaboration"><strong>Collaboration</strong></h2>



<p>Our systems upgrade is the result of more than 12 months of collaborative work between teams based in Australia, UK and Denmark.</p>



<p>The development teams established a software codebase shared by both teams and worked on a framework for genuinely open-source software development.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“The ALA and GBIF development teams worked so well together. There’s a strong sense of trust and confidence in the skills of each team leading to individual contributions contributing to the larger whole.</p><p>Our teams know that accessible, high quality biodiversity data is improving research and environmental outcomes across the globe and that their efforts are integral to making this happen,” said Joe Miller, executive secretary of GBIF and former research group leader at the Centre for Australian National Biodiversity Research, CSIRO.</p></blockquote>



<h2 id="major-upgrade-reaps-benefits-for-users"><strong>Major upgrade reaps benefits for users</strong></h2>



<h3 id="efficiency-and-effectiveness"><strong>Efficiency and effectiveness</strong></h3>



<p>The new infrastructure, using GBIF/ALA shared codebase, increases indexing speeds for the ALA, reduces its running costs, and reduces long-term technical debt. With the ALA&#8217;s infrastructure growing in excess of millions of biodiversity occurrence records annually, such efficiencies are critical. </p>



<p>Javier Molina, ALA’s Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project Lead, was pleased to report that users have noticed the system is more responsive, particularly when searching species data, using map-based navigation, and using the Spatial Portal (ALA’s analytical tool).</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Prior to the upgrade, we were experiencing some unscheduled outages every month. Since the project went live in June, we haven’t received any reports of unscheduled outages. The system has also coped well with high peaks of utilisation,” said Javier.</p><p>“We recently ingested a dataset from eBird Australia of more than 20 million records, this went smoothy and without issue. A dataset that large would have created lots of headaches for us in the old system.”</p></blockquote>



<h3 id="consistency-is-key"><strong>Consistency is key</strong></h3>



<p>Consistency between the ALA, GBIF and other biodiversity infrastructures is another component of the recent upgrade.</p>



<p>Many users of the ALA also frequently access data through GBIF. For these users, the benefits of a shared infrastructure are clear. Shared approaches to processing biodiversity data eliminate potential sources of confusion for users. For example, if there are consistent flags and interpretations, users become comfortable and proficient using multiple platforms.  </p>



<h3 id="international-living-atlases-will-also-benefit-from-upgrade"><strong>International Living Atlases will also benefit from upgrade</strong></h3>



<p>Software originally developed by the Atlas of Living Australia team is increasingly used across the GBIF network. There are now 27 installations around the world. Some of these are national biodiversity databases and some are thematic, regional or institutional instances. The International Living Atlases is a collaborative global community that supports developers who implement the open-source platform.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Our collaborative work with GBIF has built social capital in the global community, and it is an excellent entry point for the International Living Atlases community to jump onboard,” said Javier.<br><br>“Completion of this first phase now makes it possible for the international community to co-develop new features and work on other mutual areas of interest and concern, including a shared registry and improved handling of sampling-event datasets.”</p></blockquote>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Core-infrastructure-upgrade-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44911" width="919" height="768"/></figure></div>



<h2 id="technical-details"><strong>Technical details</strong></h2>



<ul><li>AWS: virtual infrastructure from AWS performs better and is more affordable. The biggest impact on the infrastructure costs is by far the migration of storage for images from block storage (standard file system) to AWS S3.</li></ul>



<ul><li>Solr search engine: By optimising our software stack with the Solr search engine we reduced the required server specifications compared to the previous infrastructure.</li><li>On day 1, the project went live on an infrastructure that was 43% more affordable than the old infrastructure. This represents a saving of A$79K per annum<a> (</a>comparison based on full on-demand price, production-only systems).</li></ul>



<p>The savings on running a more stable system and co-maintaining an up-to-date codebase will be significant.</p>



<h3 id="next-steps"><strong>Next steps</strong></h3>



<p>The roll-out of the upgrade in June was the first of three stages in the project.</p>



<p>Working from a shared codebase allows us to collaborate and innovate together, for example with respect to improving how we handle eDNA data, establishing common vocabularies, and simplifying the data ingestion process.</p>



<p><br>For more details, visit our <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/core-infrastructure-upgrade-project/">Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project page</a>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Science Week 13-21 August 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/national-science-week-13-21-august-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 02:08:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44881</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are so many great events happening this week, and many of them are online so everyone can get their science on!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/"><img loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/SW21_webbanner600x400-1.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-44894"/></a></figure></div>



<p>Here are a few great events from some our partners. </p>



<h3 id="great-southern-bioblitz">Great Southern BioBlitz</h3>



<p>The Great Southern BioBlitz is an international period of intense biological surveying that attempts to record all the living species within several designated areas across the Southern Hemisphere in Spring.</p>



<p>During National Science Week, Great Southern BioBlitz is hosting two webinars on how to use iNaturalist</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/a-beginners-guide-for-using-inaturalist-2/">A beginners guide for using iNaturalist </a> (Tuesday 17 Aug 8:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;9:00pm)</li></ul>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/a-beginners-guide-for-using-inaturalist/">Advanced tips for using iNaturalist </a> (Tuesday 7 Sep 8:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;9:00pm)</li></ul>



<h3 id="atlas-of-life-in-the-coastal-wilderness"><strong>Atlas of Life in the Coastal Wilderness</strong></h3>



<p>The Atlas of Life in the Coastal Wilderness have put together an amazing program of activities for Science Week, including:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://nsweducation.zoom.us/meeting/register/u5ApcO2rpzgsGNzrZrkZTDKSN0qa0WsuJwQj"><strong>The Atlas of Life and iNaturalist</strong></a> (Monday 16 August 1.50pm)</li><li><a href="https://nsweducation.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN_oBSz2f4bSuyjnqBw8JL9QA">Bee hotels &#8211; to boost bees after fire </a>(Monday 16 August)</li><li><a href="https://nsweducation.zoom.us/meeting/register/u50vd-6urz4pGNaUoKQEzyhIeEoYHKFmCciP">Echidna CSI: Combining citizen science with microbiome research to asses bushfire impacts on echidnas </a>(Wednesday 18 August)</li></ul>



<p>Check out <a href="https://atlasoflife.org.au/2020-national-science-week-1">Atlas of Life in the Coastal Wilderness &#8211; National Science Week </a>for more details.</p>



<p></p>



<h3 id="frogid-informing-frog-conservation-through-citizen-science"><strong>FrogID: informing frog conservation through citizen science</strong></h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/frogid-informing-frog-conservation-through-citizen-science-tickets-164217732659">Informing frog conservation through citizen science</a>  (Thursday 12 August 2021, 7:30 PM – 8:30 PM AEST)</li></ul>



<p></p>



<h3 id="australian-museum-and-the-royal-botanic-gardens-sydney">Australian Museum and The Royal Botanic Gardens, Sydney</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/sydney-science-trail-live-at-royal-botanic-garden-sydney/">Sydney Science Trail:</a> ONLINE EVENT (Friday 13 Aug&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;Monday 13 Sep 12:00am&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;11:45pm)</li></ul>



<p></p>



<h3 id="museums-victoria">Museums Victoria</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/climate-change-families-for-a-thriving-future/">Climate Change: Families for a Thriving Future webinar</a> (Sunday 15 Aug 4:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;5:00pm)</li></ul>



<p></p>



<h3 id="wabsi-webinar">WABSI webinar</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/wabsi-webinar-big-issues-in-biodiversity-science-digitalisation-in-environmental-assessment-international-frontrunners/">Big issues in biodiversity science: Digitalisation in Environmental Assessment – International Frontrunners</a> (Wednesday 18 Aug 4:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;5:30pm)</li></ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Citizen science conference ticket giveaway</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/citizen-science/citizen-science-conference-ticket-giveaway/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:35:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44875</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Win a complimentary registration to the ACSA virtual conference from 27 to 29 October 2021.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/ACSA-conference.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44876" width="285" height="198" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/ACSA-conference.png 605w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/ACSA-conference-300x209.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px" /></a></figure></div>



<p>We’re proud to be sponsoring this year’s ACSA conference and we’re giving away one registration ticket to <a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/">“CitSciOz21: Celebrate, Communicate, Co-create” the Australian Citizen Science Association’s virtual conference 27 – 29 October, 2021</a> (valued at $105.00), </p>



<p>To be in the running, respond to our Twitter or Facebook posts about the competition and tell us about your favourite species observation, why it’s your favourite and which platform you used to record it.</p>



<p>Visit us on <a href="https://twitter.com/atlaslivingaust">Twitter</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/atlaslivingaust">@atlaslivingaust</a>) or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/atlasoflivingaustralia">Facebook </a>(<a href="https://www.facebook.com/atlasoflivingaustralia">atlasoflivingaustralia</a>) and tell us about your favourite species observation.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/CS-photo-compressed.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44877" width="326" height="184" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/CS-photo-compressed.png 682w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/CS-photo-compressed-300x169.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 326px) 100vw, 326px" /></figure></div>



<ul><li>You can post your favourite species observation photo Twitter and tag @atlaslivingaust in the post. Tell us why it’s your favourite observation and what citizen science app or platform you used to record your observation.</li><li>You can copy the url for your favourite observation, in the comments below our Twitter or Facebook posts, or direct message us on Facebook or Twitter, be sure to tell us which platform you used to record your observation and why it&#8217;s your favourite</li><li>Or use the Twitter and Facebook comments to tell us about your favourite species observation, which platform you used to record it and why it’s your favourite.</li></ul>



<p>This promotion is in no way sponsored, endorsed or administered by, or associated with, Twitter or Facebook.</p>



<p>We can’t wait to see your favourite observations!</p>



<h3 id="more-about-citscioz21-australian-citizen-science-association-conference">More about <a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/?sfw=pass1628638674">CitSciOz21 Australian Citizen Science Association conference</a> </h3>



<p>This year the ACSA conference will be delivered online. There is great program of events structured around the following themes:</p>



<ul><li>Celebrate: <strong>Explore, investigate and showcase successful citizen science projects from Australia and the rest of the world.</strong></li></ul>



<ul><li>Communicate: <strong>Showcase citizen science communication techniques for maximum impact.</strong></li></ul>



<ul><li>Co-Create: <strong>Encourage inclusiveness and bring together a diverse array of people to discover better science.</strong></li></ul>



<p>Two of the keynote speakers are Dr Cathy Foley and Dr Karl Kruszelnicki.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="323" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-1024x323.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44886" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-1024x323.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-300x95.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-768x243.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-1536x485.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote.png 1900w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="323" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-1024x323.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44887" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-1024x323.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-300x95.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-768x243.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-1536x485.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote.png 1900w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h3 id="terms-and-conditions"><strong>Terms and conditions</strong></h3>



<h4 id="competition-to-win-one-registration-ticket-for-citscioz21-celebrate-communicate-co-create-the-4th-conference-of-the-australian-citizen-science-association-27-29-october">Competition to win one registration ticket for “CitSciOz21: Celebrate, Communicate, Co-create” The 4th conference of the Australian Citizen Science Association 27 – 29 October, 2021.</h4>



<ol type="1"><li>The promoter is the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (“CSIRO”) (ABN 41 687 119 230), Clunies Ross Street, Black Mountain, ACT, Australia.</li><li>Entry to the competition is open to all Australian residents aged 18 years or over. Employees, directors and officers of CSIRO or any person associated with the Competition, or any organisation or individual associated with the provision of the prize(s) are not eligible to enter.</li><li>Each entry must be made in accordance with these Terms and Conditions. By entering the Competition, each entrant agrees to be bound by these Terms and Conditions. Entries not submitted in accordance with the Terms and Conditions may be deemed ineligible.&nbsp; Information on how to enter and prize details form part of these Terms and Conditions.</li><li>The promotion is in no way sponsored, endorsed, administered by or associated with Facebook or Twitter.</li><li>All respondents who post their favourite observations to Twitter and tag @atlaslivingaust and specify which citizen science app they used to upload their observation will be considered contenders to win one registration to the Australian Citizen Science Association Virtual Conference 2021 ‘Celebrate, Communicate, Co-create’ 27 – 29 October, 2021(of one available) (individual value $105.00) <a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/">https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/</a></li><li>Entries can also be in the form of a Twitter or Facebook post, or a comment in response to our Twitter or Facebook posts about the competition, or a direct message via Twitter or Facebook.</li><li>Entrants may only submit one entry to the competition and may only win one prize.</li><li>The Competition period commences at 11:59pm on 10 August 2021 and closes&nbsp;31 August at midnight. Any entry received by the promoter before or after the Competition period may be ineligible for entry and no responsibility will be accepted for lost, late or misdirected submissions.</li><li>The promoter may at its absolute discretion remove or reject any entry for any reason whatsoever.</li><li>Each entrant warrants that its entry does not breach the copyright or other intellectual property rights or privacy rights of any other person.</li><li>The entries will be judged on originality, creativity, and aesthetics by a panel of CSIRO staff on&nbsp;1 September 2021.</li><li>The winner will be notified within seven business days via Facebook direct message or Twitter direct message (whichever platform was used to submit the entry). The prize will be sent to the email supplied by the winner after the announcement of the winner. The prize is not transferable or exchangeable or redeemable for cash. We will make reasonable efforts to ensure winners receive their prize. Where we are not able to deliver a prize despite making reasonable efforts to do so the prize will be reassigned.</li><li>If there are any unclaimed or un-awarded prizes a second judging&nbsp;will be conducted following the same criteria on&nbsp;8 September 2021 at the same time and place as the original judging. The new winner&nbsp;will be contacted by email within two business days. A prize will be deemed to be unclaimed if we have been unable to contact the prize winner through the contact details provided by 11.59 pm on&nbsp;15 September 2021.</li><li>If the Competition is interfered with in any way or is not capable of being conducted as reasonably anticipated due to any reason beyond the control of the CSIRO, including as a result of technical failures, CSIRO reserves the right, in its sole discretion, to the fullest extent permitted by law to modify, postpone, suspend, terminate or cancel the Competition as appropriate.</li><li>Except for any liability that cannot by law be excluded including any statutory consumer guarantees, CSIRO, nor any of their respective officers, employees and agents will be liable for any injury, damages, expenses, or loss whatsoever (whether direct or consequential) to persons or property as a result of any person entering the Competition or accepting or using any prize, including without limitation, failure of any winner to contact the promoter, non-receipt of any prize or damage to any prize in transit.</li><li>Any questions about CSIRO’s privacy policy or any request to access, modify or delete any information provided in an entry should be directed to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></li></ol>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
