<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:47:52 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.9</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Updating our taxonomic backbone for accuracy, names matching and better searchability</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/updating-our-taxonomic-backbone-for-accuracy-names-matching-and-better-searchability/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 22:16:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=51081</guid>

					<description><![CDATA["Your hip bone's connected to your back bone" goes the old song, but did you know the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) uses a backbone as well? Ours is taxonomy and we use it to arrange all the names in the ALA.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-51110" style="aspect-ratio:1.4992854967554525;width:438px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1-1920x1280.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Eastern-Dwarf-Tree-Frog-Litoria-fallax-Photo-Credit-Isaac-Clarey-CC-BY-NC-1.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Eastern Sedgefrog (<em>Drymomantis fallax</em>). Photo: Isaac Clarey, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Taxonomy is the science of naming, describing and classifying organisms. It’s the basis for how data in the ALA are organised.</p>



<p>Species taxonomy is continuously evolving based on new scientific discoveries (new species being described), as well as techniques such as genetic sequencing, bioinformatics and advanced imaging which can change the way researchers understand existing species leading to re-classification and new names.</p>



<p>For the past two years, we have been changing and cleaning up our <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000261677-taxonomy-in-the-ala">ALA taxonomic backbone</a>. The first stage was the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/whats-in-a-name-refreshing-the-ala-taxonomy/">taxonomic backbone refresh</a> we released in 2024. Now, we are replacing that with a brand new backbone that should make it easier for our users to navigate and find the species information they need.</p>



<p>The biggest change should be almost invisible to our users – we’ve spent 12 months identifying and removing duplicates and unnecessary names, and correctly linking synonyms (different names for the same species) that were previously unlinked (being treated as different species). This reduced the number of species names in the ALA down from 283,000 to 218,000.</p>



<p>The next stage was to look at the 9 million records that either didn’t match to the taxonomic backbone or matched at higher taxonomic levels. Quite often these are as a result of spelling errors in the scientific names on observations, the use of common names instead of scientific names and other issues. We’ve directed many of these records to the correct species.</p>



<p>As a consequence, this has redirected around another 2 million records to the correct species. More importantly, these changes have added the first data for over 10,000 species. And, for over 4,000 species, correctly redirected records have increased their number of records by more than 40%.</p>



<p>Our new backbone taxonomy now matches to 99% of all statutory and state lists. Ultimately this update makes our taxonomy more accurate and our records easier to search and use.</p>



<p>So, what else is different? To make that clearer, we’ll need to go through how data is structured in the backbone.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="how-are-species-structured-in-the-ala">How are species structured in the ALA?</h3>



<p>The ALA taxonomic backbone is based on the <a href="https://biodiversity.org.au/nsl/">National Species List (NSL)</a>. Because the ALA includes herbarium data (plants and fungi) from New Zealand and because we also cover groups that the NSL does not cover (eg bacteria and viruses), we also draw names from the <a href="https://www.nzor.org.nz/">New Zealand Organism Register (NZOR)</a> as well as the <a href="https://www.catalogueoflife.org/">Catalogue of Life (CoL)</a>. Previously, these have been merged together automatically.<br>Our 2024 backbone refresh made big changes to remove duplication of species listings and improve accuracy and navigation when searching for new species or threatened species records in the ALA.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-are-the-2025-changes">What are the 2025 changes?</h3>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-1024x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-51113" style="width:328px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-768x768.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-1536x1536.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1-1920x1920.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Cape-York-Graceful-Tree-Frog-Ranoidea-bella-Photo-Credit-Mark-Simpson-CC-BY-NC-1.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cape York Graceful Treefrog (<em>Chlorohyla bella</em>). Photo: Mark Simpson, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>We’ve made some big, but less visible changes. The most obvious change is that we’ve updated the taxonomy to include all species described, as at June 2025. We have also simplified the Tree of Life (like a family tree showing how species are related using a structure with classifications such as Kingdom, Phylum, Class etc) to remove high-level duplications that result from us combining different sources.</p>



<p>Now, instead of just merging sources together we “add” species that are not in the NSL. It’s a more targeted and curated approach. This is particularly important for New Zealand plants and fungi.</p>



<p>Another big change is that we’ve added the <a href="https://algae.biodiversity.org.au/nsl/services/search/names?publication=Kuetzing%2C+F.T.+%281865%29%2C+Tabulae+Phycologicae&amp;search=true&amp;advanced=true&amp;display=apni">Australian Algal Names Index</a>, adding around 11,000 species. We’ve previously relied on an international source for algal names and that did not load properly last time. We’ve also changed fungi, bryophytes and protista so that we are only taking names from NZOR and NSL.</p>



<p>We’ve also removed a lot of species that were “international” particularly in groups like Protists. In the short term this will mean that some groups, such as slime moulds – where we were reliant on international sources – will only be represented at a higher level in the ALA until we can develop a better solution.</p>



<p>A number of quite major taxonomic changes have recently been published, since June 2025. Where we haven’t been able to include these (too late in the process and too big a change to the NSL), we’ve referenced these newly described species or new genera back to the names as recorded in the NSL. For example, all the new genera in the tree frogs are referenced back to <em>Litoria</em> (the previous genus that contained all Australian tree frogs).</p>



<p>While birds have millions of records, many species in the ALA have few or no records, so it is essential to get as many records matching as possible. The 2025 changes add around 59,000 records to 2,549 species that previously had fewer than 100 records each.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" width="1000" height="667" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Blotch-tailed-earless-dragon_Travis-W-Reeder.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-51112" style="aspect-ratio:1.499285782306447;width:439px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Blotch-tailed-earless-dragon_Travis-W-Reeder.jpg 1000w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Blotch-tailed-earless-dragon_Travis-W-Reeder-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Blotch-tailed-earless-dragon_Travis-W-Reeder-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Pebble Dragon (<em>Tympanocryptis cephalus</em>). Photo: Travis W. Reeder, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-still-remains-to-be-done">What still remains to be done?</h3>



<p>A big issue we still need to deal with is where a species is split into multiple species. For example, the pebble dragon (<em>Tympanocryptis cephalus</em>) had a number of new species described within it, including <em>Tympanocryptis gigas</em> and <em>T. diabolicus</em>.</p>



<p>The problem is that, as with most aggregated databases such as the state and territory government atlases, records are placed based on the species names used in the data or what the species was named at the time it was recorded.</p>



<p>So if a record with a scientific name of <em>T. cephalus</em> comes in that is actually <em>T. gigas</em>, there is no way to place this correctly as <em>T. gigas</em> (currently).</p>



<p>We’ll initially be looking at a way of flagging species with users so that you will know to look at more than one species to get the full picture. Down the track, we hope to place these records but flag them so our users know they have been placed automatically.</p>



<p>The other big challenge is to develop a better approach to names-matching. When data comes into the ALA, the species names in the data are matched automatically to the most correct place. This system is not perfect. This is not just the programming in the ALA; species names themselves cause problems. For example, there are over 5,000 homonyms in the ALA (identical species names for unrelated species). We hope to improve names-matching over the next 12 months.</p>



<p>All changes to the ALA taxonomic backbone have been actioned in consultation with the <a href="https://www.dcceew.gov.au/science-research/abrs">Australian Biological Resources Study</a> and the <a href="https://www.anbg.gov.au/cpbr/program/hc/hc-APC.html">Australian Plant Census.</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New projects will fill gaps in Australia&#8217;s national biodiversity data system</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-projects-will-fill-gaps-in-australias-national-biodiversity-data-system/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 22:16:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=51042</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Six new biodiversity data mobilisation projects will contribute approximately 85,000 new records to the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) under our Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program 2025.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="802" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-1024x802.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-51049" style="width:404px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-1024x802.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-300x235.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-768x601.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-1536x1203.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-2048x1603.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Biosecurity-Tasmania_Tephritidae-fruit-flies-pinned-in-the-Tasmanian-Agricultural-Insect-Collection-1920x1503.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Biosecurity Tasmania ran a previous ABDMP project to mobilise more than 73,000 invertebrate specimen records from the Tasmanian Agricultural Insect Collection. Photo: Melissa Houghton, Biosecurity Tasmania.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>The program helps data holders share species data that otherwise couldn’t be made available on the ALA, making them accessible for research and decision-making globally.</p>



<p>More complete data makes it easier to understand where species are for conservation assessment, how populations are changing, and how ecosystems are responding to external influences.</p>



<p>Species covered include amphibians, <a href="https://www.anbg.gov.au/bryophyte/what-is-bryophyte.html">bryophytes</a> (the collective term for mosses, hornworts and liverworts), fish, insects, mammals, moths, plants, reptiles and sharks. They come from collections across New South Wales, Western Australia, Tasmania and the Northern Territory.</p>



<p>Juliet Seers, ALA program lead, said that unlocking these new records will help give a more comprehensive picture of Australia’s environment.</p>



<p>“This is about filling in the gaps in our national biodiversity data system through the ALA, which can be taxonomic, geographic, or temporal,” Juliet said.</p>



<p>“In just four years, the program has brought almost a million new records into the ALA.</p>



<p>“These records will create a more representative database for biodiversity research and decision-making.</p>



<p>“And new records will include specimens from really out-of-the-way places such as Australia’s Antarctic territories and remote parts of arid central Australia.”</p>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-9d6595d7 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow" style="flex-basis:100%">
<p>The six successful projects are:</p>



<ol class="wp-block-list">
<li>Digitising the Curtin University Herbarium (Western Australian Herbarium)</li>



<li>Digitising the Downing Herbarium (Macquarie University)</li>



<li>Mobilising Northern Australian Fish and Terrestrial Vertebrate Tissues (Museum and Art Gallery of the Northern Territory)</li>



<li>Digitising and mobilising the Botany Collection (Queen Victoria Museum and Art Gallery)</li>



<li>Addressing knowledge gaps in Tasmanian insects (Tasmanian Museum &amp; Art Gallery (TMAG)</li>



<li>Mobilising Agrotis moth genus data (Western Sydney University)</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="900" height="600" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Perentie_Varanus-giganteus_John-Sullivan.jpg" alt="a large speckled lizard on a rock" class="wp-image-51050" style="aspect-ratio:1.5000364511190494;width:447px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Perentie_Varanus-giganteus_John-Sullivan.jpg 900w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Perentie_Varanus-giganteus_John-Sullivan-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Perentie_Varanus-giganteus_John-Sullivan-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Perentie (<em>Varanus giganteus</em>) Photo: John Sullivan, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-will-the-funds-be-used-for-and-what-processes-will-the-records-undergo">What will the funds be used for and what processes will the records undergo?</h4>



<p>The projects aim to support data validation and digitisation activities. This may include photographing specimens, transcribing information from specimen labels, verifying names and taxonomy, applying standardised geographic coordinates, and providing metadata where available.</p>



<p>Metadata includes institutional and principal research contacts and any licensing or usage conditions.</p>



<p>As the data becomes available through the ALA, it is also published globally through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility, supporting international science and policy.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-are-the-benefits-from-training-and-capacity-building">What are the benefits from training and capacity building?</h4>



<p>These projects will also provide learning and development opportunities for staff, students, and volunteers. Training may include biological collection management and digitisation, understanding biodiversity data standards, taxonomy, and approaches to generating high-quality digital data.</p>



<p>Through this initial funding under the Biodiversity Data Mobilisation program, it is anticipated that institutions will build the capacity to continue delivering data to the ALA.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="successful-2025-projects"><strong>Successful 2025 Projects</strong></h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="digitising-the-curtin-university-herbarium-western-australian-herbarium-department-of-biodiversity-conservation-and-attractions">Digitising the Curtin University Herbarium (Western Australian Herbarium, Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions)</h3>



<p>• The Curtin University Herbarium, now housed at the Western Australian Herbarium, was established in the 1970s and includes plant specimens from long-term monitoring plots in the Pilbara, Murchison, and mining tenements and revegetation sites. Several ‘type’ specimens are also hidden within the collections.<br>• Several university student interns will assist with the imaging, databasing and processing of the mounted and labelled orphaned collection.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“This project will accelerate databasing and data sharing of this unique collection, including the digitisation of ecological voucher collections not found in any other herbarium,” Collections Manager, Shelley James.</p>
</blockquote>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="766" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Combed-plaitmoss_John-Walter.jpeg" alt="close up of moss " class="wp-image-51054" style="width:397px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Combed-plaitmoss_John-Walter.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Combed-plaitmoss_John-Walter-300x224.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Combed-plaitmoss_John-Walter-768x575.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Combed-plaitmoss_John-Walter-640x480.jpeg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Combed Plait-moss (<em>Hypnum cupressiforme var. filiforme</em>). Photo: John Walter, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="digitising-the-downing-herbarium-macquarie-university">Digitising the Downing Herbarium (Macquarie University)</h3>



<p>• The Downing herbarium houses a unique collection of mosses, hornworts and liverworts (bryophytes) and vascular plants primarily curated by Alison Downing and Karen Marais at Macquarie University.<br>• It includes specimens from remote locations such as Macquarie and Heard islands, Antarctic territories and the seldom visited Kerguelen Islands.<br>• Bryophytes are well known as important indicators of environmental conditions, climate change and pollution but are often overlooked in sampling efforts.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“The majority of samples have a detailed verbal location description but lack the geographic coordinate data essential for the incorporation into the mapping of species distributions and other spatial analysis. This project will transcribe digital coordinates from the verbal descriptions and field notes for these specimens as well as adding photographs of each voucher, mobilising the occurrence records for the users of the ALA using best practice techniques,” Project lead, Julian Schrader.</p>
</blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="mobilising-northern-australian-fishes-and-terrestrial-vertebrate-tissues-museum-and-art-gallery-of-the-northern-territory">Mobilising Northern Australian Fishes and Terrestrial Vertebrate Tissues (Museum and Art Gallery of the Northern Territory)</h3>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="768" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Green-sawfish_Vicki.jpg" alt="a sawfish from above, showing the great length of its snout (rostrum)" class="wp-image-51057" style="aspect-ratio:0.7500142914308581;width:347px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Green-sawfish_Vicki.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Green-sawfish_Vicki-225x300.jpg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Green Sawfish (<em>Pristis zijsron</em>) Photo credit: Vicki, CC BY-NC.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>• Tissue samples, as genetic resources, are rapidly becoming one of the most sought-after specimen and data types globally. Currently the tissue collection is digitally dark and inaccessible via public platforms to interested researchers.<br>• The archival tissues focus on Top End macrotidal reef and estuary habitats, which are generally not well represented in collections. The collection also covers inland freshwater habitats, which are a current gap in ALA records.<br>• The terrestrial vertebrate tissues primarily cover reptiles and amphibians, and include threatened and critically endangered monitors (Varanus spp.).</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“Mobilising tissues to assist with important research that will underpin conservation efforts for freshwater fishes is a timely task. An estimated three quarters of Australia’s freshwater fish are found nowhere else on earth. More than a third of these species are at risk of extinction. It will also help to underpin collections-based research important to documenting biodiversity” Project lead, Kirsti Abbott.</p>
</blockquote>



<div class="wp-block-columns is-layout-flex wp-container-core-columns-is-layout-9d6595d7 wp-block-columns-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-column is-layout-flow wp-block-column-is-layout-flow"></div>
</div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="digitising-and-mobilising-the-botany-collection-queen-victoria-museum-and-art-gallery">Digitising and mobilising the Botany Collection (Queen Victoria Museum and Art Gallery)</h3>



<p>• This project will improve the representation of Tasmanian flora, particularly from the north and inland regions. Some of these areas are underrepresented in the ALA and of ecological importance due to their unique and endemic plant communities.<br>• The collection includes specimens from the late 1800s and early 1900s, offering historical insights into plant distributions and environments from periods that are currently poorly represented in the national dataset.<br>• These data are vital for understanding long-term ecological changes, identifying shifting baselines, and predicting future trends in biodiversity under climate pressure.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“High-quality images and data made accessible through ALA will facilitate remote identification and review by experts. This is currently our experience with the arthropod data we have shared with the ALA where researchers constantly get in contact with us to study specimens collected a long time ago in this region. This project will help ensure that these important and historical specimens can contribute to research in conservation, climate change, species distribution, and ecological restoration,” Project lead, Alfonsina Arriaga-Jiménez.</p>
</blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="addressing-knowledge-gaps-in-tasmanian-insects-tasmanian-museum-art-gallery-tmag">Addressing knowledge gaps in Tasmanian insects (Tasmanian Museum &amp; Art Gallery (TMAG)</h3>



<p>• Tasmanian biodiversity is world-renowned for its uniqueness, with high levels of endemism, both at species-level and higher. Among the insects proposed for digitisation are threatened species, including several butterfly species and subspecies endemic to Tasmania.<br>• This project will fast-track the digitisation of Tasmanian insect specimens covering Coleoptera (beetles), Hymenoptera (wasps) and Lepidoptera (moths).<br>• Expanding the coverage of invertebrates on the ALA is important in rectifying the current bias towards using vertebrates and plants in fields of study as diverse as biogeography, ecology, climate change impacts and conservation science, as well as in environmental impact assessment.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p></p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“TMAG’s Tasmanian invertebrate collections are a potential information goldmine regarding the status and distribution of Tasmania’s unique fauna, both past and present. Some of the taxa concerned have no databased specimens, either from TMAG or from any other institution contributing to the ALA. In an increasingly online world, it is almost as though they don’t exist at all,” Project lead, Dr Simon Grove.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="769" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Bogong-moth_Paul-George.jpg" alt="a bogong moth on a plant" class="wp-image-51060" style="aspect-ratio:1.3316133327784945;width:424px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Bogong-moth_Paul-George.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Bogong-moth_Paul-George-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Bogong-moth_Paul-George-768x577.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/12/Bogong-moth_Paul-George-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Bogong Moth (Agrotis infusa) Photo: Paul George, CC BY-NC-SA)</figcaption></figure>
</div></blockquote>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="mobilising-agrotis-moth-genus-data-western-sydney-university">Mobilising Agrotis moth genus data (Western Sydney University)</h3>



<p>• This project will mobilise museum records of Agrotis moths from across Australia to provide future research opportunities in both conservation and agriculture.<br>• This genus includes the Bogong moth (Agrotis infusa), which is culturally important to First Nations Peoples and an endangered keystone alpine species.<br>• As larvae, many Agrotis species are crop pests known as cutworms. This conflict between a need for conservation and pest control makes land management of the breeding grounds of this genus challenging.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote is-layout-flow wp-block-quote-is-layout-flow">
<p>“Building a national baseline dataset of Agrotis distribution over time is important to conservation, culture and agriculture because it will allow a better understanding of how this complex genus could be managed, for example, where targeted pest management should be applied or where conservation schemes could be implemented,” Project lead, Eleanor Drinkwater.</p>
</blockquote>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; December 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-december-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 22:15:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=51044</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Australia Partners Globally to Unlock Biodiversity Data]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="719" height="938" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48109" style="aspect-ratio:0.7665359853253246;width:256px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger-230x300.png 230w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 719px) 100vw, 719px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>Welcome to the December 2025 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>In October, I had the privilege of representing Australia at a major international biodiversity meeting in Bogotá, Colombia. The Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) brings together countries from around the world to share and connect data that helps us understand and protect nature. The discussions this year focused on how we can keep this global network strong and sustainable, while embracing new technologies like environmental DNA and advanced data standards. These innovations will make biodiversity information richer and more useful for conservation, science, and policy worldwide. Shortly after this meeting I participated in the international <a href="https://www.livingdata2025.com/">Living Data Conference</a>, which provided an opportunity to engage more broadly with the international biodiversity data and infrastructure community.</p>



<p>Through the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), we play a leading role in this global effort. Our participation ensures Australian biodiversity data contributes to international programs—and that we benefit from data collected elsewhere, which is vital for research and biosecurity. We also explored opportunities to strengthen partnerships across Oceania, support Indigenous data governance, and collaborate on cutting-edge tools that will shape the future of biodiversity science. By staying connected and sharing knowledge, Australia helps drive global solutions for nature while delivering real benefits at home.</p>



<p>The conversations in Bogotá highlighted that biodiversity data is more than just numbers—it’s the foundation for tackling global challenges like climate change and species loss. Australia has a chance to lead by example, not only through our technical expertise but also by fostering collaboration across the region. Continued engagement will help ensure that our scientists, policymakers, and communities have the best possible information to protect and enhance biodiversity for future generations.</p>



<p>I’d like to acknowledge the work of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (<a href="https://www.gbif.org/">GBIF</a>), the <a href="https://www.humboldt.org.co/">Colombian</a> hosts of Living Data, and our partners from the Group on Earth Observations Biodiversity Observation Network (<a href="https://geobon.org/">GEOBON</a>), Biodiversity Information Standards (<a href="https://www.tdwg.org/">TDWG</a>) and the Ocean Biodiversity Information System (<a href="https://obis.org/">OBIS</a>) who made the events in Bogota so successful.</p>



<p>Thank you to all our partners, users and stakeholders and I wish everyone an enjoyable summer break and festive season.</p>



<p><strong>Andre Zerger<br>ALA Director</strong></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: How biosecurity data are protecting Australia&#8217;s ecosystems</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-how-biosecurity-data-are-protecting-australias-ecosystems/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=51012</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Discover how biosecurity data are transforming the fight against invasive species in Australia. Join this webinar, hosted by the Atlas of Living Australia, to explore cutting-edge tools and strategies that are keeping our environment one step ahead. This event was hosted on 18 Nov 2025 at 12pm AEDT. Presenters David MitchellResearch officer, Australian Bureau of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Discover how biosecurity data are transforming the fight against invasive species in Australia. Join this webinar, hosted by the Atlas of Living Australia, to explore cutting-edge tools and strategies that are keeping our environment one step ahead.</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar: How biosecurity data are protecting Australia&#039;s ecosystems" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/sn6Hd0JKE68?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This event was hosted on 18 Nov 2025 at 12pm AEDT.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="presenters">Presenters</h3>



<p><strong>David Mitchell</strong><br>Research officer, Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics and Sciences</p>



<p>David works at the Australian Bureau of Agricultural and Resource Economics and Sciences (ABARES), on the National Vertebrate Pests and Weeds Distribution Project which collates and analyses data on priority invasive species. Prior to ABARES, David did his PhD and a postdoc behavioural ecology and evolution using guppies as a model species.</p>



<p><strong>Steve Csurhes</strong><br>Principal Biosecurity Officer, Invasive Plants and Animals Program, Biosecurity Qld</p>



<p>Steve has worked in the field of invasive species management for 38 years, including roles in policy, legislation, research, and operational response. His main interest lies in preventative pest management, which includes pre-emptive regulations on sale and possession of high-risk pests, surveillance and early detection and eradication response.</p>



<p><strong>Jens Froese</strong><br>Senior Research Scientist, Environmental Biosecurity Group, Health and Biosecurity, CSIRO</p>



<p>Jens is a Senior Research Scientist at CSIRO with research expertise in biosecurity and biological invasions, data integration, spatial analysis, risk modelling, and structured expert elicitation. He specialises in developing methods, workflows and tools to enable adaptive management of invasive species and other biothreats for improved on ground and policy outcomes.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="facilitator">Facilitator</h3>



<p><strong>Dr Andrew Turley</strong><br>Team Lead, Applications and Biosecurity, Atlas of Living Australia</p>



<p>Andrew is the Team Lead &#8211; Applications and Biosecurity at the Atlas of Living Australia. His diverse career has included management of scientific and public sector programs with the National Fire Ant Eradication Program, the World Mosquito Program and the Queensland Museum. Andrew holds a PhD in Medical Entomology from the University of Queensland and is an active member of the Entomological Society of Queensland.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="links">Links</h3>



<ul class="wp-block-list">
<li>During this webinar, the following dataset was discussed: <a href="https://www.agriculture.gov.au/abares/research-topics/invasive-species/national-feral-pig-current-distribution-australia" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Feral Pig Current Distribution in Australia</a> (ABARES)</li>
</ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>galaxias: tiny-fish inspired tool for huge sea of research data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/galaxias-tiny-fish-inspired-tool-for-huge-sea-of-research-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 21:56:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50956</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Our coding tool {galaxias} makes it easier for researchers to share their biodiversity data for greater open science impact.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="505" height="500" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/galaxias-team-photo_medium.png" alt="" class="wp-image-50968" style="width:411px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/galaxias-team-photo_medium.png 505w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/galaxias-team-photo_medium-300x297.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/galaxias-team-photo_medium-150x150.png 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 505px) 100vw, 505px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The ALA&#8217;s Science and Decision Support Team developed galaxias (clockwise from top right) Dax Kellie, Amanda Buyan,
Shandiya Balasubramaniam and Martin Westgate.</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>A fishy new software package will help researchers share data more easily with the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA).</p>



<p><a href="https://galaxias.ala.org.au/">{galaxias}, a new R and Python package</a>, makes it easier than ever for researchers to bundle data and metadata for sharing.</p>



<p>Martin Westgate, ALA Science &amp; Decision Support Team Lead, says a huge amount of biodiversity data is generated by long-term ecological research run out of universities.</p>



<p>“This data is very rich, so it has a lot of structure to tell us how things are changing over time, and it&#8217;s expertly derived,” Martin said.</p>



<p>“People are storing this data, publishing it and sometimes providing it to state governments as part of their permit requirements.</p>



<p>“But it&#8217;s not making its way into public data fora, so we felt that the story of biodiversity data in Australia wasn&#8217;t as complete as it might be.”</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="going-with-the-flow-swimming-with-research-workflows">Going with the flow: swimming with research workflows</h2>



<p>Dax Kellie, ALA’s Science Program Lead and a co-author of galaxias, says the team designed galaxias with a research workflow in mind.</p>



<p>It’s targeted at researchers with data that they&#8217;ve collected and worked with that they might want to share.</p>



<p>galaxias uses code many researchers already know and use for preparing, analysing and visualising their data. The idea is to empower researchers to manage their own data as the experts in their data.</p>



<p>“It gives researchers the agency to standardise their data themselves,” Dax said.</p>



<p>“So it makes data sharing simple and fast, and it does it in a language that most researchers are familiar with.”</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="when-you-fish-upon-a-star-formatting-data-for-sharing">When you fish upon a star: formatting data for sharing</h2>



<p>galaxias simplifies the process of converting biodiversity data into the <a href="https://dwc.tdwg.org/">Darwin Core Archives (DwCA) format</a>. This format enables sharing of biodiversity data by standardising identifying features, taxonomic classification and data definitions.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="844" height="512" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Spotted-Galaxias_Zacky-N_cropped.jpeg" alt="A small spotted galaxias fish in a clear plastic box" class="wp-image-50963" style="width:374px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Spotted-Galaxias_Zacky-N_cropped.jpeg 844w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Spotted-Galaxias_Zacky-N_cropped-300x182.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Spotted-Galaxias_Zacky-N_cropped-768x466.jpeg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 844px) 100vw, 844px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The <a href="https://biocache.ala.org.au/occurrences/cf102dd4-54dd-4f2d-a438-21ab5931a009">Spotted Galaxias</a> (<em><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/e4d85845-3e34-4112-90a9-f954176721ec">Galaxias truttaceus</a></em>) is found across southern Victoria, Tasmania, and south-west Western Australia. Credit: Zacky, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>“I guess the challenge or the technical problem that galaxias solves is that no one knows what our data format is,” Martin said.</p>



<p>“People will be collecting data of the same type &#8211; I saw this species on this day in this place &#8211; but using their own data structures, their own databases and their own mechanisms.”</p>



<p>galaxias makes it easy for users to convert their data to a universal standard, including ways to:<br>• standardise observational data<br>• write metadata<br>• validate minimum requirements for data sharing<br>• publish data and metadata.</p>



<p></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-left" class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-left" id="some-fin-to-celebrate">Some-fin to celebrate</h2>



<p>The name “<a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https%3A/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/cf9d20e7-5234-4ff3-94a2-23802357365f">galaxias</a>” comes from a genus of small native fish found in rivers, lakes and streams <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https%3A/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/cf9d20e7-5234-4ff3-94a2-23802357365f">across most of Australia</a>.</p>



<p>They’re small and rarely seen, and two-thirds of Australia’s Galaxias species are <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/607ec6ae-18b6-43e8-9e02-23f946aabdf7">vulnerable </a>or <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/e34d1659-1a1b-4d85-842e-3665edf32938">endangered</a>, so they could do with some publicity!</p>



<p>“galaxias is the partner package to <a href="https://galah.ala.org.au/">galah</a>—galaxias gets data in, galah gets data out. So there&#8217;s a real circle there in where galaxias fits into the ALA universe,” Dax says.</p>



<p>“And, like ‘galah’, ‘galaxias’ is the name of an Australian native animal containing our acronym ‘ALA’.”</p>



<p>Galaxias are important members of their freshwater ecosystems and great indicators of ecosystem health, but many are quite delicate and easy to overlook.</p>



<p>Similarly, the ALA’s new galaxias software package aims to play an important role in the open research data ecosystem.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="to-in-fin-ity-and-beyond">To in-fin-ity and beyond</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Mountain-Galaxias_Tse-Chung-Yi_resize.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50966" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Mountain-Galaxias_Tse-Chung-Yi_resize.jpg 400w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/10/Mountain-Galaxias_Tse-Chung-Yi_resize-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">The <a href="https://biocache.ala.org.au/occurrences/e4853e60-e08d-4ed3-b042-f4d121a39fee">Mountain Galaxias</a> (<em><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/3ca3dab8-586f-47ed-9589-7e7679762fea">Galaxias olidus</a></em>) is found on both sides of the Great Dividing Range from southern Queensland, south-eastern New South Wales, across Victoria and further west to South Australia. Credit: Tse Chung Yi, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<p>Sharing this stream of research data makes for a richer data ecosystem for biodiversity information in Australia.</p>



<p>“Sharing data means that researchers get to influence policy and get to influence the conservation of the species they’re working on&#8211;because suddenly that information is available more widely to environmental consultants,” Martin says.</p>



<p>“And the data will be available for other researchers, so they may generate insights that hadn’t been considered.”</p>



<p>Sharing data also provides the opportunity for greater insight because data from many different sources can be used to give a more comprehensive picture on the environment.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="feedback-welcome">Feedback welcome</h2>



<p>Our ultimate goal is to make the process of preparing data in Darwin Core simple and stress-free, encouraging more people to share data. If you choose to try galaxias, we’d appreciate any feedback about your experience so we can make Galaxias better!</p>



<p>Feedback can be sent to support@ala.org.au or reported as an issue on the<a href="https://github.com/AtlasOfLivingAustralia/galaxias/issues"> R package GitHub page </a>or <a href="https://github.com/AtlasOfLivingAustralia/galaxias-python/issues">Python package GitHub page</a>.</p>



<p>”This is early days and we don&#8217;t know exactly what the best package will be,” Dax said.</p>



<p>“We&#8217;re very flexible at this stage and happy to amend or adjust, which we&#8217;ve done before with galah.</p>



<p>“There’s a lot of potential here if this works to implement it more as a point and click interface too. So the more people who use it, the better; and we can build it together.”</p>



<p>See the <a href="https://galaxias.ala.org.au/R/articles/quick_start_guide.html">quick start guide in R</a> or the <a href="https://galaxias.ala.org.au/Python/getting_started/Quick_Start_Guide.html">quick start guide in Python</a> or our <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kO4-1KIxBro">short intro video</a> for more information.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Saving Swan Galaxias - one of Tasmania&#039;s rarest freshwater fish" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yn_plEofOGY?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter September 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-september-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 02:19:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50855</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA September 2025 newsletter is out now – featuring the latest project updates, research insights, upcoming events, and more!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Discover the ALA&#8217;s <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/sep-2025-newsletter" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">September 2025 newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/sep-2025-newsletter" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="660" height="862" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/newsletter-tile-sep2025.png" alt="top section of the September 2025 ALA newsletter with banner " class="wp-image-50858" style="width:459px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/newsletter-tile-sep2025.png 660w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/newsletter-tile-sep2025-230x300.png 230w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 660px) 100vw, 660px" /></a></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>From snapshot to supercharged science data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/from-snapshot-to-supercharged-science-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 06:16:27 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A new dataset sees verified images from wildlife camera traps available in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) through the Wildlife Observatory of Australia (WildObs).]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>A new dataset sees verified images from wildlife camera traps available in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA).</p>



<p>But it wasn’t just a case of point and shoot to incorporate this new data into the ALA.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://wildobs.org.au/">Wildlife Observatory of Australia</a> (WildObs) is a national initiative transforming how Australia collects, processes, and shares <a href="https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dp5214">data from wildlife camera traps</a>. WildObs is a partnership led by the <a href="https://www.qcif.edu.au/">Queensland Cyber Infrastructure Foundation</a> (QCIF) and supported by our NCRIS colleagues the <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">Terrestrial Ecosystem Monitoring Network</a> (TERN) and the <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/project/the-wildlife-observatory-of-australia-wildobs/">Australian Research Data Commons</a> (ARDC).</p>



<p>For our part, the ALA developed a new process for ingesting data in <a href="https://camtrap-dp.tdwg.org/">Camera Trap Data Package</a> (CamtrapDP), a new standard that allows richer data capture specifying deployments, observations and media. It’s been developed by the <a href="https://www.tdwg.org/">Biodiversity Information Standards organisation (TDWG)</a> and adopted by the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> (GBIF). The ALA transforms Camtrap data into <a href="https://dwc.tdwg.org/">Darwin Core </a>events and occurrences.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_brush-turkey_day_CLOSE-UP_resize-1024x576.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50819" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_brush-turkey_day_CLOSE-UP_resize-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_brush-turkey_day_CLOSE-UP_resize-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_brush-turkey_day_CLOSE-UP_resize-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_brush-turkey_day_CLOSE-UP_resize.jpg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Australian Brush Turkey (<em>Alectura lathami</em>). Identified by Zachary Amir, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>WildObs works across many research projects to curate verified camera trap datasets, and we’ve collaborated with them to mobilise data using CamtrapDP. This then allows the ALA to provide the infrastructure behind the <a href="https://collections.ala.org.au/public/show/dp5214">WildObs Tagged Image Repository</a> and makes the camera trap data <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/resource-hub/making-data-fair/">findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable</a> (FAIR).</p>



<p>The ALA’s normal data processing pipeline prepares the data for indexing and mapping. We match records to our taxonomic backbone, and standardise dates and times and coordinates. We track globally unique identifiers for the records and datasets, and we apply threatened species statuses and responsibly manage obfuscation and access to sensitive records.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_cassowary_close-up_resize-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50820" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_cassowary_close-up_resize-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_cassowary_close-up_resize-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_cassowary_close-up_resize-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_cassowary_close-up_resize-640x480.jpg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_cassowary_close-up_resize.jpg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em>), Identified by Zachary Amir, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>Peggy Newman is the ALA’s Data Manager.</p>



<p>&#8220;The ALA’s ingestion pipeline is ideal for handling most of the standardisation and data cleaning needed to produce AI-ready datasets, which is often the most time consuming and mind numbing part of building AI/ML models,&#8221; Peggy says.</p>



<p>“In the coming years, we’re expecting to see a huge influx of biodiversity datasets like this where the observations and identifications come about from automation and modelling.</p>



<p>“For the models to get better, they’ll need to be built with and informed by openly shared and verified datasets. When the models are better, they’ll be able to help produce better quality datasets in shorter timeframes.</p>



<p>“We see the ALA’s data pipelines and FAIR practices as supporting researchers to improve this kind of feedback loop in biodiversity monitoring.”</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/camera-trap_Red-legged-Pademelon_day_RESIZE-1024x768.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50822" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/camera-trap_Red-legged-Pademelon_day_RESIZE-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/camera-trap_Red-legged-Pademelon_day_RESIZE-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/camera-trap_Red-legged-Pademelon_day_RESIZE-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/camera-trap_Red-legged-Pademelon_day_RESIZE-640x480.jpg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/camera-trap_Red-legged-Pademelon_day_RESIZE.jpg 1200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Red-legged Pademelon (<em>Thylogale stigmatica</em>). Identified by Zachary Amir, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>The <a href="https://biocache.ala.org.au/occurrences/search?q=data_provider_uid:dp5214#tab_recordImages" data-type="link" data-id="https://biocache.ala.org.au/occurrences/search?q=data_provider_uid:dp5214#tab_recordImages">first dataset recently published in the ALA</a> features wildlife in the Wet Tropics captured and identified by quantitative wildlife ecologist <a href="https://about.uq.edu.au/experts/45824">Zachary Amir from the University of Queensland</a> who is part of the WildObs team, hosted by <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a>. Zach was looking at interactions between native and invasive vertebrates in the rainforests of North Queensland.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>Acknowledgment:</strong><br>WildObs is made possible through a <a href="https://wildobs.org.au/#partners">national collaboration</a> of <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy </a>enabled infrastructure. <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a> provides standardised field protocols and hosts the systematic survey data across Australian ecosystems. The ALA hosts the tagged image dataset and occurrence records for public access and reuse. The <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/">Australian Research Data Commons</a> (ARDC) through the<a href="https://www.qcif.edu.au/"> Queensland Cyber Infrastructure Foundation</a> (QCIF) is building the user-facing platform to support image upload, tagging, model training, and data sharing using advanced AI tools. It&#8217;s part of the <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/planet-research-data-commons/">ARDC&#8217;s Planet Research Data Commons</a>, which provides national-scale data infrastructure for earth and environmental science research and decision making.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="563" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_tree-kangaroo_resize.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50823" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_tree-kangaroo_resize.jpg 1000w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_tree-kangaroo_resize-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Camera-trap_tree-kangaroo_resize-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Lumholtz&#8217;s Tree-kangaroo (<em>Dendrolagus lumholtzi</em>). Identified by Zachary Amir, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; September 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-september-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 06:14:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50833</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the September 2025 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter. We are pleased to announce the release of our new&#160;Five-Year Strategy (2025–2030), which sets a clear direction for the Atlas of Living Australia’s priorities and development over the coming years.&#160; As Australia’s national biodiversity data infrastructure, our vision is to deliver [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="719" height="938" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48109" style="width:251px" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-zerger-230x300.png 230w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 719px) 100vw, 719px" /></figure>
</div>


<p>Welcome to the September 2025 edition of our Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) newsletter.</p>



<p>We are pleased to announce the release of our new&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/publications/ala-strategy-2025-2030/">Five-Year Strategy (2025–2030)</a></strong>, which sets a clear direction for the Atlas of Living Australia’s priorities and development over the coming years.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As Australia’s national biodiversity data infrastructure, our vision is to deliver trusted biodiversity data services to support world-class science and decision-making. The strategy responds to a suite of new drivers, including the growth in novel biodiversity monitoring technologies, opportunities around the management of sensitive data, increased cybersecurity risk, and improving how we incorporate the richness of Indigenous biodiversity knowledge into the ALA.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In parallel, the strategy affirms the ongoing commitment to partner with and deliver benefits to new sectors, including industry and biosecurity, to complement our existing partnerships with our biological collections, government, citizen science and ecosystem science partners. We are also excited to grow our partnerships with other NCRIS capabilities to realise greater national benefit.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Our team are particularly proud of the guiding principles articulated on Page 8 of the strategy that will shape how we operate, akin to environmental, social and governance commitments that form a key part of corporate governance in 2025.  </p>



<p>We are grateful to our team, advisory board and stakeholders who have helped shape our strategy and look forward to working with you to deliver on our vision of delivering trusted biodiversity data services for Australia.</p>



<p><strong>Andre Zerger ALA Director</strong></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>We&#8217;re frond of plants &#8211; ALA at the Australasian Plant Pathology Association conference 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/were-frond-of-plants-ala-at-the-australasian-plant-pathology-association-conference-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ian Dewar]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2025 06:14:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50791</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Plants are the third biggest type of occurrence record in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), with over 24 million occurrence records. And scientific collections have a big role to play in helping to tackle plant diseases. We recently participated in the Australasian Plant Pathology Society conference: From Field to Future, Scientific Collections and Plant [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Plants are the third biggest type of occurrence record in the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), with over 24 million occurrence records. And scientific collections have a big role to play in helping to tackle plant diseases.</p>



<p>We recently participated in the <a href="https://www.appsnet.org/">Australasian Plant Pathology Society</a> conference: From Field to Future, Scientific Collections and Plant Pathology.</p>



<p>As part of this, we offered bursaries to support university students and early career researchers to attend the conference. We spoke with three of them to find out their perspectives on the future of plant disease science and the role of online platforms like the ALA.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="966" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-1024x966.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50792" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-1024x966.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-300x283.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-768x724.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-1536x1449.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-2048x1932.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/APPP-bursaries-image_cropped-1920x1811.jpg 1920w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>ALA bursary recipients with ALA biosecurity lead Erin Roger at the Australasian Plant Pathology Society conference 2025. Pictured left to right: Vivian Rincon-Florez, Jonathan Haworth, Erin Roger, Haixa Guan and Alyssa Martino.</em></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="haixia-guan-phd-candidate-the-university-of-sydney">Haixia Guan, PhD candidate, The University of Sydney</h2>



<p>Haixia is interested in the evolutionary ’arms race’ between plants and pathogens, and how genome-scale data can be used to better understand disease dynamics. In her PhD she explored the evolution and virulence variation of crown rust pathogens of Australia using comparative genomics and population-level variation analysis.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="did-you-already-know-about-the-atlas-of-living-australia">Did you already know about the Atlas of Living Australia?</h4>



<p>I was aware of the ALA but hadn’t used it widely. Attending APPS 2025 gave me the opportunity to further understand the scope and potential of the ALA, especially in terms of integrating species distribution data with environmental and genomic data.</p>



<p>I realised that the ALA could be a valuable tool for planning field sampling strategies and for relating pathogen occurrence to environmental variables.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="375" height="342" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Crown-Rust-Puccinia-coronata_Trisha_S_CC-BY-NC_CROPPED.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50807" style="width:360px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Crown-Rust-Puccinia-coronata_Trisha_S_CC-BY-NC_CROPPED.jpg 375w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Crown-Rust-Puccinia-coronata_Trisha_S_CC-BY-NC_CROPPED-300x274.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 375px) 100vw, 375px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Crown Rust (<em>Puccinia coronata</em>). Credit: trisha_s, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-did-you-most-enjoy-learning-more-about-at-the-conference">What did you most enjoy learning more about at the conference?</h4>



<p>I enjoyed most the diversity of research topics and the opportunity to interact with researchers working in different areas of plant pathology &#8211; and understanding species diversity and evolution from a genomic perspective.</p>



<p>An unexpected but inspiring moment was learning how open data platforms and other bioinformatics resources are being used to maintain biological diversity and systematically monitor plant pathogens.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="where-do-you-see-yourself-working-studying-in-plant-pathology-in-the-future-and-what-do-you-see-as-the-role-of-online-data-platforms-like-the-atlas-of-living-australia">Where do you see yourself working/studying in plant pathology in the future? And what do you see as the role of online data platforms like the Atlas of Living Australia?</h4>



<p>In the future, I hope to continue working in fungal pathogen genomics, ideally combining computational biology and field-based studies to address key questions about disease surveillance and management.</p>



<p>Online data platforms like the ALA play a crucial role in this context. They offer an incredible foundation for integrative analyses—linking species distribution, environmental data, and temporal changes. For researchers, platforms like ALA democratise access to biodiversity data and support more informed, large-scale plant epidemiology studies.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="arundhati-singh-phd-candidate-curtin-university">Arundhati Singh, PhD Candidate, Curtin University</h2>



<p>Arundhati is interested in fungicide research. In her PhD, she’s specifically investigating the spatial and temporal dynamics of fungicide distribution within plants and how these influence disease control and the development of resistance.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="did-you-already-know-about-the-atlas-of-living-australia">Did you already know about the Atlas of Living Australia?</h4>



<p>Yes, I’m familiar with the ALA. While I haven’t contributed occurrence records yet, I’ve used the platform to review species distributions and understand local biodiversity for understanding the background of my experiments.</p>



<p>As my current work focuses on fungicide distribution and its role in disease management, tools like the ALA offer an excellent opportunity to connect biological datasets with plant pathology research. I’m looking forward to exploring it further as my research expands into more field-based components.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="2048" height="1536" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-50810" style="width:317px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC-1920x1440.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Fork-leaved-Sundew-Drosera-binata-Photo-Credit-Thilo-Krueger-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpeg 640w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Fork-leaved Sundew (<em>Drosera binata</em>). Credit: Thilo Krueger, CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-did-you-most-enjoy-learning-more-about-at-the-conference">What did you most enjoy learning more about at the conference?</h4>



<p>I thoroughly enjoyed the sessions on integrated disease management and pathogen evolution. It was especially inspiring to see how molecular techniques are being integrated with field-based approaches to develop more sustainable plant disease control strategies.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="where-do-you-see-yourself-working-studying-in-plant-pathology-in-the-future-and-what-do-you-see-as-the-role-of-online-data-platforms-like-the-atlas-of-living-australia">Where do you see yourself working/studying in plant pathology in the future? And what do you see as the role of online data platforms like the Atlas of Living Australia?</h4>



<p>I hope to continue in academia, focusing on research that bridges fundamental laboratory science with applied, field-based strategies to develop targeted and sustainable plant protection methods.</p>



<p>I see platforms like the ALA playing an increasingly vital role in this work; offering accessible, reliable biodiversity data that can inform disease risk assessments, support research planning, and enhance biosecurity efforts.</p>



<p>I also believe integrating such platforms into both research and teaching will be critical in training the next generation of plant pathologists.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="alyssa-martino-scientific-officer-biodiversity-research-research-centre-for-ecosystem-resilience">Alyssa Martino, Scientific Officer Biodiversity Research, Research Centre for Ecosystem Resilience</h2>



<p>Alyssa’s research focuses on forest pathology, in particular host resistance to the fungal pathogen <em>Austropuccinia psidii</em> which causes myrtle rust. This has involved investigating disease resistance genes in Australian native trees, which are highly diverse both within and between species. It’s sparked a broader interest in researching disease resistance gene evolution, and gene diversity across native plant populations.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="did-you-already-know-about-the-atlas-of-living-australia">Did you already know about the Atlas of Living Australia?</h4>



<p>Yes, I am familiar with the platform and have used it both during my PhD and now during my postdoc. During my PhD, I established the<a href="https://inaturalist.ala.org.au/projects/gum-tree-guardians"> Gum Tree Guardians project </a>on iNaturalist as a citizen scientist initiative to increase awareness of myrtle rust in Australia.</p>



<p>I was fortunate to collaborate with Erin Roger and the ALA and Rebecca Paxton from the University of Adelaide on a broader <a href="https://theconversation.com/myrtle-rust-is-lethal-to-australian-plants-could-citizen-scientists-help-track-its-spread-225681">myrtle rust campaign</a> to boost the total myrtle rust observations in ALA.</p>



<p>I also use the ALA platform (especially the spatial portal) in my postdoc role. Based at the Sydney Botanic Gardens within the <a href="https://www.botanicgardens.org.au/our-science/what-we-do/research-centre-ecosystem-resilience">Research Centre for Ecosystem Resilience</a>, I work on the population genetics of threatened plant species across NSW. The <a href="https://spatial.ala.org.au/">spatial portal</a> has been a great tool for planning collections of these species across the state.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1000" height="667" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-edited.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-50805" style="width:332px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-edited.jpeg 1000w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-edited-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-edited-768x512.jpeg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Myrtle Rust (<em>Austropuccinia psidii</em>). Credit: Pete Woodall, CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h4 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-did-you-most-enjoy-learning-more-about-at-the-conference">What did you most enjoy learning more about at the conference?</h4>



<p>The conference was incredibly inspiring! Having recently started my first postdoc, based at the Sydney Botanic Gardens, the conference theme of collections sparked a lot of ideas for future research, especially seeing research using herbarium specimens to uncover the history, evolution, and diversity of plant pathogens.</p>



<p>I was amazed to see the preservation of fungal spores on herbarium specimens, making me think about what may be lurking in the Sydney Botanic Gardens collections.</p>



<p></p>



<p></p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-left" class="wp-block-heading has-text-align-left" id="where-do-you-see-yourself-working-studying-in-plant-pathology-in-the-future-and-what-do-you-see-as-the-role-of-online-data-platforms-like-the-atlas-of-living-australia">Where do you see yourself working/studying in plant pathology in the future? And what do you see as the role of online data platforms like the Atlas of Living Australia?</h4>



<p>Being born and raised in Western Australia, I see myself one day taking the learnings from my time in Sydney back to Perth or Albany. My goal is to bring high-quality plant pathology research down to the south-west biodiversity hotspot in Western Australia, with a focus on investigating disease resistance gene diversity in WA’s endemic plant species.</p>



<p>Platforms like the ALA will assist ahead of fieldwork for collections, and will also enable the collection of data on plants and pathogens during this type of research. It will be incredibly beneficial in a biodiversity hotspot which is threatened by plant pathogens like<em> Phytophthora cinnamomi</em>, which has already had a large impact in that region.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="576" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/ALA-Variable-Bossiaea.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-50796" style="width:235px;height:auto" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/ALA-Variable-Bossiaea.jpg 576w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2025/09/ALA-Variable-Bossiaea-169x300.jpg 169w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 576px) 100vw, 576px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Variable Bossiaea (<em>Bossiaea heterophylla</em>). Credit: Ambrosia1, CC BY-NC</figcaption></figure>
</div>


<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="ala-biosecurity-alerts-and-plant-health">ALA Biosecurity Alerts and plant health</h2>



<p>Our former biosecurity lead <a href="https://ca.linkedin.com/in/erin-roger-9299a067">Dr Erin Roger</a> delivered a conference keynote address on how open data research infrastructure can support data driven biosecurity initiatives.</p>



<p>“Our <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">Biosecurity Alerts Service</a>, based largely on citizen science data, can detect and report invasive species throughout Australia. It can support the plant pathology sector by monitoring the spread of plant pests and diseases, such as myrtle rust,” Erin said.</p>



<p>“We’ve also been improving data quality and taxonomic representation for the benefit of plant pathology. For example, we’ve greatly expanded ALA representation of biosecurity relevant species via our <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">data mobilisation program</a>.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Insights: The hidden world of sensitive species data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-insights-the-hidden-world-of-sensitive-species-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 22:50:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=50691</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) provides reliable biodiversity data for research and conservation, but did you know it also plays a key role in managing sensitive species information? In this session, you&#8217;ll learn how the ALA identifies and protects sensitive species records, and how you can request access to the data and contribute by [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) provides reliable biodiversity data for research and conservation, but did you know it also plays a key role in managing sensitive species information?</p>



<p>In this session, you&#8217;ll learn how the ALA identifies and protects sensitive species records, and how you can request access to the data and contribute by suggesting the addition of species to the sensitive lists.</p>



<p>The ALA receives support from the Australian Government through the <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/ncris">National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy</a> (NCRIS) and is hosted by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.csiro.au/en/">CSIRO</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Insights: The hidden world of sensitive species data" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AVigz0nlQY4?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This event was hosted on 24 July 2025 at 12pm AEST.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id=""></h3>



<p><strong>Tania Laity &#8211; ALA Business and Policy Analyst<br>Cam Slatyer &#8211; ALA National Biodiversity Data Initiatives Project Manager</strong></p>



<p>Tania Laity and Cam Slatyer both have over thirty years of experience working on science and biodiversity issues in government, conservation and the collections sectors. Cam is currently the subject matter lead on taxonomy for the Atlas of Living Australia and Tania is the Business Analyst. They are currently leading an international working group to develop a data standard for handling Restricted Access Species Data.</p>



<p>Previously, they led a diverse group of government and non-government stakeholders that produced the <a href="https://rasd.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Framework for the Sharing of Restricted Access Species Data</a> in Australia, supported by the Australian Research Data Commons, Atlas of Living Australia and CSIRO as part of the Australian Government&#8217;s National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy.</p>



<p></p>



<p>This event was hosted by <strong>Juliet Seers, </strong>the ALA Training and Outreach Coordinator.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
