<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2023 01:19:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Advances in Genomics and Biological Collections</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-advances-in-genomics-and-biological-collections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2023 23:43:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48348</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Collections specimens are valuable resources in genomics as they provide a historical record of the diversity of life on earth. By analysing the DNA and other biological markers from these specimens, researchers can gain important insights into this diversity and inform conservation efforts to protect our species. When these kinds of data are aggregated from [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Collections specimens are valuable resources in genomics as they provide a historical record of the diversity of life on earth. By analysing the DNA and other biological markers from these specimens, researchers can gain important insights into this diversity and inform conservation efforts to protect our species. When these kinds of data are aggregated from multiple sources, researchers can pool their knowledge, compare results, and build on one another&#8217;s work – essential for driving innovation and advancing our understanding of the natural world.</p>



<p>This webinar brings together experts from three projects to discuss their work in this space. It is ideal for researchers, practitioners, and anyone interested in the latest developments in genomics and biological collections, and the mobilisation of these data.</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="ALA webinar: Advances in Genomics and Biological Collections" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YLaBiSQkOlM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEDT, Tuesday 28 March 2023, with 170 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/erin-hahn.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48351"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Erin Hahn | Australian National Wildlife Collection (CSIRO)</h3>



<p>Dr Hahn is a postdoctoral fellow and conservation geneticist at the Australian National Wildlife Collection at CSIRO. She is working to enable whole genome sequencing and characterisation of gene expression from formalin-preserved museum tissues. Her research will deliver new data streams with which to study how species have historically responded to our changing environment. Erin received her PhD from the University of Arizona in Tucson, Arizona, USA. Her doctoral work on endangered Sonoran pronghorn enabled wildlife managers to identify appropriate captive individuals for mating and release and was the first study characterising population epigenetics in an endangered species.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/jessica-fenker.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48352"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Jéssica Fenker | Museums Victoria</h3>



<p>Jess is a Research Fellow at Museums Victoria, working in Jane Melville’s lab on how Quaternary changes affected past and recent reptile communities, using rich fossil data. She is also associated with the Australian National University (ANU), collaborating with the Moritz and Cardillo labs. Jess has previously worked as a data analyst for the ALA and EcoCommons, in relocations for the Australian National Wildlife Collection (CSIRO), and as a postdoc at the University of Michigan. Prior to this, Jess completed her PhD at ANU, working on macroecological questions and landscape genomics related to lizards in savanna environments, mostly in Australia and Brazil.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/kathryn-hall.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48353"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="ana-belgun-data61">Kathryn Hall | Australian Reference Genome Atlas (ARGA)</h3>



<p>Kathryn leads an innovative multidisciplinary team as the Product Champion for the Australian Reference Genome Atlas (ARGA). She has extensive experience in taxonomy, genomics and the eResearch space, having created the SpongeMaps website, worked at the Queensland Museum on sponge taxonomy, and the Australian Museum investigating polychaete systematics using DNA data. Prior to this, Kathryn held a postdoc role working on digenean and monogenean parasites in aquaculture fishes in Japan. Kathryn completed her PhD at the University of Queensland, where she specialised in the taxonomy and systematics of a family of parasitic worms in fishes.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/keeva-connolly.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48354"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="ana-belgun-data61">Keeva Connolly | ARGA, Australian BioCommons</h3>



<p>Keeva is a scientific business analyst for the Australian BioCommons, a digital infrastructure platform providing tools, methods and training to extend national research capacity in the life sciences. Before starting at the Australian BioCommons, she studied a Bachelor of Genetics (Hons) at the Australian National University and worked for the Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment (now DCCEEW) in plant biosecurity. In her spare time, she enjoys reading, cooking and visiting libraries.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Webinar-moderator-Martin.png" alt="Martin Westgate" class="wp-image-45781"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin&nbsp;Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific&nbsp;information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin&nbsp;is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="want-more">Want more?</h2>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Introducing the ALA’s Biosecurity Hub</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/introducing-the-alas-biosecurity-hub/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 22:05:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47699</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The one stop-shop for Australian biosecurity data, project, and partner information.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>With over 7.6 million hectares of land and 60,000 km of coastline, Australia is vulnerable to the introduction of new biosecurity threats every day. As an island nation, much of the biodiversity found in Australia is unique, therefore introduced species encroaching on our ecosystems can have devastating effects on native flora and fauna.</p>



<p>It is estimated that there are now more introduced species in Australia than native species, but until recently, data to support this has been elusive. <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/#tab_pane-B">The Atlas of Living Australia</a> (ALA) aggregates biodiversity data from native and introduced species found in Australia, making species occurrence information available to governments, land holders, policymakers, researchers and the public, for open-access use.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-1-1024x683.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47715" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-1-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-1-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-1-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Myrtle-Rust-Austropuccinia-psidii-Photo-Credit-Pete-Woodall-CC-BY-NC-1.jpeg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Invasive fungal disease &#8211; Myrtle Rust (<em>Austropuccinia psidii) </em>Photo Credit Pete Woodall CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>The ALA currently holds information on more than 2,383 exotic species and 1.9 million occurrences of pests, weeds, and diseases. Through the automated aggregation of data from more than 900 data partners, and the development of the ALA Biosecurity Hub, the ALA aims to connect people and systems to create a wholistic and informed picture of biosecurity in Australia.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">ALA Biosecurity Hub</a> is a one-stop-shop for biosecurity records, projects and information that leverages ALA’s existing biodiversity infrastructure. It makes biosecurity data more findable and accessible to the biosecurity sector and aggregates several ALA biosecurity tools including:</p>



<ul>
<li>ALA Biosecurity Alerts System</li>



<li>Invasive Species Taxonomy</li>



<li><a href="https://lists.ala.org.au/public/speciesLists?&amp;max=25&amp;sort=listName&amp;order=asc&amp;isInvasive=eq:true">Invasive Species Lists</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p>Additionally, the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">ALA Biosecurity Hub</a> aggregates information across ALA partnered projects such as <a href="https://www.biosecuritycommons.org.au/">Biosecurity Commons</a> and <a href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/biocontrolhub">Australian Biocontrol Hub</a> in one place.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Red-Fox-Vulpes-vulpes-iNaturalist-KHarrison42-91932867.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47706" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Red-Fox-Vulpes-vulpes-iNaturalist-KHarrison42-91932867.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Red-Fox-Vulpes-vulpes-iNaturalist-KHarrison42-91932867-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Red-Fox-Vulpes-vulpes-iNaturalist-KHarrison42-91932867-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Red-Fox-Vulpes-vulpes-iNaturalist-KHarrison42-91932867-768x768.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Invasive carnivore species &#8211; Red Fox <em>(Vulpes vulpes</em>). Photo Credit KHarrison42 CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>ALA Biosecurity Data Analyst Andrew Turley said the development of the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">ALA Biosecurity Hub</a> would be critical in supporting Australia’s Border Force to detect pests early and act.</p>



<p>“Biosecurity affects us every day &#8211; from the way we care for the environment, to protection measures governments implement to manage livestock, plants, and food safety from an economic and health perspective,” Dr Turley said.</p>



<p>“Not only does the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">ALA Biosecurity Hub </a>allow for early notification and detection of pests, it’ll make data more accessible so governments, researchers and industries can implement measures to better protect Australia’s biodiversity.”</p>



<p>Museums Victoria Senior Curator Dr Ken Walker agreed, acknowledging the value of consolidated biosecurity resources in defending against and responding to threats.</p>



<p>“It is important to have a resource that is not only accessible by government and researcher sectors, but also by citizen scientists to be able to better identify emerging threats before their impact becomes widespread,” Dr Walker said. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Recently, data aggregated in the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">ALA Biosecurity Hub</a> has been used in Australia’s State of the Environment reports. These data were used to quantify the trend of increasing diversity and abundance of invasive species across Australia, with invasive species also identified as the most common pressure on threatened species in Australia.</p>



<p>Check out the ALA Biosecurity hub <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/biosecurity/">here</a>, or if you would like to discuss biosecurity data and impacts further, you can contact us <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/">here</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="960" height="640" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Corn-Snake-Pantherophis-guttatus-Photo-Credit-Phila-Goldman-CC-BY-NC.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47700" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Corn-Snake-Pantherophis-guttatus-Photo-Credit-Phila-Goldman-CC-BY-NC.jpg 960w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Corn-Snake-Pantherophis-guttatus-Photo-Credit-Phila-Goldman-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Corn-Snake-Pantherophis-guttatus-Photo-Credit-Phila-Goldman-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Invasive reptile species &#8211; Corn Snake <em>(Pantherophis guttatus).</em> Photo Credit Phila Goldman CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Taxonomist Appreciation Day</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/taxonomist-appreciation-day/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 19 Mar 2023 22:34:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48330</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Taxonomists work in the field of biological classification, and their work is critical to ensuring we can understand and protect Australian species into the future. To celebrate Taxonomist Appreciation Day on 19 March, we sat down with the Atlas of Living Australia’s (ALA) Engagement Team Lead Dr Ely Wallis to find out more about her [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Taxonomists work in the field of biological classification, and their work is critical to ensuring we can understand and protect Australian species into the future.</p>



<p>To celebrate Taxonomist Appreciation Day on 19 March, we sat down with the Atlas of Living Australia’s (ALA) Engagement Team Lead Dr Ely Wallis to find out more about her career and taxonomy experience.<em> </em><em></em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="769" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-1024x769.jpeg" alt="Photo of Ely Wallis" class="wp-image-48339" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-1024x769.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-768x577.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-1536x1154.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-1920x1442.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Ely-Sept2022.jpeg 2046w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>ALA Engagement Team Lead Dr Ely Wallis</em>.</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>1. Why is the field of taxonomy so important to the ALA’s work?</strong></p>



<p><em>Taxonomy provides the mechanism to identify and classify organisms. It’s vital to the ALA because the name of the species observed is one of the three core pieces of information (with location and date) that is required to create a species occurrence record. It’s estimated that only about a third of the +700,000 species found in Australia have been given a scientific name.</em></p>



<p><em>Aggregating species data is reliant on the records being accurately identified at the lowest resolution of the taxonomic hierarchy possible. Identifying organisms in a particular place is important to making decisions about natural resource management and understanding changing climates.</em></p>



<p><em>Taxonomy provides a way to both get data into the ALA and to search for data. All incoming data points are matched to the ‘taxonomic backbone’ or placed into the classification hierarchy in the ALA infrastructure.</em></p>



<p><em>It’s important to be aware that taxonomic names are not static and are continually being revised. This is because researchers learn more (through techniques such as genetic analysis) to better understand how to delineate species. The ALA is on a constant journey to update our taxonomic backbone, to ensure our structure is as current and accurate as possible.</em></p>



<p><strong>2. Tell us about taxonomy in your career?</strong></p>



<p><em>I wouldn’t call myself a taxonomist, both my honours and PhD projects were in zoophysiology rather than taxonomy, but I have been around taxonomy since I started working at Museums Victoria after my PhD in 1995. Earlier than that, I’ve had an interest in collecting biological things since I was a child. I would collect shells at the beach, sorting, identifying, and labelling them. Even as a nine-year-old, I would pack a bag full of books alongside my beach towel, so that I could identify my finds. I had a logbook for recording what I collected each year, so I guess that’s where it started!</em></p>



<p><em>I think that for many people, wanting to know what an animal or plant is called is their first interaction with taxonomy – even if they wouldn’t put it that way. At Museums Victoria, I led a fantastic team to develop&nbsp;</em><a href="https://museumsvictoria.com.au/apps/national-field-guide-apps/"><em>The National Field Guide</em></a><em>&nbsp;apps project. It was a collaborative project with museums around Australia to write species descriptions, gather photographs and sounds to allow anyone to identify common species near them.</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="805" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/National-Field-guide-app-Museums-Victoria-1024x805.jpg" alt="Image of the Museums Victoria Field Guide app" class="wp-image-48336" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/National-Field-guide-app-Museums-Victoria-1024x805.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/National-Field-guide-app-Museums-Victoria-300x236.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/National-Field-guide-app-Museums-Victoria-768x603.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/National-Field-guide-app-Museums-Victoria.jpg 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>National Field Guide App for Victoria. Development of this app was led by Ely’s team in Museums Victoria.</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><em>Scientific literature is vital to taxonomy. Another project that supports taxonomy that I am involved with is the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/collection/bhlau"><em>Biodiversity Heritage Library</em></a><em>&nbsp;(BHL). This global project digitises and makes scientific literature freely accessible to anyone. The Australian BHL supports over forty publishers to digitise Australian published literature. This project also assigns DOIs so that articles can have a persistent and resolvable identifier so researchers can find those papers. I was very proud to start the BHL project in Australia and am lucky to have travelled all over the world with literature.</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="657" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-1024x657.jpg" alt="Illustration of a ring-tailed possum" class="wp-image-48337" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-1024x657.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-300x193.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-768x493.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-1536x986.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-2048x1314.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/BHL-The-Mammals-of-Australia-scan-by-the-Biodiversity-Heritage-Library-n117-w1150-26679138504-1920x1232.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>From the Australian Biodiversity Heritage Library, The Mammals of Australia, London, Printed by Taylor and Francis, pub. by the author,1863.</em></figcaption></figure>



<p><em>I am the current Chair of the international organisation called Biodiversity Information Standards (</em><a href="https://www.tdwg.org/"><em>TDWG</em></a><em>) which develops and maintains the standard for&nbsp;</em><a href="https://dwc.tdwg.org/"><em>Darwin Core</em></a><em>&nbsp;(the international standard for sharing biological data). I also sit on the steering committee for&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.taxonomyaustralia.org.au/"><em>Taxonomy Australia</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p><em>In the ALA we also collaborate with communities on Country to document and share Indigenous language names for plants and animals through the&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/indigenous-ecological-knowledge/"><em>Indigenous Ecological Knowledge</em></a><em>&nbsp;program. Language words and descriptions of species are published, with consent, on the ALA website and I am proud to be able to play a small part in that project.</em></p>



<p><strong>3. Tell us about the species named after you!</strong></p>



<p><em>The species named after me (Birubius wallisae) is a type of crustacean, an amphipod. Amphipods are small creatures (less than a centimetre) and common in marine environments. The amphipod named after me is found around Moreton Bay in Queensland. It’s about 5mm long so you need a good microscope to look at it. It was named after me by my good friend Dr Joanne Taylor at Museums Victoria. Jo named the&nbsp;species after me in appreciation of the support I was able to give her while she was completing her PhD. The literature publication (which is required to recognise a validly named species) for Birubius wallisae is open-access and can be found&nbsp;</em><a href="http://doi.org/10.24199/j.mmv.2001.58.15"><em>here</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="616" height="844" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Birubius-wallisae.jpg" alt="Scientific drawing of the Amphipod named after Ely" class="wp-image-48331" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Birubius-wallisae.jpg 616w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Birubius-wallisae-219x300.jpg 219w" sizes="(max-width: 616px) 100vw, 616px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>Amphipod species (Birubius wallisae) described by Dr Joanne Taylor in honour of Dr Ely Wallis.</em></figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA March 2023 Newsletter</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/newsletter/ala-march-2023-newsletter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 01:53:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48326</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out our the ALA March 2023 Newsletter here.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Check out our the ALA March 2023 Newsletter <a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/march-2023-newsletter">here</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://mailchi.mp/ala/march-2023-newsletter"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="602" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Screen-Shot-2023-03-15-at-12.45.53-pm-602x1024.png" alt="Spider and fox images with newsletter text in between" class="wp-image-48327" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Screen-Shot-2023-03-15-at-12.45.53-pm-602x1024.png 602w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Screen-Shot-2023-03-15-at-12.45.53-pm-176x300.png 176w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/03/Screen-Shot-2023-03-15-at-12.45.53-pm.png 657w" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" /></a></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s message &#8211; March 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-message-march-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 04:36:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48177</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the March 2023 edition of our newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-cropped-218x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48178" width="218" height="300" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-cropped-218x300.jpg 218w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-cropped.jpg 608w" sizes="(max-width: 218px) 100vw, 218px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>2023 will be an exciting year for the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) and our partners in the biodiversity data sector with Australia hosting two major international events later this year. </p>



<p>First, in partnership with CSIRO’s National Research Collections Australia we are excited to bring the <a href="https://www.tdwg.org/conferences/2023/">Biodiversity Information Standards TDWG</a> (Taxonomic Data Working Group) conference to Hobart from 9 &#8211; 13 October. TDWG sets and evolves international standards such as <a href="https://dwc.tdwg.org/">Darwin Core</a> that make the work that ALA and our partners do possible. In addition to TDWG’s focus on biodiversity informatics, science applications of biodiversity data will feature prominently at the conference, so we warmly invite you to get involved – who doesn’t enjoy a major science event on the Hobart waterfront?&nbsp;</p>



<p>Second, the ALA has been proud of its ongoing partnership with the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank">GBIF</a>) where we’ve gained enormous value from relationships with the international GBIF network. At last year’s GBIF Governing Board meeting in Brussels, the ALA and our biological collections partners in CSIRO successfully bid to host the 2023 meeting of the Governing Board in Australia. The meeting will follow directly from the TDWG event and will be hosted in Canberra in mid-October. It’s been 20 years since Australia hosted a meeting of the Governing Board and we are excited to welcome our international partners. </p>



<p>Finally, I’d like to reflect on a remarkable experience our team had over recent months hosting two Indigenous Internship students. We welcomed <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/meet-caitlin-an-ala-indigenous-internship-student-with-a-flare-for-coding/">Caitlin Ramsay </a>(University of New South Wales) and <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/diving-into-dingo-data-with-amos-smith/">Amos Smith</a> (University of Western Australia) who partnered with our Science and Decision Support team over the summer period on two applied projects. As a team, we gained so much from their involvement in our work, and it was rewarding to provide them with some insight into the role of national research infrastructure in Australia’s science and innovation system. For me, it highlighted the value of bringing diversity and new ideas into a team, and the responsibility more established institutions such as the ALA have in supporting our upcoming research infrastructure specialists.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We hope you enjoy our March newsletter. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Celebrating ALA women in STEM</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/celebrating-ala-women-in-stem/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 21:40:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48107</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The&#160;Churchill Fellowship Trust&#160;is a highly competitive awards program that provides opportunities for individuals to travel overseas to gain new knowledge and perspectives in their field of work. The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is privileged to have two Churchill Fellowship Award recipients, Nat Raisbeck-Brown and Dr Erin Roger. What better way to celebrate International Women’s [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.churchilltrust.com.au/">Churchill Fellowship Trust</a>&nbsp;is a highly competitive awards program that provides opportunities for individuals to travel overseas to gain new knowledge and perspectives in their field of work. The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is privileged to have two Churchill Fellowship Award recipients, Nat Raisbeck-Brown and Dr Erin Roger. What better way to celebrate International Women’s Day than chatting with both Nat and Erin about their fantastic achievements and to find out more about their Churchill Fellowship projects.</p>



<p><strong>Nat Raisbeck-Brown</strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="222" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Nat-Raisbeck-Brown-222x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48128" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Nat-Raisbeck-Brown-222x300.jpg 222w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Nat-Raisbeck-Brown.jpg 644w" sizes="(max-width: 222px) 100vw, 222px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Nat Raisbeck-Brown, Churchill Fellowship Award recipient</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Q: What is your role within the ALA and some of your ALA highlights?</p>



<p><em>I’ve led the Indigenous Ecological Knowledge Program (IEK) within the ALA since 2018. In 2019 we published the first set of Indigenous words in the ALA for the Kamilaroi languages. This was launched at the PULiiMA language and technology conference in Darwin. We have also been working with the Noongar Boodjar Language Centre in Perth, &nbsp;the Irra Wangga Language Centre in Geraldton and the Yugul Mangi Rangers in South East Arnhem Land and have now published more than 3200 language words for approximately 700 species in 12 languages. This work links the traditional knowledge from South East Arnhem Land, Kamilaroi Country and the Noongar Nation to each other. These inter-cultural synchronicities mean for the first time we can compare stories from different cultures and find they are both surprisingly similar and different</em>.</p>



<p><br>Q; Can you describe your educational and career journey? How did you become interested in pursuing science?</p>



<p><em>After travelling abroad, I completed my undergraduate degree in Environmental Biology at Curtin University where I discovered a love of Geographic Information System&nbsp;(GIS). I went straight into a Post Graduate Diploma in GIS and have worked in spatial science ever since. I worked for a small mining company and Western Australia’s State Government Land Corporation. I then spent seven years in the Kimberley, working on fire management and running a GIS consultancy and map shop. In that time I did a lot of work and training with Aboriginal people and communities. I started work for CSIRO in 2009 as a GIS projects officer in Agriculture and Ecology and from 2018 have worked with the ALA.</em></p>



<p>Q: Other than being awarded a Churchill Fellowship, what has been a career highlight for you?</p>



<p><em>I feel incredibly privileged to be working with Aboriginal people in the collection, protection, promotion and sharing of their knowledge through the ALA IEK program. Another career highlight was working on the creation of the fire information systems, Fire Fax, NAFI and FireWatch with Allan Lawford and his community over the seven years I was in the Kimberley</em>.</p>



<p>Q: Can you describe your Churchill Fellowship project?</p>



<p><em>My</em><a href="https://www.churchilltrust.com.au/project/to-build-and-share-new-knowledge-of-indigenous-mapping-techniques-from-first-nations-people-globally/"><em>&nbsp;Churchill Fellowship</em></a><em>&nbsp;is supporting me to visit First Nations peoples in Canada, the US and Norway to talk about how they are using mapping technologies to collect, protect and share their traditional knowledge. I’ll be travelling through San Francisco to meet with Google Outreach, Vancouver to meet with Indigenous Mapping Workshop founders – Firelight Group, Vancouver Island, Oklahoma, Kansas, Boston, Oslo and Tromso</em>.</p>



<p>Q: How do you believe diversity in science can drive innovation and progress?</p>



<p><em>It is essential for knowledge to be shared.</em>&nbsp;<em>Aboriginal people have been managing this land for +65,000 year. Now 235 years since colonisation we can see our English-based methods of land and fire management are not appropriate. Science is the platform to bring these two knowledge systems together to ensure we can look after Country into the future.</em></p>



<p>Q: What advice would you give to young women considering a career in science?</p>



<p><em>Find strong and trusted allies that can help you navigate the pathway to the career you want. Reach out to people whose work and methods you admire, let them know what you are doing and what you are interested in.</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IEK-graphic.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48132" width="614" height="521" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IEK-graphic.jpg 777w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IEK-graphic-300x255.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IEK-graphic-768x653.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 614px) 100vw, 614px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Map showing current and future ALA IEK projects. Credit: Nat Raisbeck-Brown, ALA.</figcaption></figure>



<p><br></p>



<p><strong>Dr Erin Roger</strong></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="284" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2022-10-26-111120-300x284.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48130" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2022-10-26-111120-300x284.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Screenshot-2022-10-26-111120.png 700w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr Erin Roger, Churchill Fellowship Award recipient</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Q: What is your role within the ALA and how long have you been at CSIRO/ALA?</p>



<p><em>I’ve been with the ALA now for 2.5 years, but with CSIRO for 3.5 years. I initially joined CSIRO in the Global team but moved to the ALA for an opportunity to support the organisation’s bushfire citizen science response. I currently am the Sector Lead for ALA’s biosecurity and citizen science initiatives.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: Can you describe your educational and career journey? How did you become interested in pursuing science?</p>



<p><em>I’ve always loved the natural environment, I grew up canoe camping with my family in remote areas of Northern Ontario which was formative. I’ve never really known what I wanted to do, but I’ve let my passion and interest in the environment shape my career. That’s resulted in some amazing experiences from aerial moose surveys in Nova Scotia for my Bachelor of Science (Honours) work, modelling wombat presence on the Snowy Mountains Highway for my PhD and working in semi-arid ecology. After university, I became interested in the science-policy interface and joined the New South Wales Environment department to understand science translation. I was lucky enough to have several roles; one of which led me to thinking about how to engage a broader cohort of people in science via citizen science to drive impact. That interest then led me to the ALA.</em></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/DSCN1444-768x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48146" width="344" height="455"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Erin undertaking wombat research </figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Q: Other than being awarded a Churchill Fellowship, what has been a career highlight for you?</p>



<p><em>I attended a United Nations Science-Policy Business meeting in Nairobi as well as the International Union for Conservation of Nature conference in Hawaii as part of a delegation. My highlight though is just the diversity of experiences I’ve had throughout my career ranging from remote field work to getting to meeting diverse people while being involved in challenging and interesting work.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: Can you describe your Churchill Fellowship project?</p>



<p><em>My</em><a href="https://www.churchilltrust.com.au/fellow/erin-roger-nsw-2022/"><em>&nbsp;Churchill Fellowship project</em></a><em>&nbsp;is related to what I do at the ALA. I’m interested in how to engage communities in biosecurity surveillance, essentially getting more eyes and ears on the ground. There are some great examples globally we can learn from. I’ve set a bit of a whirlwind schedule travelling to New Zealand, Samoa, the US, Denmark, Belgium, and the UK. I have a range of meetings lined up including Indigenous leaders, government, NGOs and academics.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: How do you believe diversity in science can drive innovation and progress?</p>



<p><em>More diverse teams can shape research priorities and challenge norms. The more people involved lead to a diversity in thinking of how problems are represented and solved. Citizen science is a great way to increase diversity, but it also comes with challenges like thinking through ethics, proper attribution, exploitation and ensuring a diversity of communication methods. These considerations aren’t just unique to citizen science and can be used to inform STEM development more broadly.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What advice would you give to young women considering a career in science?</p>



<p><em>Pursue what you’re interested in and passionate about. If you can’t put a name to what specific job you want, that’s okay. The ALA didn’t exist when I was in high school. I think a background in STEM can open-up opportunities that we can’t really imagine right now. It can also lead to a diverse career working across a number of areas</em>.</p>



<p><br>Q: In your opinion, how can we encourage more girls and women to pursue careers in science?</p>



<p><em>It’s important to put the ladder down so to speak. Wherever people are in their career, there are opportunities to give a hand up. If you see amazing women doing a great job, tell them and, equally important, tell others. Word about talent spreads quickly. The more people that see women in a diversity of positions the easier it is to pursue a career in science.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>From little things, NatureMapr grows</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/from-little-things-naturemapr-grows/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2023 23:39:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48194</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[NatureMapr is a data partner of the ALA, contributing verified citizen scientist biodiversity records to support the awareness and knowledge of species in local areas. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Have you ever been mountain biking and discovered that you were inches away from one of Australia’s most endangered orchard species? This was the basis for how <a href="https://naturemapr.org/home">NatureMapr</a> came to life!</p>



<p>NatureMapr is a citizen science data partner of the ALA. It has evolved from a humble sighting of a <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/id.biodiversity.org.au/taxon/apni/51398755">Canberra Spider Orchid (Caladenia actensis</a>) into an innovative and robust data platform underpinned by a community of keen users and expert moderators.</p>



<p>The tool is a repository to record sightings of species, with the data and image gallery used to inform both the public, and government bodies for planning and scientific research. Information from NatureMapr is used to support on-ground environmental outcomes such as the protection of sensitive species, informing of development decisions and guiding prescribed burns.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="785" height="585" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Graphium-macleayanum-Photo-credit-MichaelMulvaney-NatureMapr.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48196" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Graphium-macleayanum-Photo-credit-MichaelMulvaney-NatureMapr.jpg 785w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Graphium-macleayanum-Photo-credit-MichaelMulvaney-NatureMapr-300x224.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Graphium-macleayanum-Photo-credit-MichaelMulvaney-NatureMapr-768x572.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 785px) 100vw, 785px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Macleay&#8217;s Swallowtail <em>(Graphium macleayanum) </em>Photo credit MichaelMulvaney, NatureMapr</figcaption></figure>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"><strong>How does NatureMapr work with the ALA?</strong></p>



<p>Any citizen scientist can record a species sighting to contribute to the database, along with uploading other critical information like GPS locations, audio recordings and images to support the data record. The platform supports both ad-hoc species occurrence records as well as structured citizen science-led surveys (bioblitzes and photographic competitions). Data submissions can be made in less than a minute using the NatureMapr App (available through mobile app for <a href="https://apps.apple.com/au/app/naturemapr/id1042299523">iOS</a> or <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=naturemapr.mobile.droid&amp;hl=en_AU&amp;gl=US">Android</a>) or through the NatureMapr website.</p>



<p>NatureMapr’s AI based non-human moderator works together with its community of expert human moderators to quickly provide expert identification of submissions to users. From there, verified data is automatically passed through to the ALA as well as respective state and local government biodiversity databases as open data. The work of data partners like NatureMapr helps to bridge the gap between citizen science observations and driving on-ground research to allow easy discoverability and visibility of Australian biodiversity data.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="400" height="100" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Naturemapr-logo.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48195" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Naturemapr-logo.png 400w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Naturemapr-logo-300x75.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Diving into Dingo data with Amos Smith</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/diving-into-dingo-data-with-amos-smith/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 22:48:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48148</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We sat down with Amos Smith, one of Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) Indigenous Interns. Amos recently completed his Internship with the ALA as part of CSIRO’s Indigenous Scholarship Program over summer 22-23. Read more about Amos and his project below. Q: What are you currently studying? I’m in my final year studying conservation biology [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>We sat down with Amos Smith, one of Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s (ALA) Indigenous Interns. Amos recently completed his Internship with the ALA as part of CSIRO’s Indigenous Scholarship Program over summer 22-23. Read more about Amos and his project below.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="215" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-215x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48149" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-215x300.jpg 215w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-732x1024.jpg 732w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-768x1074.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-1098x1536.jpg 1098w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-1464x2048.jpg 1464w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-1920x2685.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Smith-scaled.jpg 1830w" sizes="(max-width: 215px) 100vw, 215px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Amos Smith, ALA Indigenous Intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Q: What are you currently studying?</p>



<p><em>I’m in my final year studying conservation biology at the </em><a href="https://www.uwa.edu.au/"><em>University of Western Australia</em></a><em>. Once I finish my undergraduate degree, I would like to aim for postgraduate studies and possibly undertake a research project in the future.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What did your ALA Internship project focus on? What factors led you to choose this topic?</p>



<p><em>I focused on investigating</em><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/c2056f1b-fcde-45b9-904b-1cab280368d1#overview"><em>&nbsp;</em></a><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/c2056f1b-fcde-45b9-904b-1cab280368d1#overview"><em>Dingo (Canis familiaris</em>)</a>&nbsp;<em>data within the ALA using R Studio. I had no clue what species to choose and happened to have a dream about dingoes during this time, so I just took it as a sign. I then realised that we have a serious ecological problem with the removal of dingoes as an apex predator from the Australian landscape. Investigating what the data can tell us in the ALA about dingoes may lead to better conservation for the species in the future.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What’s a new skill that that you learned through the program?</p>



<p><em>How to code using R Studio as well as the process of investigating data.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?</p>



<p><em>Hitting points where I just keep getting errors in the code and trying to figure out what’s wrong.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What was the highlight of your internship experience?</p>



<p><em>Going to Canberra and meeting the team with such a positive and supportive work environment. Also travelling down to Esperance, WA and meeting the Tjaltjraak Indigenous Rangers and introducing them to the ALA. I loved learning from them, and really appreciated them showing me their Country and how they are caring for it. It’s always really motivating being surrounded by people who have the drive to make positive change.</em></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Data-Viz.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48150" width="657" height="519" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Data-Viz.jpg 657w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Amos-Data-Viz-300x237.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 657px) 100vw, 657px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dingo <em>(Canis familiaris</em>) species occurrence records and dingo fencing plotted across Nationally Protected Areas (NPA) in NT and SA, Amos Smith.  Amos selected to plot data against NPAs as this is where dingoes have the most protection by legislation.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Congratulations Amos on completing your Internship with the ALA! </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Meet Caitlin &#8211; An ALA Indigenous Internship student with a flare for coding</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/meet-caitlin-an-ala-indigenous-internship-student-with-a-flare-for-coding/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 06:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48091</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Across summer 2022-23, the ALA hosted two Indigenous Internship students as part of the National Collections and Marine Infrastructure (NCMI) Indigenous Scholarship Program. Celebrating International Women and Girls in Science Day, we&#8217;re profiling Caitlin Ramsay! Caitlin joined the ALA Science and Decision Support team during her internship, where she investigated the distribution of invasive species [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Across summer 2022-23, the ALA hosted two Indigenous Internship students as part of the National Collections and Marine Infrastructure (NCMI) Indigenous Scholarship Program. Celebrating International Women and Girls in Science Day, we&#8217;re profiling Caitlin Ramsay! Caitlin joined the ALA Science and Decision Support team during her internship, where she investigated the distribution of invasive species across Australia over time. </p>



<p>We chatted with Caitlin to find out more about her project through the Atlas of Living Australia.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="297" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-300x297.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48094" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-300x297.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-1024x1012.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-768x759.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-1536x1519.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-2048x2025.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-1920x1898.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Caitlin Ramsay, ALA Indigenous Internship student</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Q: What degree are you currently studying, and what made you study science? </p>



<p><em>I’m in my last term studying a double degree of Bioinformatics Engineering and Ecology at UNSW. At first, I wanted to go straight into work once I finished my undergraduate degree, but now, I’m considering completing either a Masters or PhD in something related to environmental science. I’ve always had a strong connection to the land and ocean as well as a curiosity for the natural world. It became clearer to me as I got older that an environmental science degree would foster these values of mine and potentially let me make an impact.</em></p>



<p>Q: What made you apply for the Indigenous Studentship Internship program?</p>



<p><em>I heard about ALA internships from some friends at UNSW who participated in another internship program. From there I investigated whether the ALA offered internships over the summer and stumbled upon the Indigenous Studentship program. I applied because I wanted to see what it was like to apply the skills I’ve learned at university in industry.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What did your ALA internship project focus on?<br><em>My project focused on invasive species and how they have moved around over time. At first, I was interested in species&#8217; ranges shifting as a way to cope with climate change. This then led into this idea of changing species distributions and how quickly invasive species can spread within Australia. I also helped with the galah python package development which involved writing tests, finding bugs and helping to design its website.</em><br></p>



<p>Q: What was a new skill that that you learned through the program that you’re proud of and what were some challenges that you faced during your project?</p>



<p><em>Coming into this internship I had never really done any data visualisation before. Now I feel like I have a pretty good grasp on how to code figures in Python and have been able to produce some aesthetic plots that I’m super proud of.  While coding my data visualisations, I ran into a lot of bugs which is always challenging as sometimes it would take an entire day to try fix. I also was using Python to make data visualisations while the rest of the team predominantly used R. This meant I had to figure out a lot of the bugs on my own which was challenging but also a useful skill to develop.</em><br></p>



<p>Q: Tell us about your highlight of the internship program? </p>



<p><em>The highlight of the internship for me would definitely have to be the people I worked with. They were all so amazing and friendly and just made my experience here so fun that I’m a bit sad to be leaving</em>!</p>



<p></p>



<p>Congratulations Caitlin on successfully completing your project with the ALA! Check out some of the incredible data visualisations Caitlin produced through her project using the ALA galah Python package.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1024x768.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48092" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1024x768.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-300x225.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-768x576.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1536x1152.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-2048x1536.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1920x1440.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-640x480.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cane toads <em>(Rhinella marina)</em> were introduced to far north Queensland in the 1930s and since then have multiplied quickly and spread far across northern Australia. This figure shows where cane toads were distributed in Australia each decade since their introduction.</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1024x768.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48093" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1024x768.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-300x225.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-768x576.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1536x1152.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-2048x1536.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1920x1440.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-640x480.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Invasive species are not always non-native and even some Australian native species can become invasive. (<em>Pittosporum undulatum)</em> trees are one example of this as they have been transported outside of their known native range where it acts as a weed and is changing ecosystem structure. This figure shows the Australian bioregions that <em>P. undulatum</em> is native to and the ones it has been introduced to.</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Call for applications &#8211; GBIF 2023 Graduate Researchers Award</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/call-for-applications-gbif-2023-graduate-researchers-award/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 22:39:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are open for the GBIF 2023 Graduate Researchers Award! This award is an annual program aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics at the Masters and PhD student level. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1151" height="414" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47988" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF.jpg 1151w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF-300x108.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF-1024x368.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF-768x276.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1151px) 100vw, 1151px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Illustration of&nbsp;<em>Macrolepiota procera</em>&nbsp;(Scop.) Gray, from&nbsp;<a href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/1266181"><em>Führer für Pilzfreunde</em></a>&nbsp;(1821) via&nbsp;<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biodivlibrary/8509418243/in/album-72157632865665228/">Biodiversity Heritage Library</a>, no rights reserved under&nbsp;<a href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">CC0</a>.</figcaption></figure>



<p>The 2023 programme will provide two €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD $7,700) recognising the work of two early-career researchers. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> (GBIF). The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA are also accessible via GBIF.</p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p class="has-red-color has-text-color has-medium-font-size" style="text-decoration:underline"><strong><em><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)" class="has-inline-color has-red-color">Australian applications to the ALA are due by 31st May 2023.</mark></em></strong></p>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a> if you require further information.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat. The winners will be announced in September/October 2023.</p>



<p>Note: Awardees are expected to acknowledge GBIF support when disseminating research results via peer-reviewed publications, presentations at professional meetings, and other media.</p>



<p><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></p>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol type="1" start="1">
<li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)</li>



<li><strong>Project description</strong>&nbsp;(<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em>) that describes:<br>a. How the research advances biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity.<br>b.&nbsp;<strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.</li>



<li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.</li>



<li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate program of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li>
</ol>



<p><strong>How to submit an application to the ALA (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol type="1" start="1">
<li>Visit the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6gyLOum00YsYc4OtVGK33Y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2023-gbif-graduate-researchers-award">GBIF 2023 Graduate Researchers Award</a> page&nbsp;and follow the instructions.&nbsp;<br><br></li>



<li>Submit your nominations to <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a> with ‘2023 GBIF Graduate Researchers Application _YOUR NAME’ in the subject line by <strong>31st May 2023.</strong></li>
</ol>



<p>The criteria for the awards include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Originality and innovation</li>



<li>Use of and strategic significance for data accessed through GBIF</li>



<li>Measurable effectiveness and impact in advancing biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6gyLOum00YsYc4OtVGK33Y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2023-gbif-graduate-researchers-award">GBIF</a> website.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
