<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 06:32:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Meet Caitlin &#8211; An ALA Indigenous Internship student with a flare for coding</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/meet-caitlin-an-ala-indigenous-internship-student-with-a-flare-for-coding/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2023 06:32:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48091</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Across summer 2022-23, the ALA hosted two Indigenous Internship students as part of the National Collections and Marine Infrastructure (NCMI) Indigenous Scholarship Program. Celebrating International Women and Girls in Science Day, we&#8217;re profiling Caitlin Ramsay! Caitlin joined the ALA Science and Decision Support team during her internship, where she investigated the distribution of invasive species [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Across summer 2022-23, the ALA hosted two Indigenous Internship students as part of the National Collections and Marine Infrastructure (NCMI) Indigenous Scholarship Program. Celebrating International Women and Girls in Science Day, we&#8217;re profiling Caitlin Ramsay! Caitlin joined the ALA Science and Decision Support team during her internship, where she investigated the distribution of invasive species across Australia over time. </p>



<p>We chatted with Caitlin to find out more about her project through the Atlas of Living Australia.</p>



<p></p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="300" height="297" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-300x297.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48094" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-300x297.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-1024x1012.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-768x759.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-1536x1519.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-2048x2025.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/IMG_0852-1920x1898.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Caitlin Ramsay, ALA Indigenous Internship student</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Q: What degree are you currently studying, and what made you study science? </p>



<p><em>I’m in my last term studying a double degree of Bioinformatics Engineering and Ecology at UNSW. At first, I wanted to go straight into work once I finished my undergraduate degree, but now, I’m considering completing either a Masters or PhD in something related to environmental science. I’ve always had a strong connection to the land and ocean as well as a curiosity for the natural world. It became clearer to me as I got older that an environmental science degree would foster these values of mine and potentially let me make an impact.</em></p>



<p>Q: What made you apply for the Indigenous Studentship Internship program?</p>



<p><em>I heard about ALA internships from some friends at UNSW who participated in another internship program. From there I investigated whether the ALA offered internships over the summer and stumbled upon the Indigenous Studentship program. I applied because I wanted to see what it was like to apply the skills I’ve learned at university in industry.</em></p>



<p><br>Q: What did your ALA internship project focus on?<br><em>My project focused on invasive species and how they have moved around over time. At first, I was interested in species&#8217; ranges shifting as a way to cope with climate change. This then led into this idea of changing species distributions and how quickly invasive species can spread within Australia. I also helped with the galah python package development which involved writing tests, finding bugs and helping to design its website.</em><br></p>



<p>Q: What was a new skill that that you learned through the program that you’re proud of and what were some challenges that you faced during your project?</p>



<p><em>Coming into this internship I had never really done any data visualisation before. Now I feel like I have a pretty good grasp on how to code figures in Python and have been able to produce some aesthetic plots that I’m super proud of.  While coding my data visualisations, I ran into a lot of bugs which is always challenging as sometimes it would take an entire day to try fix. I also was using Python to make data visualisations while the rest of the team predominantly used R. This meant I had to figure out a lot of the bugs on my own which was challenging but also a useful skill to develop.</em><br></p>



<p>Q: Tell us about your highlight of the internship program? </p>



<p><em>The highlight of the internship for me would definitely have to be the people I worked with. They were all so amazing and friendly and just made my experience here so fun that I’m a bit sad to be leaving</em>!</p>



<p></p>



<p>Congratulations Caitlin on successfully completing your project with the ALA! Check out some of the incredible data visualisations Caitlin produced through her project using the ALA galah Python package.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1024x768.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48092" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1024x768.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-300x225.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-768x576.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1536x1152.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-2048x1536.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-1920x1440.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/cane-toads-final-640x480.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Cane toads <em>(Rhinella marina)</em> were introduced to far north Queensland in the 1930s and since then have multiplied quickly and spread far across northern Australia. This figure shows where cane toads were distributed in Australia each decade since their introduction.</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1024x768.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48093" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1024x768.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-300x225.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-768x576.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1536x1152.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-2048x1536.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-1920x1440.png 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/p-undulatum-bioregions-final-640x480.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Invasive species are not always non-native and even some Australian native species can become invasive. (<em>Pittosporum undulatum)</em> trees are one example of this as they have been transported outside of their known native range where it acts as a weed and is changing ecosystem structure. This figure shows the Australian bioregions that <em>P. undulatum</em> is native to and the ones it has been introduced to.</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Call for applications &#8211; GBIF 2023 Graduate Researchers Award</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/call-for-applications-gbif-2023-graduate-researchers-award/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2023 22:39:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47986</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are open for the GBIF 2023 Graduate Researchers Award! This award is an annual program aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics at the Masters and PhD student level. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1151" height="414" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47988" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF.jpg 1151w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF-300x108.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF-1024x368.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/grad-researcher-award-2023-GBIF-768x276.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1151px) 100vw, 1151px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Illustration of&nbsp;<em>Macrolepiota procera</em>&nbsp;(Scop.) Gray, from&nbsp;<a href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/1266181"><em>Führer für Pilzfreunde</em></a>&nbsp;(1821) via&nbsp;<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biodivlibrary/8509418243/in/album-72157632865665228/">Biodiversity Heritage Library</a>, no rights reserved under&nbsp;<a href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">CC0</a>.</figcaption></figure>



<p>The 2023 programme will provide two €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD $7,700) recognising the work of two early-career researchers. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/" target="_blank">Global Biodiversity Information Facility</a> (GBIF). The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA are also accessible via GBIF.</p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p class="has-red-color has-text-color has-medium-font-size" style="text-decoration:underline"><strong><em><mark style="background-color:rgba(0, 0, 0, 0)" class="has-inline-color has-red-color">Australian applications to the ALA are due by 31st May 2023.</mark></em></strong></p>



<p><strong>Nomination process</strong></p>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:ala@csiro.au">ala@csiro.au</a> if you require further information.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat. The winners will be announced in September/October 2023.</p>



<p>Note: Awardees are expected to acknowledge GBIF support when disseminating research results via peer-reviewed publications, presentations at professional meetings, and other media.</p>



<p><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></p>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol type="1" start="1">
<li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)</li>



<li><strong>Project description</strong> (<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em>) that describes:<br>a. How the research advances biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity.<br>b. <strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.</li>



<li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.</li>



<li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate program of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li>
</ol>



<p><strong>How to submit an application to the ALA (Australian applicants)</strong></p>



<ol type="1" start="1">
<li>Visit the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6gyLOum00YsYc4OtVGK33Y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2023-gbif-graduate-researchers-award">GBIF 2023 Graduate Researchers Award</a> page&nbsp;and follow the instructions.&nbsp;<br><br></li>



<li>Submit your nominations to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:ala@csiro.au">ala@csiro.au</a>, with ‘2023 GBIF Graduate Researchers Application _YOUR NAME’ in the subject line by&nbsp;<strong>31st May 2023.</strong></li>
</ol>



<p>The criteria for the awards include:</p>



<ul>
<li>Originality and innovation</li>



<li>Use of and strategic significance for data accessed through GBIF</li>



<li>Measurable effectiveness and impact in advancing biodiversity informatics and/or the conservation of biological diversity</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Further information</strong></p>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the <a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6gyLOum00YsYc4OtVGK33Y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2023-gbif-graduate-researchers-award">GBIF</a> website.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protecting Australian biodiversity with data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/protecting-australian-biodiversity-with-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2023 22:41:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47966</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Meet our 2022 Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species. While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><strong>Meet our 2022 Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program winners</strong></p>



<p>As Australia is home to unique biodiversity and ecosystems, it’s vital that researchers, governments and industry have access to high-quality data so they can better understand, monitor and protect species.</p>



<p>While biodiversity data such as physical specimens in collections, or data from field programs are used to address specific research goals, these data often require additional resources to ensure they can be digitised and made available nationally as open data.</p>



<p>To improve data accessibility the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) launched the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>. This program is designed to support Australian museums, biological collections, herbaria, and research teams to digitise their data, and making it available through the ALA, and internationally through the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF).</p>



<p>Through a nationally competitive application process, six projects were awarded grants to digitise their priority biodiversity data. The output from this program will enable data on rare and unique species to become open and accessible through the ALA. Using FAIR principles (findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable), this data will support research, decision making and conservation efforts to better protect Australian biodiversity.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Copy-of-ALA-Facebook-Cover-old-1024x577.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47994" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Copy-of-ALA-Facebook-Cover-old-1024x577.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Copy-of-ALA-Facebook-Cover-old-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Copy-of-ALA-Facebook-Cover-old-768x433.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Copy-of-ALA-Facebook-Cover-old-1536x865.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Copy-of-ALA-Facebook-Cover-old.jpg 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Australian Biodiversity Mobilisation Program 2022 Projects banner</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>The successful projects:</strong></p>



<p>In the 2022 round of the program, applicants were able to apply for either a small grant of $20,000 or a large grant of $50,000 to support activities to digitise existing biodiversity data. Four small grants and two large grants were awarded in 2022 with data from these projects expected to be made available through the ALA by July 2023.</p>



<p>The successful 2022 projects include the following:</p>



<ol type="1" start="1">
<li>New South Wales Department of Primary Industries, NSW – mobilising plant pest and disease data from the NSW Biosecurity Collections (~600,000 records).</li>



<li>South Australia Museum (SAM), SA– mobilise the SAM’s Australian Biological Tissues Collection of 39 donated frozen tissue collections of Australian freshwater fishes (around 90% of all known species and ~46,000 records).</li>



<li>Queensland Museum Network, QLD – mobilising and enhance data from the Cribb Australian Fish Trematode Collection (&gt;20,000 records of &gt;1,000 fish species).</li>



<li>Tasmanian Museum and Art Gallery, TAS – mobilising wildlife molecular and tissue data (&gt; 8,500 sample vials and 1,650 formalin fixed specimens in the histology collection).</li>



<li>Edith Cowan University, WA – mobilising plant and fungi data from the Robert Brown Herbarium.</li>



<li>Botanic Gardens and Parks Authority, WA – mobilising data in the Kings Park and Botanic Garden Herbarium collection (18,200 specimens).</li>
</ol>



<p>Congratulations to the successful projects, we look forward to working with them to make their data available nationally. We’d like to also acknowledge the applications that were not successful as they were universally excellent making our assessment process very challenging. We are also grateful to the independent review panel chaired by Professor David Cantrill for their work in reviewing proposals and selecting a fantastic suite of final recipients.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="200" height="300" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47969" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-200x300.jpg 200w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/DenisSmith_110613_IMG_4630_LR-1.jpg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Leanne Wheaton working on collections specimens at South Australia Museum, Photo Credit Denis Smith, South Australia Museum. </figcaption></figure>



<p>The 2023 grant round for the Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program will open for applications in&nbsp;<strong>March 2023</strong>. Keep an eye on the ALA website, social media and blogs for more information shortly.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA user experience (UX) project: Call for expressions of interest</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-user-experience-ux-project-call-for-expressions-of-interest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 02:27:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47953</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Want to help us improve the ALA? We’re reviewing our website and need your feedback! ALA is looking for volunteers to help us improve the usability, look and feel of our website. If you’re interested in shaping the future of the ALA, we’d love to hear from you! The ALA has undertaken several user satisfaction [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 style="font-size:25px" style="font-size:25px" id="want-to-help-us-improve-the-ala-were-reviewing-our-website-and-need-your-feedback"><strong>Want to help us improve the ALA? We’re reviewing our website and need your feedback!</strong></h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>ALA is looking for volunteers to help us improve the usability, look and feel of our website. If you’re interested in shaping the future of the ALA, we’d love to hear from you!</p>



<p>The ALA has undertaken several user satisfaction surveys since launching in 2010. As a response to your feedback, we’ve implemented many of the comments and suggestions raised. We also have more exciting improvements in our pipeline. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Since web technologies and styles are constantly changing, we are looking to undertake a review of our website and we need your input.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="369" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1024x369.png" alt="Five screenshots of the ALA home page from left to right: 2011, 2013, 2017, 2019, 2023. Dotted line and year labels are also shown left to right. Background is yellow with a tech/system motif of lines, circles and arrows" class="wp-image-47955" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1024x369.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-300x108.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-768x276.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1536x553.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-2048x737.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1920x691.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>ALA homepage over the years</em></figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>We are looking for volunteers to help us by undertaking a series of tasks. These would include a face-to-face interview (via video conference), reviewing mockups, and testing prototypes. Essentially, we’d like to hear your feedback on the site as it currently is and continue hearing your input as we develop new designs.</p>



<p>We appreciate your time and feedback, and your input will help shape the ALA.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="who-can-participate"><strong>Who can participate?</strong></h2>



<ul>
<li>Any ALA user over 18 may volunteer</li>



<li>You may be a new user or have been using the ALA for years</li>



<li>We are <em>mostly</em> looking for Australian-based users, but international users are welcome too</li>



<li><a>Whether you’re a researcher, government assessor, collections curator, citizen scientist, university student, community group member or otherwise use the ALA on a regular basis, you’re welcome to participate.</a></li>
</ul>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="whats-involved"><strong>What’s involved?</strong></h2>



<p>Participating in our user experience testing will involve a series of tasks including a face-to-face (online) interview, reviewing mockup designs and testing prototypes. All up, these activities would take just 3-4 hours of your time over the next 12 months, starting from late February 2023.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="when-do-registrations-close"><strong>When do registrations close?</strong></h2>



<p>If you are interested in participating, please let us know by Friday, 10 February 2023.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="how-do-i-register"><strong>How do I register?</strong></h2>



<p class="has-text-color has-medium-font-size" style="color:#f26649"><strong><a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/HZG8XJW" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Register my interest</a></strong></p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="next-steps"><strong>Next steps</strong></h2>



<p>In late February we’ll select a representative user group, and email those users to organise the first activities.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="any-questions"><strong>Any questions?</strong></h2>



<p>Please email us at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ux-image-only-1024x586.png" alt="A group of four people sitting around a table, having a conversation. They have laptops and coffee mugs." class="wp-image-47956" width="1000" height="566"/></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Our ALA interns dive into data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/our-ala-interns-dive-into-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 04:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47728</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia was delighted to host three undergraduate students from the University of New South Wales (UNSW) as part of a 12-week internship program across spring – summer 2022. Our interns were spread across two streams: a Data Science Internship, which offered students the opportunity to apply their Python or R skills [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/#tab_pane-B">Atlas of Living Australia</a> was delighted to host three undergraduate students from the <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/">University of New South Wales</a> (UNSW) as part of a 12-week internship program across spring – summer 2022. Our interns were spread across two streams: a Data Science Internship, which offered students the opportunity to apply their Python or R skills to biodiversity problem solving, and a Data Visualisation for Communication Internship, which used ALA’s R package, <a href="https://galah.ala.org.au/">{galah}</a>, to create visualisations that are reproducible and scientifically transparent.</p>



<p>We chatted with our students, Steph, Elijah and Thai, to find out more about their ALA internship experience and what they’ve learned throughout the process.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Steph-Wooley-2022-ALA-intern-300x290.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47730" width="370" height="361"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Steph Woolley &#8211; Data Visualisation intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong><u>Steph is studying a Bachelor of Advanced Science majoring in Marine &amp; Coastal Science.</u></strong></p>



<p>Q) What made you apply for the 2022 ALA Internship program?</p>



<p><em>A) Throughout my studies, I had always seen these amazing ways of displaying data and communicating science. When this internship appeared through an email by UNSW, I thought it was the perfect opportunity to develop my skills and to try to create one of the visualisations I had always seen in my courses.</em></p>



<p>Q) What did your ALA internship project focus on?</p>



<p><em>A) My internship was a data visualisation and analysis project. I spent my time analysing ALA data and developing a visualisation from the data that I had chosen to look at.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was a new skill you learned through the program that you’re proud of?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>I’m most proud of how my coding skills have developed over the internship. When I look back to the knowledge I had when I started this internship compared to what I have now, there’s a really big difference. I’m proud of how much I’ve learnt and the skills I’ve been able to build upon over the last 12 weeks.</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Q) What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>The biggest challenge for me across the 12 weeks has been time management and trusting the process. Throughout my university experience, I haven’t really had any experiences like this where we are working towards one main goal for such a long period of time. I think the process of making little steps each week towards the main goal has been a really big learning experience and it was definitely a challenge to get used to trying to achieve smaller tasks on a weekly basis rather than a larger main goal.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was your highlight from the internship program?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>The main highlight of the internship program was having the opportunity to develop my coding skills and being able and develop this skill with help and feedback from my supervisor. Having the opportunity to spend a long period of time working on a project that you have come up with, and that you find interesting, was also a big highlight.</em></p>



<p><em>The best individual moment though was definitely the day I finally got my visualisation and model to work and I could see the project coming together!</em></p>



<p>See what Steph created below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="600" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year-1.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-47737"/></figure>



<div class="wp-block-file"><a id="wp-block-file--media-d6436e48-4eff-46ff-b33b-1043425fef2d" href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year.gif">Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year</a><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year.gif" class="wp-block-file__button wp-element-button" download aria-describedby="wp-block-file--media-d6436e48-4eff-46ff-b33b-1043425fef2d">Download</a></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="633" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-1024x633.png" alt="" class="wp-image-47736" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-1024x633.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-300x185.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-768x475.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia.png 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Species Distribution Model of Nudibranch occurrences across Australia.</figcaption></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern-300x282.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47729" width="322" height="303" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern-300x282.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern-768x723.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern.jpg 981w" sizes="(max-width: 322px) 100vw, 322px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Elijah Magistrado &#8211; Data Science intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong><u>Elijah is studying a Bachelor of Advanced Science majoring in Ecology</u></strong></p>



<p>Q) What made you apply for the 2022 ALA Internship program?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em> I had wanted to do an internship position before I started my honours project in February and thought it was a great opportunity to gain real-world experience and further develop my skills in data science.</em></p>



<p>Q) What did your ALA internship project focus on?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>A) My internship focused on standardising expert distribution maps. These are maps that represent where species can be found in Australia. These datasets are sent through to the ALA in different formats and layouts which need to be managed. My task was to convert all of the datasets into the format of existing expert distribution maps in the ALA and upload them so everyone can see the new maps.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was a new skill you learned through the program that you’re proud of?</p>



<p><em>A) I am proud to say that I can now program in Python! I have attempted to learn Python prior to the internship but having a project to work on makes motivation much easier. I am very pleased to have learned this skill as it helps broaden my study and career choices in the future.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?</p>



<p><em>A) Learning how to manage my time properly was definitely my biggest challenge. I hadn’t realised how exhausting it was to balance study, work, and learning Python. However, creating a structured routine has helped significantly with managing my time. It was great to have this opportunity to further develop time-management skills ahead of my honours project.&nbsp;&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>Q) What was your highlight of the internship program?</p>



<p><em>A) The highlight of my internship program was seeing the maps load properly on the test server. Initially, I had many issues that had caused the maps I uploaded to not show up. Once I had figured out what I had done wrong, fixed the issues, and tried uploading again, I felt very relieved to see that the maps were loading properly. After the issues were ironed out, the rest of the datasets were straight-forward.</em></p>



<p>See what Elijah created below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1015" height="980" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map.png" alt="" class="wp-image-47738" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map.png 1015w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map-300x290.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map-768x742.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1015px) 100vw, 1015px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Occurrence records of Rainbow Lorikeets <em>(Trichoglossus moluccanus</em>) from 2020 onwards against its expert distribution map provided by BirdLife Australia.</figcaption></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Thai-2022-intern-ALA-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47731" width="383" height="385"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Thai Rushbrook &#8211;  Data Visualisation intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong><u>Thai is studying a Bachelor of Fine Arts and Science majoring in Photography &amp; Ecology.</u></strong></p>



<p>Q) What made you apply for the 2022 ALA Internship program?</p>



<p>A)<em>&nbsp;My university posted a list of internship positions available, and the ALA was on there! I’d heard of the ALA before and thought the data analysis/visualization combination suited my interests really well.</em></p>



<p>Q) What did your ALA internship project focus on?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A<em>) My project focused on the number of ducks recorded in greater Melbourne in the COVID-19 lockdown periods of 2020-2021. I was comparing them to ‘normal’ years, 2017-2019, to see if there was any difference.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was a new skill you learned through the program that you’re proud of?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>I started the term with very basic R-Studio skills, so I learnt a lot about R by organising data, transforming it, and creating the actual visualisations. I think I learnt more R-Studio tricks in this one term than the rest of my degree to date!</em></p>



<p>Q) What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A)<em> Initially I was so nervous I didn’t have the skills needed to make a great project, so it took me a while to get started. Once I gained a little confidence, I was able to get creative and I’m very happy with the results.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was your highlight of the internship program?&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A<em>) Coming together with the other interns at the end of the term to see what they had been working on was amazing. I loved seeing the different paths we took given a similar brief.</em></p>



<p>See what Thai created below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="936" height="542" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47739" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow.jpg 936w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow-300x174.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow-768x445.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 936px) 100vw, 936px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Visualisation of the number of duck records submitted to the ALA &#8211; 2020-21 compared to 2017-19 &#8211; with COVID-19 periods highlighted in yellow.</figcaption></figure>



<p>If you would like to know more about ALA internship opportunities, contact us <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/" data-type="URL">he</a><a href="communications@ala.org.au">r</a><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/">e</a>. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA webinar: Advances in Biodiversity Modelling</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-advances-in-biodiversity-modelling/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:44:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Advancements in scientific modelling have enabled improvements in key decision-making. When it comes to biodiversity this work is crucial, especially in our changing environment. Hear from our distinguished speakers about their work in this space, including the applications of modelling to conservation prioritisation, and sustainable land use.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA webinar: Advances in Biodiversity Modelling – 23 Nov 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-vuDDO-Dt-k?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEDT, Wednesday 23 November 2022, with 201 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="speakers">Speakers</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/s.ferrier-speaker.png" alt="Simon Ferrier" class="wp-image-47647"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Simon Ferrier | CSIRO Land &amp; Water</h3>



<p>Simon Ferrier is a Chief Research Scientist with CSIRO Land and Water, an Honorary Professor at the Australian National University, and an Honorary Fellow at the United Nations Environment Programme World Conservation Monitoring Centre (UNEP-WCMC). Simon and his CSIRO colleagues have been developing a new generation of macroecological approaches to biodiversity modelling and scenario analysis, focused on assessing past-to-present change in the status of biodiversity, projecting impacts of future scenarios of climate and land-use change. Prior to this, Simon spent over 20 years working with state-government agencies, including pioneering the development of species- and community-level biodiversity modelling.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/c.archibald-speaker.png" alt="Carla Archibald" class="wp-image-47651"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Carla Archibald | Centre for Integrative Ecology, Deakin University</h3>



<p>Dr Carla Archibald is a Research Fellow at Deakin University under the Land Use Future project. This Land Use Future project is led by Prof. Brett Bryan and Climateworks in collaboration with CSIRO. This project aims to further develop the LUTO model and to provide pathways towards sustainable environmental and food futures for the Australian agricultural landscape. In this Advances in Biodiversity Modelling talk, Carla will share some of the biodiversity modelling which she conducted as a part of the Land Use Future project. This involved working with the CliMAS team at JCU to update MaxEnt models with CMIP6 climate data and scenarios. The outcome of this modelling has resulted in the construction of specific-level data to use with the LUTO2.0 as both input data, as well as in the environmental accounts.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/p.bal_.png" alt="Payal Bal" class="wp-image-47653"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="ana-belgun-data61">Payal Bal | University of Melbourne</h3>



<p>Payal Bal is currently based at the Quantitative and Applied Ecology Group at The University of Melbourne, where she works on developing models to assess the global impacts of socioeconomic trends on biodiversity and on assessing the national-level impacts of bushfires on Australian invertebrate species. During her doctoral research at The University of Queensland, she applied decision analysis and structured decision-making approaches to evaluate monitoring strategies for conservation. She has previously worked on modelling spatial vegetation patterns to develop indicators of ecosystem collapse; on developing methods of abundance estimation for biodiversity from distance sampling; and on studying the human–elephant conflict in India.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Webinar-moderator-Martin.png" alt="Martin Westgate" class="wp-image-45781"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="want-more">Want more?</h2>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 05:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter November 2022]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fv24jl/202ad5d9fa1b5d465f11542bf8d2f1f1"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/11/newsletter-nov22-807x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-47627" width="438" height="554"/></a></figure>



<p>    <a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fv24jl/202ad5d9fa1b5d465f11542bf8d2f1f1">ALA Newsletter November 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Welcome to the November 2022 edition of our newsletter</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/welcome-to-the-november-2022-edition-of-our-newsletter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 03:44:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47517</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to our November newsletter]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-thumbnail is-style-rounded"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="150" height="150" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/A57I6674-150x150.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47518"/><figcaption>Dr. Andre Zerger &#8211; Atlas of Living Australia Director</figcaption></figure>



<p>In this issue, we are pleased to present you with our Year in Review for 2021-22. Our Year in Review showcases ALA’s highlights, and reflects on the fundamental contribution made by our partners in supporting our mission. 2021-22 was an important year for the ALA, highlighted by some innovative new capability releases including <a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/">ALA Labs</a>, our work with partner NCRIS facilities to establish and launch <a href="https://ecoassets.org.au/">EcoAssets</a>, and the inaugural launch of the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>. Last year was also a time of significant team growth for the ALA and we now have staff in six  capital cities working with our partners, our projects and supporting our applications and systems. Having a national team has been a welcome by-product of some of the constraints imposed upon us over the past few years. Finally, doing justice to the breadth of research we enable in any year is always a challenge, but we’ve showcased four stellar examples of how a national biodiversity data infrastructure enables Australian science. We hope you enjoy reading our 2021-22 story as much as we’ve enjoyed building it.</p>



<p>I was recently privileged to represent the Australian delegation at the Governing Board meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) held for the first time in person in three years in Brussels, but also supporting a hybrid model. It was a great opportunity to connect with people we only ever see virtually. It&#8217;s nice to see the shared challenges, understand where our partners are heading strategically and benchmark ALA’s approach both technically and strategically. The global context is different to ours but nevertheless, we run a federated data infrastructure built on strong relationships across many sectors, so we learn so much at these events. An additional highlight for me was attending a one-day symposium hosted by GBIF and the European Biodiversa+ program called Data Beyond Borders that explored the role data infrastructure can play in supporting major national research and policy programs. This is clearly one of the next frontiers for capabilities such as ALA, and our partners in the NCRIS program.</p>



<p>The GBIF experience has affirmed the importance of ALA’s international role, and the opportunities this affords moving forward. Our delegation concluded the meeting with a successful nomination to host the 2023 Governing Board Meeting in Canberra – it’s been almost 20 years since Australia played this role and we are excited to welcome our international partners in 2023.</p>



<p>It&#8217;s been some years since we’ve all travelled and engaged in person, but our team have been re-energised by this year’s conference season. This has included our recent participation in eResearch Australasia in Brisbane, remote participation in the TDWG international meeting, GBIF in Europe, and in-person participation at the Ecological Society of Australia conference in Wollongong in November. I’d like to conclude by acknowledging the groups and individuals that do such an amazing job designing, coordinating, and running conferences to support our sector.&nbsp; We appreciate the work you do! We hope you enjoy our November edition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sneak peek of our new API portal</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/sneak-peek-of-our-new-api-portal/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 05:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47573</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’ve just released a new API gateway to access our APIs: docs.ala.org.au! Over 130 API endpoints have been migrated across to Swagger in a beta release, and we’re working on making more available very soon. ALA is passionate about empowering and supporting great research, so we’ve released APIs which were only used internally in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>We’ve just released a new API gateway to access our APIs: <a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/">docs.ala.org.au</a>! Over 130 API endpoints have been migrated across to Swagger in a beta release, and we’re working on making more available very soon.</p>



<p>ALA is passionate about empowering and supporting great research, so we’ve released APIs which were only used internally in the past. You can now use these in your work to access our open-source data more easily and feed into downstream analyses using your own system. We can’t wait for you to try them out and let us know what you think!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/API-portal.png" alt="software developer coding at a computer" class="wp-image-47544" width="597" height="499" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/API-portal.png 940w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/API-portal-300x251.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 597px) 100vw, 597px" /></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="faqs"><strong>FAQs</strong></h3>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="what-about-security"><strong>What about security?</strong></h4>



<p>The new portal will increase security for both ALA and you, our user. By moving to JSON Web Tokens (JWT), we’re able to open up access to previously unreleased APIs.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="jwt-tokens-but-isnt-ala-providing-access-to-open-data"><strong>JWT tokens? But isn’t ALA providing access to open data?</strong></h4>



<p>Yes, we still are! (And we’re still free to use too).</p>



<p>Most of our APIs&nbsp;<strong>do not</strong>&nbsp;require authentication and can be accessed freely as documented in the relevant Swagger specifications found at&nbsp;<a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/">docs.ala.org.au</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the protected APIs (such as sensitive or private data), you’ll need a&nbsp;JWT, which can be generated via a Client ID and Client Secret&nbsp;– let us know if you require this and we can assist.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="whats-happening-to-the-existing-api-portal"><strong>What’s happening to the existing API portal?</strong></h4>



<p>While we are in the process of migrating more APIs across, the <a href="https://api.ala.org.au/">existing ALA API portal</a> will still be fully available and everything will be backwards compatible.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="still-have-questions"><strong>Still have questions?</strong></h4>



<p>See our updated support article: <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000261502-ala-for-developers-how-to-access-ala-apis">ALA for developers, how to access ALA APIs</a> for technical tips on working with the new portal.</p>



<p>Finally, we’d love to hear from you! If you come across any issues, need help, or have questions or feedback about the new portal, feel free to reach out to us on <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="the-tl-dr-summary"><strong>The TL; DR summary:</strong></h3>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="whats-changed"><strong>What’s changed?</strong></h4>



<ul><li>New ALA API portal with a new URL: <a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/">docs.ala.org.au</a></li><li>More API endpoints now available, and more coming soon</li><li>Increased security</li><li><a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">Contact us</a> for an authorisation key</li></ul>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="what-hasnt-changed"><strong>What hasn’t changed?</strong></h4>



<ul><li>ALA and our APIs are still <em>open-source</em> and <em>free </em>to use</li><li>The <a href="https://api.ala.org.au/">existing API portal</a> will still be available while we complete the migration</li><li>We’re still here to help if you need assistance: <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen.png" alt="screenshot of the new ALA API docs portal" class="wp-image-47564" width="682" height="710" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen.png 820w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen-288x300.png 288w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen-768x800.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" /></a></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Are you sitting on camera trap data?</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/are-you-sitting-on-camera-trap-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 23:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47426</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WildObs would like to hear about your camera trap work!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="202" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-1024x202.png" alt="green banner reading &quot;WildObs Australia&quot; with a picture of a dingo, a wallaby, a kangaroo and a cassowary. " class="wp-image-47427" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-1024x202.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-300x59.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-768x152.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-1536x303.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs.png 1752w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>WildObs banner (TERN)</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p>Our friends at <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.tern.org.au/wildobs/" target="_blank">WildObs</a> are conducting a review of camera trapping in Australia. This review will help establish a useful synthesis centre devoted to curating vertebrate data. The team are seeking metadata from camera trapping surveys to assist in the project and are offering co-authorship upon receipt of data.</p>



<p>The aim of the project is to generate a modern snapshot of<em> where</em>, <em>how </em>and <em>who</em> is carrying out surveys, including habitats, target species and methods (both deployment and analysis). The project and participant information sheets are below, with a deadline of <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">15 November 2022</span></strong> for data submissions.<br><br>To participate, please see the below three actions:<br>&nbsp;1) <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://tinyurl.com/3bu89jta" target="_blank">Complete the questionnaire</a>, including the consent form on the first page.&nbsp;<br>&nbsp;2) <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://tinyurl.com/457cc6cm" target="_blank">Add basic metadata</a> from your camera trapping surveys<br>&nbsp;3) <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://tinyurl.com/32r5m6c6" target="_blank">Enter your name and affiliation</a> for co-authorship<br><br>For more information, contact Tom Bruce (<a href="mailto:tom.bruce@uq.edu.au">tom.bruce@uq.edu.au</a>) or Matthew Luskin (<a href="mailto:mluskin@uq.edu.au">mluskin@uq.edu.au</a>).<br></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><a href="http://www.tern.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="77" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/TERN-logo-1-300x77.png" alt="TERN logo with map of Australia" class="wp-image-47433" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/TERN-logo-1-300x77.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/TERN-logo-1.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
