<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 04:17:42 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.3.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Elevating ALA’s Data Security with OpenID Connect</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/elevating-alas-data-security-with-openid-connect/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2023 04:17:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48865</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As Australia’s national biodiversity data infrastructure, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is committed to providing reliable and secure data access to our users. In line with this commitment, we are excited to announce our transition to OpenID Connect (OIDC) authentication, which will help to streamline the process for accessing data within the ALA across [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" width="1024" height="223" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-1024x223.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48871" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-1024x223.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-300x65.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-768x167.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner-1536x335.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/infrastructure-update-banner.png 1867w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>As Australia’s national biodiversity data infrastructure, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is committed to providing reliable and secure data access to our users. In line with this commitment, we are excited to announce our transition to OpenID Connect (OIDC) authentication, which will help to streamline the process for accessing data within the ALA across multiple platforms.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="what-is-oidc">What is OIDC?</h2>



<p>With OIDC, you can log in to multiple platforms using a single set of sign-in credentials while ensuring that your personal information is secure and private.</p>



<p>OIDC is an identity layer built on top of the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://oauth.net/2/" target="_blank">OAuth 2.0</a> protocol. It&#8217;s designed to facilitate secure authentication and single sign-on (SSO) across different applications and services. If you’d like to read more about how OIDC works with OAuth 2.0, see OpenID Foundation&#8217;s article on <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://openid.net/developers/how-connect-works/" target="_blank">how OpenID Connect works</a><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://openid.net/developers/how-connect-works/" target="_blank">.</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-1024x858.png" alt="the layers of how OIDC works. when a HTTP request is sent, OAuth2.0 checks for authorisation access permissions, and OIDC checks for user identity" class="wp-image-48868" style="width:633px;height:531px" width="633" height="531" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-1024x858.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-300x251.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-768x644.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1-1536x1288.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/OIDC-1.png 1880w" sizes="(max-width: 633px) 100vw, 633px" /></figure>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="why-oidc">Why OIDC?</h2>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="enhanced-security"><strong>Enhanced Security</strong></h3>



<p>One of the key drivers behind ALA&#8217;s adoption of OpenID Connect (OIDC) is its ability to enhance data security.</p>



<p>OIDC operates by employing secure tokens in the background to validate a user&#8217;s identity. These tokens are designed to be short-lived and encrypted, ensuring that your credentials remain protected and reducing the potential for unauthorised access or data breaches.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="seamless-user-experience"><strong>Seamless User Experience</strong></h3>



<p>We’re committed to improving your experience across the ALA site; while this includes features like navigation, readability and look and feel, it also relates to login experience and performance. OIDC enhances our current SSO capabilities, allowing you to log in once to access multiple services without repeatedly entering your credentials.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="federated-sign-in"><strong>Federated sign-in</strong></h3>



<p>OIDC also enhances federated identity services. This means that you can continue to leverage your existing accounts from trusted identity providers such as the <a href="https://aaf.edu.au/">Australian Access Federation</a> (AAF), eliminating the need to create another username and password – making it quicker and easier to access the ALA for existing AAF users.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="scalability-and-integration"><strong>Scalability and Integration</strong></h3>



<p>As the number of records in the ALA grows, we ensure that our systems are flexible and scalable. OIDC allows us to integrate with a variety of web applications and evolve alongside other technical advancements.</p>



<p>Collaboration is also a big part of what we do at the ALA, so we can continue to make even more data findable and accessible. With the growing adoption of OIDC, integration is made easier with our data partners and other collaborators. For example, we are working with <a href="https://www.tern.org.au/">TERN</a> to integrate OIDC, making it quicker and easier for our <a href="https://fieldcapture.ala.org.au/">MERIT</a> users to sign in and submit data to the MERIT system using the TERN Monitor application.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" class="wp-block-heading" id="summary">Summary</h2>



<p>The adoption of OIDC authentication represents a significant milestone in the ALA’s ongoing commitment to data security, performance, and user experience. We remain dedicated to staying at the forefront of technology to do so, and we look forward to continued growth and collaboration with our user community. The ALA has more exciting infrastructure and technology changes coming soon – watch this space!</p>



<p>If you would like to know more about how OIDC benefits your data access experience, please reach out at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="ALA adopts OpenID Connect (OIDC)" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rIpy_f1pHtM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>This is one bird to be cass-o-wary of!</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/this-is-one-bird-to-be-cass-o-wary-of/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 26 Sep 2023 00:37:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48809</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Celebrating #WorldCassowaryDay]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Err&#8230; is that a bird or a dinosaur?</p>



<p>Well, both (kind of)! We’re talking about the <a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/5fc1b9fe-ccdd-4c3a-adfc-6f6e5c5c396b">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em></a>), often described as one of the closest living relatives of dinosaurs.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-Tom-Hunt-CC-BY-NC-819x1024.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48810" style="width:1000px;height:1024px" width="1000" height="1024"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em>) adult. Photo Credit Tom Hunt CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p>These gigantic flightless birds (‘ratites’) occupy tropical areas of northern Australia and Papua New Guinea. Cassowaries are the second heaviest birds in the world (after ostriches), with females reaching a maximum weight of 55kgs and males up to 76kgs! They lay bright green eggs, with dads stepping up to be in charge of incubation and chick rearing. Once the eggs hatch, baby cassowaries can walk almost immediately with their strong back legs. Babies are not born with their signature black plumage, instead have banded yellow and brown striped patterning as chicks. </p>



<p></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="967" height="649" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-DHFischer-CC-BY-NC.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48811" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-DHFischer-CC-BY-NC.jpg 967w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-DHFischer-CC-BY-NC-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Southern-Cassowary-Casuarius-casuarius-Photo-Credit-DHFischer-CC-BY-NC-768x515.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 967px) 100vw, 967px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Southern Cassowary (<em>Casuarius casuarius</em>) chick. Photo Credit DHFischer CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Keep your distance</strong></p>



<p>You&#8217;ll often hear these big birds before you see them! Cassowaries are notorious for communicating through deep rumbles, hisses and grunting sounds. Cassowaries use various vocalisations to communicate through their dense rainforest habitats. If you hear a cassowary calling, make sure you keep your distance. Equipped with a razor-sharp beak, talons and a particularly territorial nature, cassowaries are more than capable of tearing through flesh if they feel threatened. </p>



<p><strong>Keystone species</strong></p>



<p>Cassowaries are ‘keystone species’ &#8211; species which has a disproportionately important role in their natural ecosystems. In rainforest habitats across northern QLD, cassowaries play a critical role in dispersing many native seeds through fragmented rainforest landscapes. Due to their large size, cassowaries can swallow fruits and other plants whole, digest the pulp and excrete seeds intact in dung piles (aka natural fertilisers). This ability to disperse large seeds helps to maintain healthy ecosystems by promoting vegetation regeneration.</p>



<p>To better illustrate how cassowaries support native plant dispersal across rainforest ecosystems, Callum and Shandiya from the ALA Science and Decision Support team have created an interactive map. The map shows 15 native plant species across the QLD wet tropics against cassowary records in the ALA!</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://cjwaite23.shinyapps.io/cassowary_app/" data-type="link" data-id="https://cjwaite23.shinyapps.io/cassowary_app/">Check out the interactive map!</a></strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://cjwaite23.shinyapps.io/cassowary_app/"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="534" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-1024x534.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-48855" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-1024x534.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-300x156.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-768x400.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-1536x801.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-2048x1068.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/09/Cassowary-day-1920x1001.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></a></figure>



<p>To learn more about native seeds in tropical areas, check out the <a href="https://www.ath.org.au/">Australian Topical Herbarium</a>.</p>



<p>#WorldCassowaryDay</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA National Science Week 2023 recordings</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-national-science-week-2023-recordings/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 25 Aug 2023 00:42:56 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48740</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[To celebrate National Science Week 2023, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) hosted three free virtual events. Our events aimed to ignite curiosity, foster learning, and deepen connection with biological sciences and the environment. Whether you were able to join us on the day and want to catch-up on the content, or if you weren&#8217;t [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>To celebrate National Science Week 2023, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) hosted three free virtual events. Our events aimed to ignite curiosity, foster learning, and deepen connection with biological sciences and the environment.</p>



<p>Whether you were able to join us on the day and want to catch-up on the content, or if you weren&#8217;t able to make it, we&#8217;ve got you covered with recordings of our three events.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>15th August 2023 &#8211; {galah} 101 Beginners guide</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Workshop: galah 101 Beginner&#039;s guide – National Science Week – 15 Aug 2023" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8YY63sqKfEM?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Check out the slides from Dr Dax Kellie and Dr Amanda Buyan <a href="https://acbuyan.quarto.pub/galah-101-beginners-guide/">here</a></p>



<p>Are you interested in getting the most out of data in the ALA? We’ve developed the ALA {galah} tool to&nbsp;enable users to deep-dive and transform species occurrence information. Whether you want to locate and download species records, investigate taxonomic information and associated media such as images or sounds, or restrict queries to certain taxa or locations, {galah} can do it all! This tool has been developed for both the R-Studio and Python coding languages.</p>



<p>Our beginner-friendly workshop introduces a step-by-step introduction to using both {galah} for R-Studio and Python</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>16th August 2023 &#8211; All is F.A.I.R. in open science and data</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar: All is F.A.I.R in open science &amp; data – National Science Week – 16 Aug 2023" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Dp_jF8Zxyxc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Open science is the practice of making scientific knowledge, research and information accessible. As Australia’s national biodiversity data aggregator, we explore why open science is so important to delivering strong biodiversity outcomes.</p>



<p>Hear ALA team members Ely Wallis, Peggy Newman and Dax Kellie discuss:</p>



<ul>
<li>How the F.A.I.R. (findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable) principles are used through copyright and licencing in the ALA</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>How the ALA supports open science through its data infrastructure and services</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li>How open science facilitates transparent, robust research.</li>
</ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>17th August 2023 &#8211; Maximising your metadata for citizen science</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar – Maximising your metadata for citizen science – National Science Week – 17 Aug 2023" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XU-62h4Q-Zs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>Citizen science is an accessible gateway for anybody to engage in science regardless of age, location or demographic. Integrated citizen science apps take in millions of species occurrence records each year, which are then verified before being fed through to the ALA to become open and accessible data.</p>



<p>Hear from Dr Erin Roger and Cam Slatyer from the ALA, Thomas Mesaglio from iNaturalist and Dr Jasmin Packer from the FungiMap Project discuss what makes a great species observation record, and learn tips and tricks for collecting the best quality metadata – data about data. Higher quality metadata (attributes like location, images, date of collection, etc.) helps to paint a more detailed picture of Australia’s biodiversity. More accurate metadata also helps to identify native vs. invasive species more readily for better biosecurity monitoring. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Get involved in the Threatened Species Bake Off 2023!</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/get-involved-in-the-threatened-species-bake-off-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 06:36:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48646</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Help raise the profile of Australia’s most threatened biodiversity]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="341" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/08/Landscape-banner-headings-1-1024x341.png" alt="Blue tiles that reads threatened species bake off 2023 with a picture of a velvet worm, a cake of a phasmid and a green mushroom" class="wp-image-48689" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/08/Landscape-banner-headings-1-1024x341.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/08/Landscape-banner-headings-1-300x100.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/08/Landscape-banner-headings-1-768x256.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/08/Landscape-banner-headings-1.png 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Now in its seventh year, the Threatened Species Bake Off hosted by the <a href="https://www.dcceew.gov.au/environment/biodiversity/threatened/commissioner/tsbakeoff">Office of the Threatened Species Commissioner </a>(part of the <a href="https://www.dcceew.gov.au/environment/biodiversity/threatened/commissioner"></a><a href="https://www.dcceew.gov.au/">Department of Climate Change, Energy, the Environment and Water</a>) is an excellent opportunity to raise the profile of Australia’s threatened species! </p>



<p>With hundreds of entries each year, there’s no shortage of love and passion for the event, but how can we make sure less-well-known species are also represented in the bake off?</p>



<p>Unfortunately, in Australia, there are more than 1,700 threatened species listed, with this number growing every year. The Atlas of Living Australia has put together a list of underrepresented species to help give you inspiration to share the love across the species represented in the bake off entries this year! </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/Fungi-Friday-1-1024x577.png" alt="" class="wp-image-48656" width="1000" height="563" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/Fungi-Friday-1-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/Fungi-Friday-1-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/Fungi-Friday-1-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/Fungi-Friday-1-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/Fungi-Friday-1.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Entries from previous years include: &nbsp;‘Moss, lichens, fungi &amp; Gippsland Giant Earthworm’ (credit Holly) and ‘Margaret River Burrowing Crayfish&nbsp;<em>(Engaewa pseudoreducta)’</em>&nbsp;(credit Linette).</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>How you can get involved:</strong></p>



<p><em>Note entries are open 24 August &#8211; 24 September with Threatened Species Day on 7 September. </em></p>



<ol type="1">
<li>Choose an Australian threatened species to bake! Check out our list of species that are underrepresented in data records <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1aBzHvM-ycEAsUYOHvMoh0pM4eMBvsOauAbn--nLPTYU/edit?usp=sharing">here</a>.</li>



<li>Get creative with your baking! It doesn’t have to be a sweet treat if you’re more of a savoury connoisseur- try to capture the likeness of your chosen species the best you can.</li>



<li>Take a picture and upload it to Facebook, Twitter or Instagram with the hashtag #TSBakeOff2023 and tag the Threatened Species Commissioner. If you’re unable to access social media, you can still submit your entry by sending your picture to <a href="mailto:tsbakeoff@environment.gov.au">tsbakeoff@dcceew.gov.au</a>.</li>
</ol>



<p>Each year, a panel of judges will assess the entry to the bake off across the following categories: Early Learners Award, Children’s Award, Open Category, People’s Choice, Schools Award and Organisation Award.  </p>



<p>You can further help threatened species in Australia by engaging in citizen science to help fill the gaps in species records across the country. One of the most effective tools for protecting our native biodiversity is having access to information that shows where species are and how their populations are changing over time. Taxonomic groups like invertebrates, fungi and plants are underrepresented in species occurrence records, therefore the number of identified threatened species from these groups is thought to be much higher than current reported figures. Click the link to learn more about <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000261577-citizen-science">submitting citizen science species occurrence records</a> to support Australian biodiversity sciences.</p>


]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Webinar: Safeguarding Sensitive Species</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-safeguarding-sensitive-species/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 03:00:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48630</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hosted by the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), this webinar brings together expert speakers from three organisations to explore the challenges, management strategies, and data sensitivities used to protect Australia’s rarest and most vulnerable species. Restricted Access Species Data &#8211; often known as ‘sensitive species data’ – is information about biodiversity with features that mean [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Hosted by the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), this webinar brings together expert speakers from three organisations to explore the challenges, management strategies, and data sensitivities used to protect Australia’s rarest and most vulnerable species. </p>



<p>Restricted Access Species Data &#8211; often known as ‘sensitive species data’ – is information about biodiversity with features that mean there are reasons for withholding the data from public view or modifying it before it is made public. An example of why obscuring species information may be necessary is because exposing a species’ exact location could risk harm, exploitation, or poaching. Restricted Access Species Data are needed for conservation management, decision-making, and research to implement strategies to best protect ‘sensitive species.’</p>



<div style="height:11px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar: Safeguarding Sensitive Species – 5 July 2023" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tdqYFDEXkLw?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEST, Wednesday 5 July 2023, with 195 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="speakers">Speakers</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/philip-gleeson.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48634"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Philip Gleeson | NSW Department of Planning &amp; Environment</h3>



<p>Philip Gleeson is Senior Wildlife Data Officer for the NSW Department of Planning and Environment. Philip has worked on BioNet Atlas, the NSW government’s primary repository of biodiversity data since 2001. He was part of the development team that turned it from an internal database to a website providing public and secure login access to external clients in 2011. It was through that development that the department was able to implement its Sensitive Species Data Policy which had been developed following 5 years of internal discussion and negotiation. In order to maintain his understanding of the biodiversity data he manages, Philip has participated in a range of survey programs across the department and is currently involved in the survey and mapping of two cliff-dwelling endemic plants of the Blue Mountains where he now resides.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/rachel-swain.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48635"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Rachel Swain | BirdLife Australia</h3>



<p>Rachel Swain is the Citizen Science Engagement Manager at BirdLife Australia and has a background in data analysis, engineering and acoustic monitoring. As a strong advocate for citizen science, Rachel is committed to ensuring the Birdata community is an exciting and inclusive space that delivers the best conservation impact for Australian birds. When not working with the Birdata community, Rachel can usually be found trekking through the great outdoors, whether on foot or by bike, trying to spot as many birds as she can along the way.&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/golo-maurer.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48636"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="ana-belgun-data61">Golo Maurer | BirdLife Australia</h3>



<p>Golo Maurer has been involved in ecological research and conservation for over 20 years both in Australia and overseas with over 50 peer-reviewed publications. He joined BirdLife Australia in 2010 and now leads BirdLife&#8217;s Citizen Science Program and BirdLife&#8217;s Indigenous engagement work. In his role, Golo helps ensure that the 22 million bird records in Birdata work for conservation and that Birdata empowers and inspires thousands of citizen scientists across Australia to make their birding count. When Golo does not watch birds or work to save them, he sleeps, compiling a dream list with 363 species recorded to date in this most challenging realm of birding.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/07/helen-eniskat.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-48637"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="ana-belgun-data61">Helen Ensikat | WA Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions</h3>



<p>Helen is the manager of Western Australia’s Biodiversity Information Office, hosted within the Department of Biodiversity, Conservation and Attractions. She has a background in public sector data policy, evaluation, and regulation, and has been involved in the development of Western Australia’s Open Data Policy, and forthcoming Privacy and Responsible Information Sharing reforms. She and her team at BIO are working to make curated biodiversity data from all environment-related sectors more discoverable, accessible, and useful.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Webinar-moderator-Martin.png" alt="Martin Westgate" class="wp-image-45781"/></figure></div>


<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin&nbsp;Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the&nbsp;Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific&nbsp;information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin&nbsp;is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="want-more">Want more?</h2>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter June 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/newsletter/ala-newsletter-june-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 01:25:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48573</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Check out the ALA June 2023 Newsletter.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p id="block-e6556f64-c2e0-49e7-b903-7825bd5b688f">Check out the ALA <a href="http://mailchi.mp/ala/june-2023-newsletter" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">June 2023 Newsletter</a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="http://mailchi.mp/ala/june-2023-newsletter" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="602" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ALA-newsletter-june-2023-602x1024.png" alt="ALA's June newsletter - header includes the ALA logo next to a yellow frog. Below that includes the heading 'June 2023 Newsletter' with a welcome message." class="wp-image-48575" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ALA-newsletter-june-2023-602x1024.png 602w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ALA-newsletter-june-2023-176x300.png 176w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ALA-newsletter-june-2023.png 658w" sizes="(max-width: 602px) 100vw, 602px" /></a></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Protecting Australia’s restricted access plants and animals through better data access </title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/protecting-australias-restricted-access-plants-and-animals-through-better-data-access/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 05:08:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48408</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Launching the National Framework for the Sharing of Restricted Access Species Data and the Restricted Access Species Data Service for Australia]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.rasd.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">National Framework for the Sharing of Restricted Access Species Data</a> provides a best practice guide for the custodians and users of species data that is restricted.</p>



<p>The development of the National Framework streamlines the process of accessing, sharing and managing restricted access species data across Australia, leading to better environmental management and improved species outcomes.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="578" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/RASD_Headline-Image-v21-1024x578.png" alt="Green caterpillar on a blue background with the ALA, ARDC and NCRIS logos" class="wp-image-48569" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/RASD_Headline-Image-v21-1024x578.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/RASD_Headline-Image-v21-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/RASD_Headline-Image-v21-768x434.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/RASD_Headline-Image-v21-1536x867.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/RASD_Headline-Image-v21.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><em>Caption: Sensitive species Australian Atlas Moth (Attacus wardi), photo credit James P. Tuttle CC BY NC&nbsp;</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Historically, the difficulty of accessing restricted data on species has created barriers for research, environmental <a>assessmen</a>t and conservation. Data on species has been modified, withheld or shared based on inconsistent organisational polices. The <a>National Framework </a>is the first of its kind, jointly developed by the Atlas of Living Australia, the Australian Research Data Commons, all the government environmental agencies in Australia, herbaria, fauna collections, EcoCommons Australia and the Western Australian Biodiversity Science Institute.</p>



<p>Sharing the precise locations of restricted<a> access </a>species potentially risks disturbance, harm or exploitation. Therefore, access to some species information is limited, accessible only to data custodians and approved data users.</p>



<p>The National Framework outlines the principles to guide data custodians and users in the sharing of restricted access species data responsibly and appropriately. By adopting a nationally consistent evidence-based approach to managing restricted access species data, the National Framework aim to:</p>



<ul>
<li>promote responsible data-sharing practices</li>



<li>give data custodians the confidence to safely share restricted access species data</li>



<li>assist data custodians to maintain the consistency and quality of data.</li>
</ul>



<p><em>“BirdLife Australia has long upheld a restricted access policy for sensitive species data as a basis for our citizen science work. This gives contributors the confidence that sharing their data will not put species at risk, while still allowing for its use in conservation. We are excited to now have a nationally consistent framework for sensitive species data sharing, which will massively increase the use and impact of bird and other species data in science and conservation” said</em> Dr Golo Maurer, BirdLife Citizen Science Program Leader.</p>



<p><strong>A Restricted Access Species Data Service (RASDS) for Australia</strong></p>



<p>The new RASDS allows researchers and other trusted data users to request restricted access species data from all participating data custodians in Australia via a central point. &nbsp;The service allows data custodians a way of managing and storing request workflows.</p>



<p><em>“RASDS seeks to remove a major barrier to the flow of species data by standardising the way we describe and exchange sensitive species data</em>” said Ron Avery, STL Biodiversity Information Systems Science, Economics and Insight Division, NSW Dept&nbsp;of Planning and Environment.</p>



<p><strong>Partners:</strong></p>



<p>These products were developed as part of a collaborative project between the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/#tab_pane-C">Atlas of Living Australia</a>, <a href="https://ardc.edu.au">Australian Research Data Commons</a> (ARDC), the Australian Government, state and territory governments, conservation agencies, museums, and herbaria, <a href="https://www.ecocommons.org.au/">EcoCommons</a> and the <a href="https://wabsi.org.au/">Western Australian Biodiversity Science Institute</a>.</p>



<p>To find out more, visit the <a href="https://www.rasd.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RASD webpage</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s Update &#8211; June 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-update-june-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 05:13:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48521</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Hear about the latest ALA news and events.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/02/Andre-cropped-218x300.jpg" alt="Profile shot of Andre Zerger" class="wp-image-48178" width="225" height="318"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Dr Andre Zerger, ALA Director</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Welcome to the June 2023 edition of our ALA newsletter.</p>



<p>Biological collections play an important role in understanding trends in biodiversity life sciences. With advances in genomics, imaging, artificial intelligence and machine learning, more information can be obtained from physical-biological specimens than has ever been possible before. </p>



<p>The ALA has been proud to play a key role in ensuring data emerging from Australia’s collections is made findable, accessible, interoperable, and reusable globally. Recently, the ALA was pleased to partner with our key stakeholders across the museums, collections and herbaria sectors to host a national workshop in Canberra. The workshop &#8211; <em>‘Towards a national approach to biological collections’ </em>– brought together experts to explore current capabilities, emerging research drivers and key components that are required to support biological collections in Australia. Having our partners from across the nation meet together <a>highlighted the maturity and cohesiveness of our sector</a>, as well as the opportunities for international collaboration and improving data connections to deliver greater scientific benefit. We look forward to continuing collaborations to further advance work in this space at a national level. T<a>his will be pivotal in informing future priorities and co-investment pathways aligning with the recently released National Research Infrastructure Roadmap. </a></p>



<p><a>In addition </a>to a focus on collections for the rest of the year, we look forward to further engaging with the broader scientific community through multiple <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/where-to-find-the-atlas-of-living-australia-this-year/">conferences</a> such as the Ecological Society of Australia event in Darwin and the Biodiversity Information Standards (TDWG) event in Hobart in the coming months. You’ll also find an exciting line-up of virtual events to support <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/national-science-week-2023/">National Science Week </a>in August which I encourage you to register for participation.</p>



<p>We hope you enjoy our June newsletter.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Science Week 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/national-science-week-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 04:42:43 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48527</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’re gearing up for National Science Week (12-20 August 2023). The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is proud to be hosting three free virtual events! Hear from STEM leaders about the importance of open science and how we practise this in the ALA, learn the basics of how to use ALA’s {galah} tool with demonstrations [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-43-1024x577.png" alt="Grey banner with a graphic of a person using AR. Text reads register for our ALA events with the ALA and National Science Wek logos." class="wp-image-48528" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-43-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-43-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-43-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-43-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-43.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>We’re gearing up for National Science Week (12-20 August 2023). The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) is proud to be hosting three <strong>free</strong> virtual events!</p>



<p>Hear from STEM leaders about the importance of open science and how we practise this in the ALA, learn the basics of how to use ALA’s {galah} tool with demonstrations of both the R-Studio and Python versions, and find out how to collect better metadata through citizen science!</p>



<p><strong>Make sure you register for the events and submit your questions ahead of time to make the most out of each session.</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/19-1024x1024.png" alt="Green and white text with a graphic of a person with a pigeon on their head that reads galah 101 beginners guide. " class="wp-image-48534" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/19-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/19-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/19-150x150.png 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/19-768x768.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/19.png 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://events.csiro.au/Events/2023/June/16/ALA-NSW-galah-101-Beginners-guide"><strong>Webinar<strong> </strong>Event: ALA National Science Week: {galah} 101 – Beginner’s guide</strong> </a></p>



<p><strong>Tuesday 15th August 2023, 1-2PM AEST</strong></p>



<p>Are you interested in getting more out of data in the ALA? We’ve developed the ALA {galah} tool to&nbsp;enable users to deep-dive and transform species occurrence information. Whether you want to locate and download species records, investigate taxonomic information and associated media such as images or sounds, or restrict queries to certain taxa or locations, {galah} can do it all! This tool has been developed for both the R-Studio and Python coding languages.</p>



<p>At this beginner-friendly workshop, Dax Kellie and Amanda Buyan will take you through a step-by-step introduction to using both {galah} for R-Studio and Python.</p>



<p>If you’re already an advanced coder or have a specific question, you can submit your questions ahead of time for the Q&amp;A at the end of the session.</p>



<p>*Please note we strongly recommend that you download&nbsp;<a href="https://posit.co/download/rstudio-desktop/">R-Studio</a>&nbsp;(from this link) and/or&nbsp;<a href="https://sparkbyexamples.com/python/install-anaconda-jupyter-notebook/">Python</a>&nbsp;(following the instructions below) ahead of this session.</p>



<p><strong>ALA {galah} Python Package download instructions:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Download&nbsp;<a href="https://sparkbyexamples.com/python/install-anaconda-jupyter-notebook/">Jupyter Notebook</a>,&nbsp;which allows you access to Anaconda.</li>



<li>Launch &amp; locate “Anaconda Navigator”.</li>



<li>From the main screen of Anaconda Navigator, locate “Environments”.</li>



<li>Click the “Create” button to create a new environment, selecting Python as the software.</li>



<li>Click the “play” button and then click “open with terminal”.</li>



<li>Run command “pip install galah-python.&#8221;</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Submit your questions ahead of time to&nbsp;</strong><a href="mailto:communications@ala.org.au"><strong>communications@ala.org.au</strong></a>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/All-is-FAIR-in-open-science-and-data-1024x1024.png" alt="blue and white graphic with a person holding a plant that reads all is fair in open science and data" class="wp-image-48530" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/All-is-FAIR-in-open-science-and-data-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/All-is-FAIR-in-open-science-and-data-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/All-is-FAIR-in-open-science-and-data-150x150.png 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/All-is-FAIR-in-open-science-and-data-768x768.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/All-is-FAIR-in-open-science-and-data.png 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://events.csiro.au/Events/2023/June/16/ALA-NSW-All-is-FAIR">Webinar Event: ALA National Science Week: All is F.A.I.R in open science &amp; data</a></strong></p>



<p><strong>Wednesday 16th August 2023, 1-2PM AEST</strong></p>



<p>Open science is the practice of making scientific knowledge, research and information accessible. As Australia’s national biodiversity data aggregator, we explore why open science is so important to delivering strong biodiversity outcomes.</p>



<p>Hear ALA team members Ely Wallis, Peggy Newman and Dax Kellie discuss:</p>



<ul>
<li>How the F.A.I.R. (findable, accessible, interoperable and reusable) principles are used through copyright and licencing in the ALA</li>



<li>How the ALA supports open science through its data infrastructure and services</li>



<li>How open science facilitates transparent, robust research.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Submit your questions ahead of time to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:communications@ala.org.au"><strong>communications@ala.org.au</strong></a></strong>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="1024" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-Instagram-Post-Square-16-1024x1024.png" alt="Burnt orange and white graphic of a person diving with an octopus that reads maximising your metadata for citizen science" class="wp-image-48531" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-Instagram-Post-Square-16-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-Instagram-Post-Square-16-300x300.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-Instagram-Post-Square-16-150x150.png 150w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-Instagram-Post-Square-16-768x768.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-Instagram-Post-Square-16.png 1080w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://events.csiro.au/Events/2023/June/16/ALA-NSW-Maximising-your-metadata">Webinar Event: ALA National Science Week: Maximising your metadata for citizen science</a></strong> </p>



<p><strong>Thursday 17th August 2023, 1-2PM AEST</strong></p>



<p>Citizen science is an accessible gateway for anybody to engage in science regardless of age, location or demographic. Integrated citizen science apps take in millions of species occurrence records each year, which are then verified before being fed through to the ALA to become open and accessible data.</p>



<p>In this workshop, learn from industry experts about what makes a great species observation record, and learn tips and tricks for collecting the best quality&nbsp;metadata&nbsp; – data about data. Higher quality metadata (attributes like location, images, date of collection, etc.) helps to paint a more detailed picture of Australia’s biodiversity. More accurate metadata also helps to identify native vs. invasive species more readily for better biosecurity monitoring.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Submit your questions ahead of time to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:communications@ala.org.au"><strong>communications@ala.org.au</strong></a></strong>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Where to find the Atlas of Living Australia this year</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/where-to-find-the-atlas-of-living-australia-this-year/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2023 00:49:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=48500</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[With so many events happening in 2023, here's a list of where you'll find the Atlas of Living Australia!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-39-1024x577.png" alt="white spider sitting on purple flowers" class="wp-image-48512" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-39-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-39-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-39-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-39-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-39.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<p>Check out our 2023 Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) conference line-up below. We will continue to update our schedule throughout the year, so make sure you check back!</p>



<p><a href="http://esa2023.org.au/">Ecological Society of Australia conference</a> | Darwin | 3-7 July 2023</p>



<p>The ALA will be both sponsoring and attending ESA 2023, with team members facilitating the following sessions:<br>1. EcoAssets: streamlining access to data from Australian environmental research infrastructures (Shandiya Balasubramaniam)<br>2. How to make a sharable code workflow for reproducible and efficient science: Learnings from {galah} and ALA Labs (Dax Kellie).</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="157" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ESA-300x157.png" alt="Black and orange banner advertising ESA with a native mouse" class="wp-image-48501" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ESA-300x157.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ESA-1024x536.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ESA-768x402.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/ESA.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.icg2023.com.au/?gclid=EAIaIQobChMI-I2avaar_wIVBCdgCh3NaQeEEAAYASAAEgLr-vD_BwE">The XXIII<sup>rd</sup> <span style="font-size: revert; background-color: var(--bs-body-bg); color: var(--bs-body-color); font-family: var(--bs-body-font-family); font-weight: var(--bs-body-font-weight); text-align: var(--bs-body-text-align);">International Congress of Genetics conference</span></a><span style="font-size: revert; background-color: var(--bs-body-bg); color: var(--bs-body-color); font-family: var(--bs-body-font-family); font-weight: var(--bs-body-font-weight); text-align: var(--bs-body-text-align);"> | Melbourne | 16-21 July</span> 2023</p>



<p>The ALA will be attending this event and team members will be available at the Australian BioCommons booth.&nbsp; We will be introducing the Australian Reference Genome Atlas data app via a scientific poster and demonstrations of an early release of a demonstration product.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Genetics-conference-300x78.jpg" alt="Black banner with yellow text" class="wp-image-48502" style="width:300px;height:78px" width="300" height="78" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Genetics-conference-300x78.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Genetics-conference-1024x266.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Genetics-conference-768x200.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Genetics-conference.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://puliima.com/">PULiiMA Indigenous Language and Technology Conference</a> | Darwin | 21-25 August 2023</p>



<p>The ALA will be both sponsoring and attending the PULiiMA conference, with Nat Raisbeck Brown presenting the following sessions:<br>&#8211; Growing the Indigenous Ecological Knowledge Network for plants and animals <br>&#8211; Language as the key to growing reciprocity and respect between Indigenous peoples and the Australian science community<br>&#8211; Gadji Gadji Garden – creating safe spaces to collect, protect and share Indigenous language and knowledge about plants and animals<br>&#8211; Linking language and cross-cultural knowledge of animals and plants of South East Arnhem Land to Western science knowledge through the Atlas of Living Australia.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="131" height="99" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/PULiiMA.png" alt="three coloured leaves - green, red and yellow advertising the PULLiiMA conference" class="wp-image-48503"/></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.tdwg.org/conferences/2023/">Biodiversity Information Standards (<span style="font-size: revert; background-color: var(--bs-body-bg); color: var(--bs-body-color); font-family: var(--bs-body-font-family); font-weight: var(--bs-body-font-weight); text-align: var(--bs-body-text-align);">TDWG)</span></a><span style="font-size: revert; background-color: var(--bs-body-bg); color: var(--bs-body-color); font-family: var(--bs-body-font-family); font-weight: var(--bs-body-font-weight); text-align: var(--bs-body-text-align);"> | Hobart | 9-13 October 2023 </span></p>



<p>In partnership with CSIRO’s National Research Collections Australia (NRCA), the ALA will be hosting the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.tdwg.org/conferences/2023/">Biodiversity Information Standards TDWG</a>&nbsp;conference. TDWG sets and evolves international standards such as&nbsp;<a href="https://dwc.tdwg.org/">Darwin Core</a>&nbsp;that make the work that ALA and our partners do possible. In addition to TDWG’s focus on biodiversity informatics, science applications of biodiversity data will feature prominently at this conference.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Check out where to find the ALA team:</p>



<p><strong>Opening and closing: </strong></p>



<p><strong>Ely Wallis</strong> is the co-chair of the conference and is moderating the opening and closing sessions</p>



<p><strong>MONDAY 9 October</strong></p>



<p><strong>Niels Klazenga</strong>: The Catalogue of Life Data Package (CoLDP) and the Taxon Concept Standard (TCS): A Comparison <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.110965">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.110965</a> &nbsp;Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 12:45 PM &#8211; 01:00 PM (AEDT)</p>



<p>And <strong>Niels</strong> also: Improved Sharing and Linkage of Taxonomic Data with the Taxon Concept Standard (TCS) <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112045">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112045</a></p>



<p>Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 05:15 PM &#8211; 05:30 PM (AEDT)</p>



<p><strong>Simon Sherrin </strong>Insights into Delivering a Robust and Comprehensive Names Classification for a Living Atlas Using Diverse Taxonomic Sources <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.111331">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.111331</a> Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 03:01 PM &#8211; 03:15 PM</p>



<p>Jeff Christiansen and<strong> Kathryn Hall: </strong>Biodata Infrastructure within Australia and Beyond: Landscapes and horizons <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112274">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112274</a> Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 03:01 PM &#8211; 03:15 PM. The speaker will be Jeff</p>



<p>And <strong>Kathryn</strong> also: The Australian Reference Genome Atlas (ARGA): Finding, sharing and reusing Australian genomics data in an occurrence-driven context <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112129">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112129</a> Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 03:15 PM &#8211; 03:30 PM</p>



<p><strong>Peggy Newman</strong> Building Software for Hierarchical Events in Biodiversity Informatics <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.111770">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.111770</a> Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 03:30 PM &#8211; 03:45 PM (AEDT)</p>



<p><strong>Donald Hobern</strong> Global Lepidoptera Index: Progress and Issues with Developing a Comprehensive Global Checklist of Moths and Butterflies <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.111328">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.111328</a> Mon, Oct 09, 2023, 04:00 PM &#8211; 04:15 PM</p>



<p><strong>Tuesday 10 October</strong></p>



<p><strong>Nicole Kearney</strong>: &nbsp;Celebrating BHL Australia through the Eye of the (Tasmanian) Tiger&nbsp; <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112352">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112352</a> &nbsp;Tue, Oct 10, 2023, 09:01 AM &#8211; 09:15 AM (AEDT)</p>



<p><strong>Thursday 12 October</strong></p>



<p><strong>Peter Brenton </strong>Measuring Habitat Restoration using the Darwin and Event Cores: Australian examples powered by BioCollect <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112083">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112083</a>&nbsp; Thu, Oct 12, 2023, 11:01 AM &#8211; 11:15 AM</p>



<p><strong>Andrew Turley and Erin Roger</strong>: Invasions, Plagues, and Epidemics: The Atlas of Living Australia’s deep dive into biosecurity <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112127">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.7.112127</a> Thu, Oct 12, 2023, 11:15 AM &#8211; 11:30 AM (AEDT)</p>



<p><strong>Session organisers:</strong></p>



<p><strong>MONDAY 9 October</strong></p>



<p><strong>Peggy Newman</strong> with US colleagues Abby Benson and Steve Formel: SYM04 The CARE principles: Learning and growing as a data management community Monday 9 October 1130–1300</p>



<p><strong>Lee Belbin, </strong>Arthur Chapman PD01 Data quality: Lessons and directions (panel discussion) Monday 9 October 1130–1300</p>



<p><strong>Cameron Slatyer, </strong>Andrew Rodrigues,<strong> Tania Laity </strong>WKSH03 Handling restricted access data in an open data landscape (workshop) Monday 9 October 1700–1830</p>



<p>Olaf Bánki, Thomas Orrell,<strong> Donald Hobern </strong>SYM12 Improving the quality of taxonomic data publishing and list building Monday 9 October 1130–1300, 1500–1630 (2 sessions)</p>



<p>Chuck Cook, <strong>Kathryn Hall</strong>, Jeff Christiansen SYM10 Global biodata resources: A crucial infrastructure underpinning biodiversity research Monday 9 October 1500–1630</p>



<p><strong>Thursday 12 October</strong></p>



<p>Francisco Pando and <strong>Javier Molina </strong>SYM11 Combining biodiversity and environmental data for addressing scientific and societal questions Thursday 12 October 1100–1230</p>



<p><strong>Peggy Newman, Javier Molina</strong> and colleagues outside ALA Vicente J. Ruiz Jurado, Anne-Sophie Archambeau, Francisco Pando, Sophia Ratcliffe SYM07 Ten Years of the Living Atlases Thursday 12 October 1630–1815</p>



<p><strong>Erin Roger and Andrew Turley</strong>: &nbsp;SYM01 Biosecurity data: Why does it matter and how can access be facilitated? Thursday 12 October 1100–1230</p>



<p><strong>Kathryn Hall </strong>WKSH04 Working session to develop genomics-specific extensions with the Darwin Core event model (workshop) Thursday 12 October 1430–1600</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="132" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-300x132.jpg" alt="green and blue logo depicting Australian native animals in the shape of Australia for TDWG conference " class="wp-image-48506" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-300x132.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-1024x452.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient-768x339.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/BIS-TDWG-Logo-CMYK-Gradient.jpg 1478w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.biodiversity2023.com/">WA Biodiversity Conference 2023</a> <a>| Perth | 10-12 October 2023</a></p>



<p>Amanda Buyan from the ALA Science and Decision Support team will be facilitating 2x workshops on {galah} at this event.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="166" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/WA-Biodiversity-conference-300x166.png" alt="Numbat logo that reads The Biodiversity Conference 2023, listen to Country" class="wp-image-48516" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/WA-Biodiversity-conference-300x166.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/WA-Biodiversity-conference.png 602w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>



<p><a href="https://gb30.gbif.org/">GB30 &#8211; Global Biodiversity Information Standards</a> | Canberra | <span style="font-size: revert; background-color: var(--bs-body-bg); color: var(--bs-body-color); font-family: var(--bs-body-font-family); font-weight: var(--bs-body-font-weight); text-align: var(--bs-body-text-align);">15-20 October 2023</span></p>



<p>The ALA and our biological collections partners in CSIRO have successfully bid to host the 2023 meeting of the Governing Board in Australia. We welcome the opportunity to bring together international delegates to Canberra to share knowledge, data practises and biodiversity information together. </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="169" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-35-300x169.png" alt="cream coloured background with multiple native Australian animals and plants advertising GB30" class="wp-image-48508" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-35-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-35-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-35-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-35-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/Fungi-Friday-35.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>



<p><span style="font-size: revert; background-color: var(--bs-body-bg); color: var(--bs-body-color); font-family: var(--bs-body-font-family); font-weight: var(--bs-body-font-weight); text-align: var(--bs-body-text-align);"><a href="https://conference.eresearch.edu.au/">eResearch Australasia 2023</a> | Brisbane | 16-20 October 2023 </span></p>



<p>The ALA will be sponsoring eResearch Australasia, with a booth presence on the conference floor in collaboration with the Australian Reference Genome Atlas (ARGA). The ALA will also be giving a joint presentation with Amazon Web Services (AWS). </p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="169" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/eresearch-300x169.jpeg" alt="navy blue map of the world depicted in pixel art advertising eResearch conference" class="wp-image-48509" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/eresearch-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/06/eresearch.jpeg 726w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
