<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www-test.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 23:28:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.7.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>International Living Atlases: Australian software used across the globe</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/impact-stories/international-living-atlases-australian-software-used-across-the-globe/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Alex Horvat]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2021 23:27:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=44546</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia is a world leader in biodiversity data infrastructure. Software code originally developed by our Australian team is now in use by countries around the world to help manage their national biodiversity databases.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In 2010, the Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was established by the Australian Government’s National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) to provide researchers, decision makers and community groups a one-stop-shop for biodiversity data. There are now over 20 international Living Atlases based on the software platform originally developed by the ALA.</p>



<h2 id="the-ala-goes-global">The ALA goes global</h2>



<p>Within a few years of operation, the ALA rapidly established 100s of data partners across museums and herbaria, universities, government departments and community groups in Australia. Soon Australia’s biodiversity data were accessible online for ecoscience research, state and federal government environment and species conservation management programs. As the Australian node of GBIF – the Global Biodiversity Information Facility – the ALA supported the international community by sharing expertise and open software code.<br></p>



<p>In 2015, the ALA hosted the first international Living Atlases community meeting to respond to requests from countries around the world. This helped form the collaborative global community that now supports developers implementing the open source platform. The software code has been used to set up 27 installations around the world for national biodiversity databases as well as thematic, regional and institutional instances.</p>



<h2 id="the-international-living-atlases-community">The international Living Atlases community</h2>



<p>The Living Atlases platform enables countries to aggregate biodiversity data from multiple sources and supports integrated access to other biological and environmental information such as temperature, habitat etc.<br></p>



<p>Living Atlas community members continue to work collaboratively to share code and learn from experiences in establishing national biodiversity databases in their countries. They have organised technical training sessions and presented at numerous international meetings. As a result of these and other efforts, an increasing number of GBIF nodes and other organisations have implemented the platform. The Living Atlases community website offers full technical documentation, news from across the community and a current and complete list of participating countries.</p>



<h2 id="for-more-information">For more information:</h2>



<p><a href="https://living-atlases.gbif.org/">Living Atlases website</a></p>



<p><a href="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/21280-ALA-Case-Study-Fact-Sheet-International-Living-Atlases-V3.pdf">View this impact story as a PDF</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Liquid from the sky</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/liquid-from-the-sky/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Andrews]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 23:14:02 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=44491</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In shocking news, it appears that an unknown natural process is causing blobs of an unidentified clear liquid to fall from the sky. Scientists are investigating.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In shocking news, it appears that an unknown natural process is causing blobs of an unidentified clear liquid to fall from the sky. Scientists are investigating.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The néws they tried to BAN: it&#8217;s Thursdäy!</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-news-they-tried-to-ban-its-thursday/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Andrews]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 23:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=44488</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It's Thursday! But Big Néws wouldn't tell you thåt.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Apostrophes&#8217;R&#8217;Us! We are always interested &#8211; despite protestations &#8211; in (bracketed) spécial chäracters!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unconfirmed rumours: it&#8217;s Wednesday!</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/unconfirmed-rumours-its-wednesday/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Andrews]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2021 23:02:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=44486</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Anonymous sources have revealed that, contrary to expectations, today might be Wednesday.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Anonymous sources have revealed that, contrary to expectations, today might be Wednesday.</p>



<p>Our reporters were unable to confirm the allegations.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Confirming that it is Monday.</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/confirming-that-it-is-monday/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Matt Andrews]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:40:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www-test.ala.org.au/?p=44484</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We have confirmation that today is Monday.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>This just in: we have official confirmation that today is Monday the 15th of February.</p>



<p>Just thought you&#8217;d like to know. Here&#8217;s a picture:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="875" src="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295-1024x875.jpg" alt="Bug." class="wp-image-44256" srcset="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295-1024x875.jpg 1024w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295-300x256.jpg 300w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295-768x656.jpg 768w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295-1536x1312.jpg 1536w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295-1920x1640.jpg 1920w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/08/Nezara-viridula-Green-Vegetable-Bug-by-Reiner-Richter-CC-BY-4.0-observations_32203295.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Green Vegetable Bug (Nezara viridula) by Reiner Richter (CC-BY-4.0) </figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2020</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2020/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 01:03:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://edit.ala.org.au/?p=44459</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter November 2020]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><a href="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/ALA-Newsletter-November-2020.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-748x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44460" width="216" height="295" srcset="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-748x1024.png 748w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-219x300.png 219w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image-768x1052.png 768w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Newsletter-Nov-2020_image.png 891w" sizes="(max-width: 216px) 100vw, 216px" /></a></figure></div>



<p class="has-text-align-center"><a href="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/ALA-Newsletter-November-2020.pdf">ALA Newsletter November 2020</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New improvements to ALA data quality filters</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/new-improvements-to-ala-data-quality-filters/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 22:55:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://edit.ala.org.au/?p=44445</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA Data Quality project has released its first product for beta testing. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/02/AcroRd32_2020-02-05_14-55-47.png" alt="ALA Data Quality Project icon" class="wp-image-43643" width="204" height="194"/></figure></div>



<p>Since the project launch in&nbsp;February this year the Data Quality project team has been working with&nbsp;the ALA user community&nbsp;to identify&nbsp;data quality related issues and develop solutions.&nbsp; Thank you to everyone who completed our surveys,&nbsp;contributed to our understanding of the baseline&nbsp;perceptions of data quality,&nbsp;helped to&nbsp;prioritise&nbsp;the issues,&nbsp;and tested&nbsp;solutions.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Prioritisation survey results</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>After establishing a baseline for perceptions of data quality (<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/data-quality-project-baseline-survey-results/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">see results</a>), we conducted a&nbsp;prioritisation&nbsp;survey to&nbsp;identify&nbsp;which&nbsp;issues&nbsp;the data quality project&nbsp;address&nbsp;first. The top two issues identified&nbsp;were:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>Users of the ALA are using data accessed via the ALA without filtering out records that are not fit for purpose.&nbsp;</li><li>I don’t know whether to use particular records or datasets for my purpose because quality indicators are not visible, or I don&#8217;t understand what the information means.&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p><strong>Data Quality project first release – improvements to data filters</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>In response to the issues above,&nbsp;the project developed a&nbsp;new&nbsp;capability&nbsp;to&nbsp;pre-filter search results so that lower quality records&nbsp;(such as&nbsp;those with incomplete or inconsistent data)&nbsp;are not shown unless they are actively included.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The filters can be seen in a new&nbsp;Data Profile&nbsp;section&nbsp;above the&nbsp;search results.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/image.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44446" width="680" height="147" srcset="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/image.png 602w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/image-300x65.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 680px) 100vw, 680px" /></figure>



<p>The new release enables users to switch filters on&nbsp;or&nbsp;off&nbsp;and manage&nbsp;them&nbsp;as a group or individually.&nbsp;Information is available on the&nbsp;fields and data that make up the filters&nbsp;through mouse-over text and&nbsp;clickable info icons (i).&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>To get involved, <a href="https://biocache-dq-beta.ala.org.au/occurrences/search?q=">join beta testing of the new Data profiles</a> feature. &nbsp;</p>



<p>To learn more about the&nbsp;new data filter features,&nbsp;read&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000240256-getting-started-with-the-data-quality-filters" target="_blank">Getting started with the Data profiles</a>&nbsp;</p>



<p>For more information on the&nbsp;data quality project please visit the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/data-quality-project/" target="_blank">Data Quality&nbsp;project page</a>&nbsp;or&nbsp;contact us at&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="mailto:dataquality@ala.org.au" target="_blank">dataquality@ala.org.au</a>.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Guest editorial: ALA newsletter November 2020</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/guest-editorial/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 22:42:06 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://edit.ala.org.au/?p=44442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s a pleasure to be invited to provide this guest editorial to help celebrate the Atlas of Living Australia’s 10th anniversary. The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was developed in 2010 to support the needs of the national and international research community for timely access to Australian biodiversity data. In this time, it has grown [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It’s a pleasure to be invited to provide this guest editorial to help celebrate the Atlas of Living Australia’s 10<sup>th</sup> anniversary.</p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was developed in 2010 to support the needs of the national and international research community for timely access to Australian biodiversity data. In this time, it has grown into one of the world’s foremost biodiversity infrastructures and leads Australia’s commitment to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (<a href="https://www.gbif.org/">GBIF</a>).</p>



<p>The Australian biodiversity information community, partnering with the Australian Government through the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (<a href="https://www.education.gov.au/national-collaborative-research-infrastructure-strategy-ncris">NCRIS</a>), should be proud of our national and global achievements. One of many remarkable achievements is the <a href="https://living-atlases.gbif.org/">international Living Atlases</a> community. This now delivers science impact globally through 27 national atlases built on ALA-developed infrastructure, shared Australian capability and knowledge.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1024x682.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44450" width="380" height="253" srcset="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-768x511.jpg 768w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1536x1022.jpg 1536w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-2048x1363.jpg 2048w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/Australian-National-Herbarium-1920x1278.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" /><figcaption>The museum and herbaria communities were fundamental to the origins of the Atlas of Living Australia. Image: Australian Tree Seed Centre CSIRO Canberra</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>In this anniversary year, it’s timely to reflect on the history of the ALA. Its origins owe much to the vision, commitment and partnerships that were already in place in the museums, collections and herbaria sectors and we are proud to be part of this story. In the late 1990s, the peak body for herbaria in the region, the Council of Heads of Australasian Herbaria (CHAH) formed a consortium with the Australian Biological Resources Study (ABRS) to digitise and database specimens resulting in the Australasian Virtual Herbarium (<a href="https://avh.ala.org.au/">AVH</a>).</p>



<p>The museum community has a similar story. The zoological collections formed the Council of Heads of Australian Faunal Collections (CHAFC) in 1992 with a national viewpoint on museum-held biodiversity data issues, an exchange of ideas and interactions with ABRS and Environmental Information Resources Network within what is now the Department of Agriculture, Water and Environment. Following the success of the AVH, CHAFC sought to improve the sharing of data through then newly evolving web technology. This resulted in the Online Zoological Collections of Australian Museums, or <a href="https://ozcam.org.au/">OZCAM</a> in 2002.</p>



<p>The establishment of the ALA owes its foundation to the prior existence of AVH and OZCAM and this history runs deep in the architecture of the ALA. More importantly the strength of these existing networks, partnerships and governance models provided a sound foundation for accelerating the vision under the newly formed NCRIS program in 2007.</p>



<p>From its origins in the collections sector, the ALA has astutely expanded its remit to broaden the portfolio of data and services it offers Australian science and decision-making. The inclusion of biodiversity data from state government agencies, major research programs and its support of the citizen sector has significantly improved our understanding of Australia’s biodiversity.</p>



<p>The events we’ve witnessed in 2020 provide a timely reminder of the criticality of maintaining a comprehensive, representative and adequate national biodiversity infrastructure. It is fundamental to improving our understanding of the impact of current and future bushfires and other environmental threats, on biodiversity and supporting ensuing restoration efforts. It provides fundamental data to help understand the global behaviour of zoonotic diseases and their role in future pandemics, and it can position Australia to more effectively deal with biosecurity risks that impact our environment and economy.</p>



<p>Reflecting on the strategic priorities for our sector – &nbsp;for example around higher throughput digitisation of our collections and the rapid growth in genomics-based methods in biodiversity sciences – &nbsp;we believe we are extremely well placed to grow and evolve to meet these challenges through our ongoing partnerships with the ALA.</p>



<p>In closing, we acknowledge the significant vision and contribution made through the Australian Government’s NCRIS program in realising the ALA vision, and the partnerships that have been so fundamental to its success. This includes the thought leaders, the data partners and ALA’s institutional supporters that can rightfully be proud of what Australia has achieved.</p>



<p><strong>Cameron Slatyer</strong><br>Branch Manager | Life and Geosciences<br>Australian Museum Research Institute, Science and Learning, Australian Museum&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Professor Darren Crayn</strong><br>Director<br>Australian Tropical Herbarium</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Federal Budget announcement 2020</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/federal-budget-announcement-2020/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2020 22:17:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://edit.ala.org.au/?p=44437</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[As an outcome from the recent Federal Budget, the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) had positive news with $96 million secured for the 2022-23 financial year for current projects. $61 million was also provided for four new national research capabilities including Humanities, Arts and Social Sciences (HASS) and Indigenous eResearch data tools and platforms. [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large"><img src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/06/NCRIS_150px.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-41895"/></figure></div>



<p>As an outcome from the recent <a href="https://www.education.gov.au/2020-21-budget-research-package#:~:text=The%20%24157%20million%202020%20Investment,Research%20Infrastructure%20Strategy%20(NCRIS)">Federal Budget</a>, the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) had positive news with $96 million secured for the 2022-23 financial year for current projects. $61 million was also provided for four new national research capabilities including <a href="https://ministers.dese.gov.au/tehan/improving-hass-and-indigenous-research-infrastructure">Humanities, Arts and Social Sciences (HASS) and Indigenous eResearch data tools and platforms</a>. This is a positive signal regarding the importance of the NCRIS program as a core capability supporting Australia’s research sector.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Celebrating 10 years of science impact</title>
		<link>https://www-test.ala.org.au/blogs-news/celebrating-10-years-of-science-impact/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2020 03:56:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Impact stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://edit.ala.org.au/?p=44420</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In 2020, we’re celebrating 10 years of the Atlas of Living Australia and today we launch a new feature to showcase ALA research impact. Browse through our ALA-cited publications web page and see the many and varied ways researchers use big data for biodiversity.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://edit.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-1024x1024.png" alt="Illustration showing research publications" class="wp-image-44421" width="293" height="293" srcset="https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-1024x1024.png 1024w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-300x300.png 300w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-150x150.png 150w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-768x768.png 768w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-1536x1536.png 1536w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-2048x2048.png 2048w, https://www-test.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/11/20322-ALA-10-Stats-for-10-Years-Infographic-images-07-1920x1919.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 293px) 100vw, 293px" /></figure></div>



<p>The ALA brings together occurrence record data, taxonomic information, spatial and historical information on species distributions, and environmental data. These data are central to the research areas of ecology, conservation, environmental planning, Indigenous ecological management and sustainability.</p>



<p>The ALA’s contribution to the research output in these fields has steadily increased over the last 10 years. Now over 2,300 scientific publications have referenced the ALA, providing novel contributions to a range of fields.</p>



<p>Researchers have used data from ALA to show <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gecco.2019.e00720">changes in Platypus numbers over the last 150 years</a>, <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/fee.2032">identify rare species that thrive in Australian towns and cities</a>, and <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/een.12856">understand complex migration behaviour in insects</a> that would otherwise go undetected. Images stored by the ALA have even been used to build apps that can <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/ICIP.2019.8803746">automatically identify Australian insects</a> in the field.</p>



<p>As our data holdings continue to grow, researchers continue finding new ways to draw on ALA in their research, bettering the understanding of Australia’s unique biodiversity. Now, you can search and browse some of this research through our new webpage, <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/ala-cited-publications/">ALA-cited publications</a>.</p>



<p>If you are a researcher and use the ALA to access data or analytical tools, read <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000195866-how-to-cite-the-ala">How to cite the ALA</a> for more detail on best practices for citing and acknowledging the ALA.</p>



<p><strong>Ten years of the ALA</strong></p>



<p>Ten years ago, Australian national collections, science organisations, and government agencies saw the opportunity for a national online and open data repository for biodiversity data. The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) was established with funding from the Australian Government’s National Research Infrastructure Strategy (NCRIS) to fulfill this role and aggregate Australia’s biodiversity data.</p>



<p>“The ALA has changed the way biodiversity research and environmental decision making occurs in Australia,” said ALA Director Dr Andre Zerger.</p>



<p>“We now have over 90 million occurrence records and function as the most comprehensive dataset on Australian biodiversity. The ALA has over 78,000 registered users and access to 700 datasets from data partners across research, government and citizen science.” he said.</p>



<p><strong>Built on partnerships</strong></p>



<p>Central to the success of the ALA are the contributions from our data partners. They are the backbone of the ALA, providing authoritative data for species names and classification, geospatial reference data, environmental layers, and species occurrence data. </p>



<p>“The work of the organisations and institutions that provide data, and manage, curate and update that data, underpins our success and we look forward to continuing and growing these partnerships over another ten years,” said Andre.</p>



<p>The diverse datasets all contribute to the rich tapestries of data that are accessible via the ALA, and enable the ALA to perform like a window into the complex world of biodiversity science.</p>



<p><strong>National and global reach</strong></p>



<p>The ALA not only delivers Australia’s biodiversity data at a national level, it also contributes to the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF), an international network and data infrastructure funded by the world&#8217;s governments to provide open access to data about all types of life on Earth.</p>



<p>“Through the GBIF living atlases community, the infrastructure our team first developed 10 years ago is now being used by 27 countries around the world to manage their biodiversity data,” said Andre.</p>



<p>The ALA is the Australian node of GBIF and has significantly contributed to this global network for open biodiversity data access.</p>



<p><strong>More information</strong></p>



<ul><li>Visit <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/ala-cited-publications/">ALA-cited publications</a> to search and browse publications that reference the ALA.</li><li>Read <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000195866-how-to-cite-the-ala">How to cite the ALA</a> for more detail on best practices for citing and acknowledging the ALA.</li></ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
