<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 06:33:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.9.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA webinar: Protecting Australia&#8217;s ecosystems: novel approaches to biosecurity management￼</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-protecting-australias-ecosystems/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 03:33:39 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46819</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Australia is home to a vast number of species, many of which occur nowhere else. Unfortunately, however, the high uniqueness of our plants and animals makes our ecosystems unusually vulnerable to invasive species. In this webinar, three presenters will talk about their efforts to predict, locate, and eradicate high-impact invasive species before they become established, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Australia is home to a vast number of species, many of which occur nowhere else. Unfortunately, however, the high uniqueness of our plants and animals makes our ecosystems unusually vulnerable to invasive species. In this webinar, three presenters will talk about their efforts to predict, locate, and eradicate high-impact invasive species before they become established, a crucial step in protecting our precious ecosystems.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe title="ALA webinar: Protecting Australia&#039;s ecosystems: novel approaches to biosecurity management 24 May 22" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bMZcDFs3dwk?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEST, Tuesday 24 May 2022, with 238 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/AI-app.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46897"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Alexander Schmidt-Lebuhn | CSIRO</h3>



<p>Alexander is a CSIRO scientist at the Australian National Herbarium in Canberra, where he leads the Plant Systematics and Population Genetics team. His research interests include phylogenetics, taxonomy, and biogeography in particular of Asteraceae (daisy family) and the application of computer vision to species identification and collection science. Alexander&#8217;s work mobilises collection specimens and their DNA and label data to understand the evolution of Australia&#8217;s biodiversity, to produce identification tools, and to support conservation, biosecurity, and biological control research.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/fire-ant.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46898"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Andrew Turley | QLD Department of Agriculture and Fisheries</h3>



<p>Andrew leads the Strategy directorate for the National Red Imported Fire Ant Eradication Program, within the Queensland Department of Agriculture and Fisheries. Having joined the program in 2019, Andrew leads the development of program strategies, the implementation of its science, policy, systems and intelligence, and communications and engagement functions. Prior to joining the fire ant program, Andrew led Project DIG at the Queensland Museum Network, and multiple projects for the World Mosquito Program within Australia and abroad. &nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/biosecurity-commons.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46899"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="ana-belgun-data61">Paul Tudman | BioSecurity Commons</h3>



<p>Set to launch in April 2023, Biosecurity Commons will deliver a cloud-based decision-support platform for modelling and analysing biosecurity risk and response. Paul is a data and analytics specialist with over 20 years of experience working on large-scale projects for state and federal governments, and academia. As the Project Manager for Biosecurity Commons, Paul is responsible for leading a highly-skilled team of software developers, scientists and communicators to build powerful decision-support tools for biosecurity using cloud-based technology.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-moderator-Erin-Roger.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46891"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Erin Roger is the Biosecurity Lead for the Atlas of Living Australia. The program aims to strengthen biosecurity practices and partnerships for Australia, improving outcomes for our native species and industry. Erin is also the former Chair of the Australian Citizen Science Association. Prior to her work in these spaces, Erin worked in climate change adaptation and has a PhD in Terrestrial Ecology.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="qa">Q&amp;A</h2>



<p>We had so many wonderful questions. Please see below for answers to the questions we didn&#8217;t quite get to:</p>



<p><strong>Q. Are there laws around the movement of dirt (fill) in fire ant areas? It is common practice in my area to seek fill. How do you discourage the community from seeking out fill and raise awareness around the risks associated with moving dirt?</strong></p>



<p>A. Andrew Turley: Yes, there are restrictions on the movement of fire ant carriers regulated through the <em>Biosecurity Act 2014. </em>However, many materials can be moved safely if appropriate mitigation measures are taken. <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.fireants.org.au/treat/business-and-industry/movement-controls" target="_blank">The National Fire Ant Eradication Program website</a> is the best source of information about this. Restricting movement relies heavily on advertising, community engagement and cooperation, though we do have a compliance team that routinely checks businesses and respond to community reports of illegal movements too. </p>



<p><strong>Q. Do events like flooding risk larger-scale movements of ants, or other species?</strong></p>



<p>A. Andrew Turley: Yes. Fire ants originate from the Amazon floodplains, and whole colonies can form large rafts and float during flooding events (see this recent media <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/2022/apr/12/the-ants-go-rafting-invasive-fire-ants-take-to-australian-flood-waters-to-colonise-new-areas" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">article from The Guardian</a> discussing this). In SEQ, we&#8217;re lucky that all fire ants are east of the great dividing range and the rivers/creeks flow eastward back into the infested area. As such, the impact of flooding on fire ant eradication efforts is minimal at this time.  </p>



<p><strong>Q. How do you deal with taxonomic inconsistency? For invasive species, the ALA, GBIF, and CABI are not consistent. Is there an expert input process?</strong></p>



<p>A. Paul Tudman: The Biosecurity Commons platform will provide a suite of online tools for analysing data and provide easy access to online data repositories through a data catalogue. However, assessing the quality of the data that is used in any analysis will fall on the shoulders of the practitioner. We may investigate the challenge of taxonomic inconsistency between repositories in future versions of the platform but that is currently out of scope for the proof-of-concept stage of the project.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="want-more">Want more?</h2>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter May 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-may-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 05:57:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46864</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter May 2022]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fbzw7j/5e28fa7d7a47a3c06f6266836eaa2b80"><img loading="lazy" width="498" height="528" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/newsletter-thumbnail-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46875" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/newsletter-thumbnail-1.png 498w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/newsletter-thumbnail-1-283x300.png 283w" sizes="(max-width: 498px) 100vw, 498px" /></a></figure>



<p><a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fbzw7j/5e28fa7d7a47a3c06f6266836eaa2b80">ALA Newsletter May 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>BioCollect update: New look for our data collection tool</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/biocollect-update-new-look-for-our-data-collection-tool/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 23:26:53 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The ALA’s field data collection system – BioCollect – is getting brand new look. &#160;&#160; The look and feel will be fresher, cleaner and more intuitive. You can still design your own data collection projects, collect data, share your project with partners, and make the data accessible via the ALA – all in a new [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The ALA’s field data collection system – BioCollect – is getting brand new look. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The look and feel will be fresher, cleaner and more intuitive. You can still design your own data collection projects, collect data, share your project with partners, and make the data accessible via the ALA – all in a new design.&nbsp;&nbsp;The new design will be rolled out this May.</p>



<p>Visitis&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/biocollect-all" target="_blank">https://biocollect.ala.org.au/biocollect-all</a> to get started.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>The BioCollect makeover – what’s new and what’s changed</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>The user interface design for BioCollect has not changed since it’s launch, so it was time for an uplift.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The update is mostly cosmetic, we simplified the interface without losing any of the great functionality. There are also some new features. You can now create projects in your own personal space and publish the project to the world only when you’re ready.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>There are also some improvements to the document search and view feature on the project resources page. Even more improvements will be coming in the near future too.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>BioCollect – a flexible biodiversity data collection tool</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>BioCollect can be used to meet the specific data collection needs of citizen science projects, non-citizen science projects or natural resource management projects. It was first released in 2015, and is now widely used by researchers, industry ecologists, citizen scientists, non-government organisations and government organisations.&nbsp;</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="BioCollect: ALA data collection tool" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QEr6VULLZks?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Echidna CSI – a BioCollect case study</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>A research project run by Dr Tahlia Perry at the University of Adelaide uses data collected by citizen scientists to study echidnas. The project has had a huge impact on echidna research and conservation. The research team developed a bespoke mobile app using BioCollect as its database.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The flexible data collection tool enabled the research team to ‘recruit’ an army of citizen scientists across the country and collect the data necessary to establish an Australia-wide distribution map of Short-Beaked Echidnas (<em>Tachyglossus culeatus</em>). The project has doubled the number of echidna records in the ALA and discovered new facts about echidna biology. <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/echidna-csi-using-citizen-science-to-track-echidnas-throughout-australia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Read more about Echidna CSI.</a>&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Collect, store, manage and share with BioCollect</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you’re running a field data collection project, why not give BioCollect a try. You can collect data for your own project, store and manage the data, and, when you’re ready to share the data, it can go straight into the ALA automatically.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Visit <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://https/:biocollect.ala.org.au" target="_blank">is <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://biocollect.ala.org.au/biocollect-all" target="_blank">https://biocollect.ala.org.au/biocollect-all</a></a> to get started. </p>



<p>Back to <a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fbzw7j/5e28fa7d7a47a3c06f6266836eaa2b80">ALA Newsletter May 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s message May 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-message-may-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 23:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46838</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to the May 2022 edition of our newsletter ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure/resources/2021-national-research-infrastructure-roadmap"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-719x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46839" width="152" height="217" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-719x1024.png 719w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-211x300.png 211w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail-768x1094.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/Roadmap-thumbnail.png 790w" sizes="(max-width: 152px) 100vw, 152px" /></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.dese.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure/resources/2021-national-research-infrastructure-roadmap">View the Australian Government&#8217;s 2021 National Research Infrastructure Roadmap</a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p></p>



<p>We were pleased to recently see the Australian Government <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.minister.industry.gov.au/ministers/price/media-releases/morrison-government-launches-roadmap-900-million-spend-australias-research-infrastructure" target="_blank">release</a> the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.dese.gov.au/national-research-infrastructure/resources/2021-national-research-infrastructure-roadmap" target="_blank">2021 National Research Infrastructure Roadmap</a> which identifies future needs and priorities for research infrastructure investment in Australia. This is an important strategy setting document for the ALA, our partners in the National Collaborative Research Infrastructure program, and the many thousands of researchers and other users that benefit from this capability.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>We’d like to thank the ALA’s partners and stakeholders who made an important contribution to the roadmap development process through contributions to surveys, consultations, discussions, and formal submissions in response to the roadmap consultation draft. The roadmap is comprehensive, respects the existing NRI foundation and historical achievements, yet sets some ambitious goals for Australia to realise improvements.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p></p>



<h3 id="ala-decadal-vision-growth-for-impact">ALA Decadal Vision: Growth for impact</h3>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-Decadal-Vision-May-2022_v1.0.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/thumbnail-decadal-vision.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46833" width="147" height="207"/></a><figcaption><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-Decadal-Vision-May-2022_v1.0.pdf">View ALA Decadal Vision: Growth for impact </a></figcaption></figure></div>



<p>To support the ALA&#8217;s involvement and engagement to the roadmap process, we worked with our Advisory Board, peak bodies, and key stakeholders to develop the ALA&#8217;s own vision-setting piece. The <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-Decadal-Vision-May-2022_v1.0.pdf">ALA Decadal Vision: Growth for Impact</a> was also released this month, framed around an aspiration to <em>deliver trusted biodiversity data for Australia supporting world-class transformational research and more effective decision-making. </em>The vision has been developed to extend and grow the ALA’s impact beyond the current <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/publications/ala-strategy-2020-2025/">ALA Strategy 2020-2025</a> and is framed around a set of principles and growth opportunities, while respecting the importance of maintaining core ALA capability.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3 id="new-data-new-sectors-and-focus-on-collections">New data, new sectors, and focus on collections</h3>



<p>What’s new relative to what the ALA currently delivers? First, the vision commits to supporting new biodiversity data types, including from advances in genomics-based biodiversity identification, biodiversity survey data, and data emerging from sensor networks all of which are becoming increasingly important for our users. The ALA also recognises the fundamental role biological collections provide in supporting science and accelerating the digitisation of physical specimens to enable digital access. This aspiration aligns closely with the collections step change identified in the NRI roadmap around collections. Finally, the ALA Decadal Vision details the new sectors we will prioritise, and partnership models the ALA will adopt moving forward.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<h3 id="work-is-already-underway"><strong>Work is already underway</strong></h3>



<p>A decade may seem a long time but the ALA has already commenced pathfinder activities across several decadal priorities, a number of which appear on our <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/" target="_blank">current projects pages</a>. Our recently announced <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/" target="_blank">data mobilisation program</a> will also provide the foundation to support any further investment in accelerating the digitisation of Australia’s biological collections.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>We encourage you to read our decadal vision, particularly in the context of future science and decision-making drivers. I’d personally welcome feedback (<a href="mailto:ala@csiro.au">ala@csiro.au)</a> if you feel we’ve missed a driver or a future capability. The science we support is diverse and rapidly evolving so it’s important we adapt, evolve and continue to deliver impact.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy reading the decadal vision and this May edition of our newsletter.</p>



<p><strong>Andre Zerger</strong></p>



<p><strong>Director, Atlas of Living Australia</strong></p>



<p>Back to <a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fbzw7j/5e28fa7d7a47a3c06f6266836eaa2b80">ALA Newsletter May 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Labs: new site offering technical solutions to scientific problems </title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-labs-new-site-offering-technical-solutions-to-scientific-problems/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 01:50:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46796</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Do you conduct research using Australian biodiversity data? Do you analyse data or make data visualisations? ALA’s newest website, ALA Labs, is here to help. ALA Labs provides technical know-how and detailed solutions to specific scientific problems using data in the ALA. Learn how with ALA Labs posts The main showcase of ALA Labs is [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46800" width="386" height="257" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16.png 783w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16-300x200.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/chrome_2022-05-04_10-51-16-768x511.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 386px) 100vw, 386px" /></figure></div>



<p>Do you conduct research using Australian biodiversity data? Do you analyse data or make data visualisations?</p>



<p>ALA’s newest website, <a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/">ALA Labs</a>, is here to help. ALA Labs provides technical know-how and detailed solutions to specific scientific problems using data in the ALA.</p>



<p><strong>Learn how with ALA Labs posts</strong></p>



<p>The main showcase of ALA Labs is the <strong>Posts </strong>section. Posts are “how-to” articles on how to conduct specific statistical analyses or how to create data visualisations. Each post provides step-by-step commentary on how to do a specific task along with code so you can reproduce the analysis.</p>



<p></p>



<p>ALA Labs is managed by <a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/about.html">our Science and Decision Support team</a>. Team members will share solutions to common problems for users, including those that they have used in their own work.</p>



<p>Solutions described in ALA Labs posts are not intended to be the “only” or “correct” way to solve a problem. Rather, each post offers one <em>possible</em> way to do or make something. The goal is to provide ALA users with working examples to implement in their own work, hopefully making everyone’s analyses and visualisations better!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="630" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-1024x630.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46797" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-1024x630.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-300x185.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot-768x473.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/05/ALA-labs-sunburst-plot.png 1248w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Sunburst plots for taxonomic data.&nbsp;<br>This visualisation of ALA’s taxonomy was created by Dr Martin Westgate in R using {galah} and {ggplot2}. The <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://labs.ala.org.au/posts/2022-02-17_sunburst-plots-for-taxonomic-data/" target="_blank">full details of how to recreate this analysis and visualisation</a> are available on labs.ala.org.au.&nbsp;</figcaption></figure>



<p>“I always love hearing about the problems people are trying to solve using the biodiversity data in the ALA. We made ALA Labs to be a community space for people to share and learn about detailed solutions to data-related problems. I can’t wait to see how it grows,” said Dr Dax Kellie, evolutionary biologist, data analyst, and ALA Labs author.</p>



<p><strong>R – the language of ALA Labs</strong></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png" alt="logo for galah, ALA's R package" class="wp-image-44815" width="220" height="254" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png 434w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630-260x300.png 260w" sizes="(max-width: 220px) 100vw, 220px" /></figure></div>



<p>So far, posts on ALA Labs offer coding solutions for users of <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">R</a> – a popular, free, open-access software for analysing and visualising data – and {<a href="https://atlasoflivingaustralia.github.io/galah/index.html">galah</a>} – the ALA’s R package to download information from the ALA. We intend to expand articles to explore other tools and coding languages in the near future.</p>



<p></p>



<p><strong>We want to hear from you</strong></p>



<p>Is there a statistical analysis you are wondering how to do in R? Would you like to make a new visualisation or map? Are you looking to use the {galah} package to filter and download information?</p>



<p>We would love to hear from you. Please send any suggestions for ALA Labs posts to <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<p>Back to <a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fbzw7j/5e28fa7d7a47a3c06f6266836eaa2b80">ALA Newsletter May 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA webinar: New Data From Historic Collections</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-new-data-from-historic-collections/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2022 01:10:07 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46527</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Across Australia there are 60 million natural history specimens held at museums, universities, botanic gardens, herbaria, seed banks and at CSIRO. These collections are made up of whole organisms, skins, tissue samples, skeletons and DNA samples – plus data &#8230; a lot of data &#8230; even including data about that data (metadata). Collections metadata can [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Across Australia there are 60 million natural history specimens held at museums, universities, botanic gardens, herbaria, seed banks and at CSIRO. These collections are made up of whole organisms, skins, tissue samples, skeletons and DNA samples – plus data &#8230; a lot of data &#8230; even including data about that data (metadata).</p>



<p>Collections metadata can describe from as little as what species the sample or organism is, to when and where they were collected; to site descriptions, species associations, and much more. There is immense hidden value in metadata, and researchers are continually discovering new things about our historic collections.</p>



<p>In this webinar three researchers describe how they use the data &#8216;hidden&#8217; in our national collections.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA Webinar: New Data from Historic Collections – 16 Mar, 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8r3YLRcvnE8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEDT, Wednesday 16 March 2022, with 154 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="speakers">Speakers</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALADHC-220316/RocioAguilar-135px.ashx?la=en&amp;hash=9C23ED7DBC59812F7486AA9C86D0412BACDE7F00" alt="Rocio Aguilar"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Rocío Aguilar | Monash University</h3>



<p>Rocío is an Argentinean herpetologist who has called Australia home for the past 12 years. She specialises in eco-physiology and morphology, thermal biology and CT scanning. She completed her Bachelor and Masters at Comahue National University (Argentina) on habitat use in geckos, and research at the National University of Cuyo (Argentina) on the thermal ecophysiology of iguanids. Rocío worked for 6 years as a Research Assistant with Mike Kearney (University of Melbourne) and Christy Hipsley (University of Melbourne/Museum Victoria) working on eco-physio-morphology and conservation of Australian lizards. As part of a Monash University ARC Linkage Project with Museums Victoria and other Australian Museums, she is currently CT scanning all Australian lizard species to understand the evolutionary morphology pathways that make Australia the most lizard-diverse country in the world!</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALADHC-220316/EmilyRoycroft-135px.ashx?la=en&amp;hash=25301C35B33F84634E9F1483BBADC82EF3A8C55E" alt="Dr Emily Roycroft"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Emily Roycroft | ANU</h3>



<p>Emily Roycroft is an evolutionary biologist and postdoctoral researcher at the Australian National University. Her research applies genomic approaches to questions about the evolutionary history of species, primarily focusing on the spectacular diversity of native Australian mammals and reptiles. Emily is especially interested in the ways that museum collections can be used as a genomic resource for understanding recent biodiversity loss in Australia.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img src="https://events.csiro.au/~/media/Images/Events/E-ALADHC-220316/OllyBerry-135px.ashx?la=en&amp;hash=550A9B5CFB482C6E05F2EA641B67D7E1D907E545" alt="Olly Berry"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="ana-belgun-data61">Olly Berry | CSIRO</h3>



<p>Olly has a background in spatial ecology and genomics, but currently leads CSIRO’s Environomics Future Science Platform. This is an R&amp;D program whose brief is to find new ways to support environmental management with DNA technologies. It’s a field full of opportunities, and some of the most useful involve accessing information contained in natural history specimens.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright"><img loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Webinar-moderator-Martin.png" alt="Martin Westgate" class="wp-image-45781"/></figure></div>



<h3 id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin Westgate is Science Advisor to the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/">Atlas of Living Australia</a>&nbsp;and a visiting fellow at the&nbsp;<a href="https://fennerschool.anu.edu.au/">Fenner School of Environment &amp; Society</a>&nbsp;at the Australian National University. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="want-more">Want more?</h3>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter March 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-march-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 01:55:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46580</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter March 2022]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ALA-Newsletter-March-2022.pdf">ALA Newsletter March 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s message: ALA Newsletter March 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-message-ala-newsletter-march-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 22:03:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46554</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Launch of the ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program Welcome to the March 2022 edition of our newsletter, in which we launch the ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program. This new program will provide grants to institutions to mobilise their data to the ALA. This could include the transcription of historical field sheets, acquisition of [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<h2 id="launch-of-the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program">Launch of the ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</h2>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-1024x576.png" alt="" class="wp-image-46572" width="413" height="232" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/03/ABDMP_logo.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 413px) 100vw, 413px" /></figure></div>



<p>Welcome to the March 2022 edition of our newsletter, in which we launch the <strong><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program.</a></strong></p>



<p>This new program will provide grants to institutions to mobilise their data to the ALA. This could include the transcription of historical field sheets, acquisition of contemporary digital scanning technology, or even the development or purchase of software to provide better approaches to biodiversity data management and delivery. The ‘how’ will be up to the successful grant recipients, hence the program will offer maximum flexibility for successful applicants. We plan to award 6 grants in the first year of the program across both small ($20K) and large grants ($50K).</p>



<h3 id="why-were-creating-this-grant-program">Why we&#8217;re creating this grant program</h3>



<p>The success of the ALA as Australia’s biodiversity data infrastructure rests so much on the contribution made by its data partners across multiple domains. Data in the ALA comes from biological collections, museum and herbaria, state government, major research programs, non-government organisations and increasingly citizen scientists.</p>



<p>We partner with over 900 of these groups and individuals to harmonise Australia’s biodiversity data. Despite these partner contributions we remain acutely aware that for small institutions, or where historical data remains in analogue format, providing biodiversity data to the ALA remains a challenge, and we encourage you to apply for assistance through this new program.</p>



<p>I’ve been reflecting on the ecological data I collected as a researcher working across the south west slopes of NSW and parts of Victoria some years ago. I spent a decade supporting the collection of fundamental data about Australia’s flora and fauna. Much of this made its way into digital databases, at the time in CSIRO and the University of Melbourne. However, the ALA did not exist so this record although digital, remains undiscoverable.&nbsp; I also saw first-hand the filing cabinets of paper field sheets from my predecessors that provide a fundamental record of our biodiversity and may never be digitised.</p>



<p>With this context in mind, I am &nbsp;very excited to be launching the <strong><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>.</strong></p>



<h3 id="program-details-application-and-assessment">Program details: application and assessment</h3>



<p>Clearly there’s a massive amount of biodiversity data that remains un-digitised and the job of the evaluation panel will be to make informed assessments against defined criteria. Detailed guidelines will be published shortly on the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blog/">ALA blog</a> and on our ALA social media channels &#8211; <a href="https://twitter.com/atlaslivingaust">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/atlasoflivingaustralia">Facebook</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/1232460">LinkedIn</a>. Principles underpinning the program include alignment with national priorities and a focus on significant historical biodiversity information not currently available as FAIR data – findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable.</p>



<p>The program will be evaluated by an independent panel Chaired by Dr David Cantrill, one of the ALA Advisory Board’s longest serving members.</p>



<p>Our team is so excited by the opportunity this program will deliver Australia’s biodiversity community and already anticipates the legacy it will deliver. We look forward to seeing some fantastic applications.</p>



<p>I hope you enjoy our March 2022 newsletter.</p>



<p>Dr. Andre Zerger </p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-ala-australian-biodiversity-data-mobilisation-program/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 23:00:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46498</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Do you work in an institution with historic biodiversity data? Our new grant program is designed to help you digitise, mobilise and share your biodiversity data via the Atlas of Living Australia. ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/3-1-edited-1.png" alt="shelves full of folders" class="wp-image-46507" width="321" height="392"/><figcaption>Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<p class="has-medium-font-size"></p>



<p class="has-medium-font-size">The <a href="https://ala.org.au/abdmp/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a> is a grant program to support people and institutions make their biodiversity data more accessible.</p>



<h3 id="accessible-data-is-better-data"><strong>Accessible data is better data</strong></h3>



<p>Making your data open and accessible makes it more valuable. FAIR data – findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable &#8211; can be shared with other researchers and people working in biodiversity policy.</p>



<p>High quality and accessible biodiversity data helps conservation efforts and informs decision-making and solutions for environmental challenges.</p>



<h3 id="funding-to-support-your-digitisation-efforts"><strong>Funding to support your digitisation efforts</strong></h3>



<p>We know that organising, standardising, and digitising data takes time and effort. The ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program is here to help. The grant program will award small (up to $20k) and large (up to $50k) grants to biodiversity data owners to support purchasing equipment (e.g. camera, scanner) or employing staff in order to mobilise data.</p>



<p>Applications for the 2022 round of the program have now closed.</p>



<h3 id="who-can-apply"><strong>Who can apply?</strong></h3>



<p>We’re looking for institutions or biodiversity researchers who need help digitising historic physical records and mobilising data into the ALA.</p>



<p>There’s no catch, as long as the records are biodiversity-related. This can be for any wild species in Australia – from koalas to cane toads, eucalypts to bioluminescent fungi, we want to know about it.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The data might be in paper field notes, or species in physical collections. Whatever it is, we’ll be giving out grants to 6 institutions through both small ($20K) and large grants($50k).</p>



<p>You might be wondering why! Well, available data = useful data – so by making historical data accessible, it can be shared more widely and used by researchers to support biodiversity conservation efforts and decision-making.&nbsp;</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-1024x576.png" alt="colourful specimens in an insect collection" class="wp-image-46503" width="1005" height="565" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/5.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<h1 id="details-of-the-program"><strong>Details of the program</strong></h1>



<h3 id="how-to-apply">How to apply</h3>



<p>All applications must be sent using the program submission form. </p>



<h3 id="closing-date-for-applications">Closing date for applications</h3>



<p>Applications for 2022 have now closed.</p>



<h3 id="how-much-funding-can-i-apply-for">How much funding can I apply for? </h3>



<p>There are two funding amounts on offer, including:</p>



<ul><li>small grants up to $20,000</li><li>large grants up to $50,000</li></ul>



<h3 id="who-can-apply">Who can apply?</h3>



<p>This grant program is open to individuals or groups within an institution, excluding existing partners who already receive ALA or National Collaborative Research Infrastructure Strategy support. </p>



<h3 id="what-data-are-suitable-for-the-grant">What data are suitable for the grant?</h3>



<ul id="block-72757bf6-1e52-42ba-81ff-c1d26286af64"><li>The program will target existing data. It cannot support new expeditions or field programs</li><li>Data mobilisation efforts should align to national priorities</li><li>Data should be in the form of biodiversity species occurrence records akin to what&#8217;s delivered through the ALA already</li><li>Emergent digital data must be mapped to the Darwin Core standard and able to be provided to the ALA as open data</li></ul>



<h3 id="what-can-i-use-the-funding-for">What can I use the funding for?</h3>



<p>Funding can be used to fund data mobilisation and/or infrastructure investments. </p>



<p>Data mobilisation investment could include:</p>



<ul><li>Staff time to digitise of specimens in physical collections including scanning</li><li>Conversion of existing analogue data, such as in field notes or other formats into the Darwin Core standard for provision to the ALA</li></ul>



<p>Infrastructure investment could include:</p>



<ul><li>Purchasing digital imaging equipment to create digital data from historic records</li><li>Purchasing software licences to improve the management and delivery of biodiversity data</li><li>Software development costs associated with the improve management and delivery of biodiversity data</li></ul>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-1024x576.png" alt="assistant photographing a specimen" class="wp-image-46504" width="737" height="414" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/4.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 737px) 100vw, 737px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="selection-criteria">Selection criteria</h3>



<p>Applications will be assessed using an online form, in a single round and selected by an independent program evaluation panel. The submission form will be available from the 14th of March. It will contain all questions and a guide to the length of answers our panel is looking for. </p>



<p>Overall, we are looking to understand the details of the proposed activity, why it is important, and how you would allocate the funds if successful.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-1024x576.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46505" width="455" height="255" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-1024x576.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-768x432.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1-1536x864.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/1.png 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 455px) 100vw, 455px" /><figcaption><meta charset="utf-8">Image: Australian National Insect Collection (ANIC)</figcaption></figure></div>



<h3 id="more-information">More information</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://ala.org.au/abdmp/">About the program</a> </li><li><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp-faq/">FAQ&#8217;s page</a></li></ul>



<h3 id="any-other-questions">Any other questions?</h3>



<p>Please <a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">email us</a> with any questions you have about the program.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>GBIF Young Researchers Award 2022 – Call for Nominations</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/gbif-young-researchers-award-2022-call-for-nominations/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 03:35:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=46442</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Nominations are now open for the GBIF 2022 Young Researchers Award. This award is an annual programme aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p class="has-background" style="background-color:#e7e6ea">Nominations are now open for the GBIF 2022 Young Researchers Award. This award is an annual program aimed at fostering and recognising innovative research and discovery in biodiversity informatics. </p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full"><img loading="lazy" width="210" height="100" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/GBIF-logo-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44593"/></figure></div>



<p>The 2022 programme will provide a pair of €5,000 prizes (approx. AUD7,500) recognising the work of two early-career researchers — preferably, one Masters and one PhD candidate. Nominations are open to Masters and PhD students conducting innovative research using biodiversity data available through GBIF. The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, meaning all data in the ALA is also accessible via GBIF. </p>



<p>All applicants need to receive a formal nomination from the heads of delegation and node managers of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/the-gbif-network">GBIF Participant countries</a>. This year our team at the Atlas of Living Australia will coordinate the applications from Australian researchers. We will select two nominations to be assessed by the GBIF Science Committee.</p>



<p class="has-text-color" style="color:#c44d34"><strong><em>Applications to the ALA are due by 30 May 2022.</em></strong></p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p> </p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-662x1024.jpg" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-46451" width="376" height="581" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-662x1024.jpg 662w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-194x300.jpg 194w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-768x1188.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o-993x1536.jpg 993w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/02/8509418243_849313e71a_o.jpg 1170w" sizes="(max-width: 376px) 100vw, 376px" /><figcaption>Illustration of&nbsp;<em>Macrolepiota procera</em>&nbsp;(Scop.) Gray, from&nbsp;<a href="http://biodiversitylibrary.org/page/1266181"><em>Führer für Pilzfreunde</em></a>&nbsp;(1821) via&nbsp;<a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/biodivlibrary/8509418243/in/album-72157632865665228/">Biodiversity Heritage Library</a>, no rights reserved under&nbsp;<a href="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/mark/1.0/">CC0</a>.</figcaption></figure></div>



<h2 id="how-to-submit-an-application-australian-applicants"><strong>How to submit an application (Australian applicants)</strong></h2>



<ol type="1"><li>Visit&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6PzaBymtwAEvbpXYtb4d1y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2022-gbif-young-researchers-award">the GBIF young researchers award website</a>&nbsp;and follow the instructions.&nbsp;<br><br></li><li>Submit your nominations to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">Jenna Wraith, ALA&#8217;s Training and Outreach Coordinator</a>, with ‘GBIF Young Researcher’ in the subject line by&nbsp;<strong>30 May 2022.</strong> </li></ol>



<p> </p>



<p> </p>



<h2 id="nomination-process"><strong>Nomination process</strong></h2>



<p>Two Australian nominations will be selected for submission to GBIF by the Australian GBIF Delegation in time for the GBIF submission deadline. Please contact&nbsp;<a href="mailto:outreach@ala.org.au">outreach@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;for further information if required.</p>



<p>A jury organised by&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.gbif.org/contact-us/directory?group=scienceCommittee" target="_blank">GBIF Science Committee</a>&nbsp;will select the two award recipients from the pool of nominees received from the country delegation by the GBIF Secretariat. The winners will be announced in September/October 2022.</p>



<p></p>



<p> </p>



<p> </p>



<h2 id="award-nomination-packet"><strong>Award nomination packet</strong></h2>



<p>Candidates should prepare their proposal and nomination packets to include:</p>



<ol><li><strong>Research summary</strong>&nbsp;(<em>200 words</em>)<br><br></li><li><strong>Project description</strong>&nbsp;(<em>maximum 5 pages, 12-point Arial</em>) that describes<br>a. The need for the research and the question(s) it addresses.<br>b.&nbsp;<strong>The role of data accessed through GBIF in addressing these questions</strong>. Research proposals must clearly demonstrate how the study incorporates data mobilised through GBIF. Students with questions about GBIF-enabled data should work with academic advisors, their GBIF national node, the GBIF Secretariat or members of the Science Committee to increase their understanding.<br>c. The research scope, plan, methodologies, relevant literature citations and timetable.<br>d. If relevant, a description or an excerpt from a data management plan that outlines how data related to the research is published or will be prepared for publication through the GBIF network to GBIF.org.<br><br></li><li><strong>Curriculum vitae</strong>&nbsp;of the student applicant including full contact information at the home institution.<br><br></li><li><strong>Supporting documents</strong><br>a. An official letter from the student’s faculty mentor/supervisor certifying that the applicant is a student in good standing in the graduate programme of the university.<br>b. At least one, and no more than three, letters of support from established researchers active in a field that encompasses and incorporates biodiversity informatics (e.g., genetics, species composition and traits, biogeography, ecology, systematics, et al.)</li></ol>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="further-information"><strong>Further information</strong></h2>



<p>Full details, including how to nominate and eligibility criteria, can be found on the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/news/6PzaBymtwAEvbpXYtb4d1y/call-for-nominations-to-the-2022-gbif-young-researchers-award" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">GBIF website.</a></p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
