<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 05:50:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.8</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Global partnership paves way for ALA system upgrade</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/global-partnership-paves-way-for-ala-system-upgrade/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 05:48:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44907</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In June this year we upgraded our ALA systems to make them more reliable, more robust, and equipped to manage increasing amounts of biodiversity data. The major upgrade was possible due to our close partnership with GBIF – the Global Biodiversity Information Facility. The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, an [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/02/GBIF-logo-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44593" width="323" height="154"/></figure></div>



<p>In June this year we upgraded our ALA systems to make them more reliable, more robust, and equipped to manage increasing amounts of biodiversity data. The major upgrade was possible due to our close partnership with GBIF – the Global Biodiversity Information Facility.</p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia is the Australian node of GBIF, an international network and data infrastructure funded by the world&#8217;s governments and aimed at providing anyone, anywhere, open access to biodiversity data.</p>



<h2 id="collaboration"><strong>Collaboration</strong></h2>



<p>Our systems upgrade is the result of more than 12 months of collaborative work between teams based in Australia, UK and Denmark.</p>



<p>The development teams established a software codebase shared by both teams and worked on a framework for genuinely open-source software development.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“The ALA and GBIF development teams worked so well together. There’s a strong sense of trust and confidence in the skills of each team leading to individual contributions contributing to the larger whole.</p><p>Our teams know that accessible, high quality biodiversity data is improving research and environmental outcomes across the globe and that their efforts are integral to making this happen,” said Joe Miller, executive secretary of GBIF and former research group leader at the Centre for Australian National Biodiversity Research, CSIRO.</p></blockquote>



<h2 id="major-upgrade-reaps-benefits-for-users"><strong>Major upgrade reaps benefits for users</strong></h2>



<h3 id="efficiency-and-effectiveness"><strong>Efficiency and effectiveness</strong></h3>



<p>The new infrastructure, using GBIF/ALA shared codebase, increases indexing speeds for the ALA, reduces its running costs, and reduces long-term technical debt. With the ALA&#8217;s infrastructure growing in excess of millions of biodiversity occurrence records annually, such efficiencies are critical. </p>



<p>Javier Molina, ALA’s Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project Lead, was pleased to report that users have noticed the system is more responsive, particularly when searching species data, using map-based navigation, and using the Spatial Portal (ALA’s analytical tool).</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Prior to the upgrade, we were experiencing some unscheduled outages every month. Since the project went live in June, we haven’t received any reports of unscheduled outages. The system has also coped well with high peaks of utilisation,” said Javier.</p><p>“We recently ingested a dataset from eBird Australia of more than 20 million records, this went smoothy and without issue. A dataset that large would have created lots of headaches for us in the old system.”</p></blockquote>



<h3 id="consistency-is-key"><strong>Consistency is key</strong></h3>



<p>Consistency between the ALA, GBIF and other biodiversity infrastructures is another component of the recent upgrade.</p>



<p>Many users of the ALA also frequently access data through GBIF. For these users, the benefits of a shared infrastructure are clear. Shared approaches to processing biodiversity data eliminate potential sources of confusion for users. For example, if there are consistent flags and interpretations, users become comfortable and proficient using multiple platforms.  </p>



<h3 id="international-living-atlases-will-also-benefit-from-upgrade"><strong>International Living Atlases will also benefit from upgrade</strong></h3>



<p>Software originally developed by the Atlas of Living Australia team is increasingly used across the GBIF network. There are now 27 installations around the world. Some of these are national biodiversity databases and some are thematic, regional or institutional instances. The International Living Atlases is a collaborative global community that supports developers who implement the open-source platform.</p>



<blockquote class="wp-block-quote"><p>“Our collaborative work with GBIF has built social capital in the global community, and it is an excellent entry point for the International Living Atlases community to jump onboard,” said Javier.<br><br>“Completion of this first phase now makes it possible for the international community to co-develop new features and work on other mutual areas of interest and concern, including a shared registry and improved handling of sampling-event datasets.”</p></blockquote>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-full is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Core-infrastructure-upgrade-1.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44911" width="919" height="768"/></figure></div>



<h2 id="technical-details"><strong>Technical details</strong></h2>



<ul><li>AWS: virtual infrastructure from AWS performs better and is more affordable. The biggest impact on the infrastructure costs is by far the migration of storage for images from block storage (standard file system) to AWS S3.</li></ul>



<ul><li>Solr search engine: By optimising our software stack with the Solr search engine we reduced the required server specifications compared to the previous infrastructure.</li><li>On day 1, the project went live on an infrastructure that was 43% more affordable than the old infrastructure. This represents a saving of A$79K per annum<a> (</a>comparison based on full on-demand price, production-only systems).</li></ul>



<p>The savings on running a more stable system and co-maintaining an up-to-date codebase will be significant.</p>



<h3 id="next-steps"><strong>Next steps</strong></h3>



<p>The roll-out of the upgrade in June was the first of three stages in the project.</p>



<p>Working from a shared codebase allows us to collaborate and innovate together, for example with respect to improving how we handle eDNA data, establishing common vocabularies, and simplifying the data ingestion process.</p>



<p><br>For more details, visit our <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/core-infrastructure-upgrade-project/">Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project page</a>.</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator"/>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Science Week 13-21 August 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/national-science-week-13-21-august-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Aug 2021 02:08:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44881</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[There are so many great events happening this week, and many of them are online so everyone can get their science on!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="aligncenter size-large"><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/"><img loading="lazy" width="600" height="400" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/SW21_webbanner600x400-1.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-44894"/></a></figure></div>



<p>Here are a few great events from some our partners. </p>



<h3 id="great-southern-bioblitz">Great Southern BioBlitz</h3>



<p>The Great Southern BioBlitz is an international period of intense biological surveying that attempts to record all the living species within several designated areas across the Southern Hemisphere in Spring.</p>



<p>During National Science Week, Great Southern BioBlitz is hosting two webinars on how to use iNaturalist</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/a-beginners-guide-for-using-inaturalist-2/">A beginners guide for using iNaturalist </a> (Tuesday 17 Aug 8:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;9:00pm)</li></ul>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/a-beginners-guide-for-using-inaturalist/">Advanced tips for using iNaturalist </a> (Tuesday 7 Sep 8:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;9:00pm)</li></ul>



<h3 id="atlas-of-life-in-the-coastal-wilderness"><strong>Atlas of Life in the Coastal Wilderness</strong></h3>



<p>The Atlas of Life in the Coastal Wilderness have put together an amazing program of activities for Science Week, including:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://nsweducation.zoom.us/meeting/register/u5ApcO2rpzgsGNzrZrkZTDKSN0qa0WsuJwQj"><strong>The Atlas of Life and iNaturalist</strong></a> (Monday 16 August 1.50pm)</li><li><a href="https://nsweducation.zoom.us/webinar/register/WN_oBSz2f4bSuyjnqBw8JL9QA">Bee hotels &#8211; to boost bees after fire </a>(Monday 16 August)</li><li><a href="https://nsweducation.zoom.us/meeting/register/u50vd-6urz4pGNaUoKQEzyhIeEoYHKFmCciP">Echidna CSI: Combining citizen science with microbiome research to asses bushfire impacts on echidnas </a>(Wednesday 18 August)</li></ul>



<p>Check out <a href="https://atlasoflife.org.au/2020-national-science-week-1">Atlas of Life in the Coastal Wilderness &#8211; National Science Week </a>for more details.</p>



<p></p>



<h3 id="frogid-informing-frog-conservation-through-citizen-science"><strong>FrogID: informing frog conservation through citizen science</strong></h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.eventbrite.com.au/e/frogid-informing-frog-conservation-through-citizen-science-tickets-164217732659">Informing frog conservation through citizen science</a>  (Thursday 12 August 2021, 7:30 PM – 8:30 PM AEST)</li></ul>



<p></p>



<h3 id="australian-museum-and-the-royal-botanic-gardens-sydney">Australian Museum and The Royal Botanic Gardens, Sydney</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/sydney-science-trail-live-at-royal-botanic-garden-sydney/">Sydney Science Trail:</a> ONLINE EVENT (Friday 13 Aug&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;Monday 13 Sep 12:00am&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;11:45pm)</li></ul>



<p></p>



<h3 id="museums-victoria">Museums Victoria</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/climate-change-families-for-a-thriving-future/">Climate Change: Families for a Thriving Future webinar</a> (Sunday 15 Aug 4:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;5:00pm)</li></ul>



<p></p>



<h3 id="wabsi-webinar">WABSI webinar</h3>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/event/wabsi-webinar-big-issues-in-biodiversity-science-digitalisation-in-environmental-assessment-international-frontrunners/">Big issues in biodiversity science: Digitalisation in Environmental Assessment – International Frontrunners</a> (Wednesday 18 Aug 4:00pm&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;5:30pm)</li></ul>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Citizen science conference ticket giveaway</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/citizen-science/citizen-science-conference-ticket-giveaway/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 00:35:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44875</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Win a complimentary registration to the ACSA virtual conference from 27 to 29 October 2021.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/ACSA-conference.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44876" width="285" height="198" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/ACSA-conference.png 605w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/ACSA-conference-300x209.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px" /></a></figure></div>



<p>We’re proud to be sponsoring this year’s ACSA conference and we’re giving away one registration ticket to <a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/">“CitSciOz21: Celebrate, Communicate, Co-create” the Australian Citizen Science Association’s virtual conference 27 – 29 October, 2021</a> (valued at $105.00), </p>



<p>To be in the running, respond to our Twitter or Facebook posts about the competition and tell us about your favourite species observation, why it’s your favourite and which platform you used to record it.</p>



<p>Visit us on <a href="https://twitter.com/atlaslivingaust">Twitter</a> (<a href="https://twitter.com/atlaslivingaust">@atlaslivingaust</a>) or <a href="https://www.facebook.com/atlasoflivingaustralia">Facebook </a>(<a href="https://www.facebook.com/atlasoflivingaustralia">atlasoflivingaustralia</a>) and tell us about your favourite species observation.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/CS-photo-compressed.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44877" width="326" height="184" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/CS-photo-compressed.png 682w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/CS-photo-compressed-300x169.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 326px) 100vw, 326px" /></figure></div>



<ul><li>You can post your favourite species observation photo Twitter and tag @atlaslivingaust in the post. Tell us why it’s your favourite observation and what citizen science app or platform you used to record your observation.</li><li>You can copy the url for your favourite observation, in the comments below our Twitter or Facebook posts, or direct message us on Facebook or Twitter, be sure to tell us which platform you used to record your observation and why it&#8217;s your favourite</li><li>Or use the Twitter and Facebook comments to tell us about your favourite species observation, which platform you used to record it and why it’s your favourite.</li></ul>



<p>This promotion is in no way sponsored, endorsed or administered by, or associated with, Twitter or Facebook.</p>



<p>We can’t wait to see your favourite observations!</p>



<h3 id="more-about-citscioz21-australian-citizen-science-association-conference">More about <a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/?sfw=pass1628638674">CitSciOz21 Australian Citizen Science Association conference</a> </h3>



<p>This year the ACSA conference will be delivered online. There is great program of events structured around the following themes:</p>



<ul><li>Celebrate: <strong>Explore, investigate and showcase successful citizen science projects from Australia and the rest of the world.</strong></li></ul>



<ul><li>Communicate: <strong>Showcase citizen science communication techniques for maximum impact.</strong></li></ul>



<ul><li>Co-Create: <strong>Encourage inclusiveness and bring together a diverse array of people to discover better science.</strong></li></ul>



<p>Two of the keynote speakers are Dr Cathy Foley and Dr Karl Kruszelnicki.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="323" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-1024x323.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44886" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-1024x323.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-300x95.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-768x243.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote-1536x485.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Cathy-keynote.png 1900w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="1024" height="323" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-1024x323.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44887" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-1024x323.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-300x95.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-768x243.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote-1536x485.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/08/Dr-Karl-keynote.png 1900w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /></figure>



<h3 id="terms-and-conditions"><strong>Terms and conditions</strong></h3>



<h4 id="competition-to-win-one-registration-ticket-for-citscioz21-celebrate-communicate-co-create-the-4th-conference-of-the-australian-citizen-science-association-27-29-october">Competition to win one registration ticket for “CitSciOz21: Celebrate, Communicate, Co-create” The 4th conference of the Australian Citizen Science Association 27 – 29 October, 2021.</h4>



<ol type="1"><li>The promoter is the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organisation (“CSIRO”) (ABN 41 687 119 230), Clunies Ross Street, Black Mountain, ACT, Australia.</li><li>Entry to the competition is open to all Australian residents aged 18 years or over. Employees, directors and officers of CSIRO or any person associated with the Competition, or any organisation or individual associated with the provision of the prize(s) are not eligible to enter.</li><li>Each entry must be made in accordance with these Terms and Conditions. By entering the Competition, each entrant agrees to be bound by these Terms and Conditions. Entries not submitted in accordance with the Terms and Conditions may be deemed ineligible.&nbsp; Information on how to enter and prize details form part of these Terms and Conditions.</li><li>The promotion is in no way sponsored, endorsed, administered by or associated with Facebook or Twitter.</li><li>All respondents who post their favourite observations to Twitter and tag @atlaslivingaust and specify which citizen science app they used to upload their observation will be considered contenders to win one registration to the Australian Citizen Science Association Virtual Conference 2021 ‘Celebrate, Communicate, Co-create’ 27 – 29 October, 2021(of one available) (individual value $105.00) <a href="https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/">https://citizenscience.org.au/citscioz21/</a></li><li>Entries can also be in the form of a Twitter or Facebook post, or a comment in response to our Twitter or Facebook posts about the competition, or a direct message via Twitter or Facebook.</li><li>Entrants may only submit one entry to the competition and may only win one prize.</li><li>The Competition period commences at 11:59pm on 10 August 2021 and closes&nbsp;31 August at midnight. Any entry received by the promoter before or after the Competition period may be ineligible for entry and no responsibility will be accepted for lost, late or misdirected submissions.</li><li>The promoter may at its absolute discretion remove or reject any entry for any reason whatsoever.</li><li>Each entrant warrants that its entry does not breach the copyright or other intellectual property rights or privacy rights of any other person.</li><li>The entries will be judged on originality, creativity, and aesthetics by a panel of CSIRO staff on&nbsp;1 September 2021.</li><li>The winner will be notified within seven business days via Facebook direct message or Twitter direct message (whichever platform was used to submit the entry). The prize will be sent to the email supplied by the winner after the announcement of the winner. The prize is not transferable or exchangeable or redeemable for cash. We will make reasonable efforts to ensure winners receive their prize. Where we are not able to deliver a prize despite making reasonable efforts to do so the prize will be reassigned.</li><li>If there are any unclaimed or un-awarded prizes a second judging&nbsp;will be conducted following the same criteria on&nbsp;8 September 2021 at the same time and place as the original judging. The new winner&nbsp;will be contacted by email within two business days. A prize will be deemed to be unclaimed if we have been unable to contact the prize winner through the contact details provided by 11.59 pm on&nbsp;15 September 2021.</li><li>If the Competition is interfered with in any way or is not capable of being conducted as reasonably anticipated due to any reason beyond the control of the CSIRO, including as a result of technical failures, CSIRO reserves the right, in its sole discretion, to the fullest extent permitted by law to modify, postpone, suspend, terminate or cancel the Competition as appropriate.</li><li>Except for any liability that cannot by law be excluded including any statutory consumer guarantees, CSIRO, nor any of their respective officers, employees and agents will be liable for any injury, damages, expenses, or loss whatsoever (whether direct or consequential) to persons or property as a result of any person entering the Competition or accepting or using any prize, including without limitation, failure of any winner to contact the promoter, non-receipt of any prize or damage to any prize in transit.</li><li>Any questions about CSIRO’s privacy policy or any request to access, modify or delete any information provided in an entry should be directed to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></li></ol>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>galah takes flight: ALA’s new R package now available</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/galah-takes-flight-alas-new-r-package-now-available/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 01:16:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Tools & Apps]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44814</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We have just released galah, our new software package for accessing ALA data. This makes it easier than ever to find, download and analyse information on Australian biodiversity. We created galah to support users who need to access ALA data in bulk. Many researchers routinely use programming languages to request data, rather than manually navigating [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44815" width="306" height="353" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630.png 434w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/21-00159_NCMI_BRAND_ALA-GalahHexSticker_FinalMockUp_210630-260x300.png 260w" sizes="(max-width: 306px) 100vw, 306px" /></figure></div>



<p>We have just released <em>galah</em>, our new software package for accessing ALA data. This makes it easier than ever to find, download and analyse information on Australian biodiversity.</p>



<p>We created <em>galah </em>to support users who need to access ALA data in bulk. Many researchers routinely use programming languages to request data, rather than manually navigating our website. For the biodiversity research community, the most commonly used programming language is called ‘R’.</p>



<p>R is a useful programming language by itself; but it’s most valuable feature is the ability to write and share bundles of software – called ‘packages’ – which users can install to achieve specific tasks.</p>



<p><em>galah</em> enables ALA users to locate and download occurrence records, taxonomic information, and associated media such as images or sounds. It allows users to directly integrate data from the ALA into their analyses in R.</p>



<h4 id="naming-ala4rs-successor">Naming ALA4R&#8217;s successor</h4>



<p>We chose to call our new software ‘galah’ for a few reasons. First, it is an iconic Australian species that many people will be familiar with. Second, the word galah already contains the acronym ‘ALA’. Finally, a poll of users on social media chose <em>galah</em> over other options.</p>



<p>This package is the successor to the earlier <em>ALA4R</em>, which has been available for R users since 2014. <em>galah </em>provides an improved and simplified user experience to <em>ALA4R</em>, while still providing the same core functionality. <em>ALA4R </em>will be maintained but not actively developed while users transition to <em>galah</em>, and we encourage users to make the switch as soon as practical.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/EcoCommons-training_galah.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44816" width="400" height="320" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/EcoCommons-training_galah.png 650w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/EcoCommons-training_galah-300x240.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /><figcaption>ALA developer Matilda Stevenson (bottom right) presents galah to an EcoCommons Software Carpentry workshop in June 2021.</figcaption></figure></div>



<h4 id="early-adoption-and-recent-updates">Early adoption and recent updates</h4>



<p>Since we developed <em>galah</em>, early adopters have been testing the package extensively in classes and research projects around the country. The team recently presented <em>galah </em>at a Software Carpentry workshop on ‘R for ecologists’, where participants learnt how to use the package to download data to use in their ecological research. Internally, the ALA’s Science and Decision Support team are already using the package in their day-to-day work and on projects such as <a href="https://ardc.edu.au/project/ecoassets/">EcoAssets</a>.</p>



<p>As part of the latest update to <em>galah</em>, released this week, support for international Living Atlases has been introduced. This enables users from countries including Austria, Guatemala and Spain to use <em>galah</em> to download and analyse data from their country.</p>



<h4 id="to-get-started-with-using-galah">To get started with using <em>galah</em>:</h4>



<ul><li>go to the package <a href="https://atlasoflivingaustralia.github.io/galah">homepage</a> for documentation and examples</li><li>read the ALA support article <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000246515-what-is-galah-">What is galah?&nbsp;</a></li><li>download galah from the Comprehensive R Archive Network (<a href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=galah">CRAN</a>) or <a href="https://github.com/AtlasOfLivingAustralia/galah">GitHub</a></li></ul>



<p>We also welcome requests or suggestions for new features, as well as bug reports, on our <a href="https://github.com/AtlasOfLivingAustralia/galah/issues">issues page</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Creating a buzz for citizen science</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/creating-a-buzz-for-citizen-science/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 01:00:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Citizen science]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44820</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[by Erin Roger, ALA Citizen Science Programme Lead]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>On the coldest day in Sydney in 25 years, I was thrilled to attend the launch of the <a href="https://www.ps.org.au/bb-highway-about">B&amp;B Highway’s</a> citizen science component of their program. The B&amp;B Highway Program –  spearheaded by Dr Judy Friedlander of <a href="https://www.ps.org.au/">PlantingSeeds Projects</a>, aims to provide habitat for birds, bees, butterflies and biodiversity through native plantings and the installation of pollinator habitats such as native stingless beehives, nesting boxes and insect hotels. The program is now in more than 50 schools and community locations throughout NSW and is making inroads in other states throughout Australia.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="842" height="399" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44821" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_1.jpg 842w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_1-300x142.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_1-768x364.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 842px) 100vw, 842px" /><figcaption><em>Schools learn more about pollinators and habitat through participation in the B&amp;B Highway Program which also offers indoor and outdoor, and theoretical and practical teachings about biodiversity.</em></figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p>The June launch celebrated the partnership of CSIRO’s Atlas of Living Australia (ALA), the Australian Citizen Science Association (ACSA) and the B&amp;B Highway in enabling citizen science data to flow from the program into the ALA. The aim for the program is to contribute valuable pollinator and plant data so the data is freely available for anyone to use. The program has been set up on <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/projects/b-b-highway-nsw">iNaturalist</a> so that all participating schools can see their observations under the umbrella B&amp;B Highway Project.</p>



<p>Despite the chill, the launch kicked off with a search of the garden at Ryde East Public School, where a number of young pollinator enthusiasts from different schools had been assembled. While we didn’t find many pollinators, it showed the importance of seasonal sampling for true indication of pollinator diversity. Speeches, snacks and celebrations then followed.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="840" height="630" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44822" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_2.jpg 840w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_2-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_2-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/07/BB-highway_2-640x480.jpg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 840px) 100vw, 840px" /><figcaption><em>B&amp;B Highway participants looking for pollinators on a cold June day in Sydney</em></figcaption></figure>



<h3 id="get-involved">Get involved</h3>



<p>For anyone interested in finding out more about the B&amp;B Highway, and its educational resources, habitat constructions and the citizen science component <a href="https://www.ps.org.au/bb-highway-school-info">click here</a>. This article also provides an email link for further information on how to have your own school connected into the Highway. </p>



<p>For participating schools interested in contributing to the citizen science initiative, email <a href="mailto:info@ps.org.au">info@ps.org.au</a>. PlantingSeeds can add your school to the B&amp;B Highway on iNaturalist/Atlas of Living Australia so you can contribute vital pollinator data to a national biobank. PlantingSeeds can also provide a user-friendly guide on how to join the citizen science initiative and upload information.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA upgrade</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-upgrade/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 23:02:21 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44797</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Between Thursday 24 June and Tuesday 29 June, we will be deploying an upgrade to improve our systems and make them more robust and more efficient. As a result of this upgrade, there will be a planned outage on Tuesday 29 June from 8:00am to 2:00pm. Most of the work is happening behind the scenes, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Between Thursday 24 June and Tuesday 29 June, we will be deploying an upgrade to improve our systems and make them more robust and more efficient. As a result of this upgrade, there will be a planned outage on <strong>Tuesday 29 June from 8:00am to 2:00pm</strong>.</p>



<p>Most of the work is happening behind the scenes, so hopefully you won’t notice any significant changes to your everyday use of the ALA. If you do see anything out of the ordinary please let us know on <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="mailto:support@ala.org.au" target="_blank">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<p>For more information:</p>



<ul><li>Browse our support articles <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000249563-ala-infrastructure-changes-2021">ALA Infrastructure Changes 2021</a></li><li>Read our blog article <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-upgrade-on-its-way/">ALA upgrade on its way</a></li><li>Visit our <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/core-infrastructure-upgrade-project/">Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project</a> page</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The path of the emu: mapping 6,000 years of emu movement</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/the-path-of-the-emu-mapping-6000-years-of-emu-movement/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2021 01:30:59 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44776</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[By Julia Ryeland, Hawkesbury Institute for the Environment, Western Sydney University]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Emus are iconic. They join Kangaroos on the Australian coat of arms and are an essential part of any visit to the outback. They are also among the last of the Australia’s giant animals, or megafauna, giving us a window on Australia’s past giants. </p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-by-Julia-Ryeland-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44778" width="521" height="346" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-by-Julia-Ryeland-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-by-Julia-Ryeland-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-by-Julia-Ryeland.jpg 1090w" sizes="(max-width: 521px) 100vw, 521px" /><figcaption>In a recent study by Julia Ryeland from Western Sydney University explored how Emus (<em>Dromaius novaehollandia)</em> have adapted to environmental changes in Australia.<em> </em> (c) Julia Ryeland.</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>The emu is a member of a unique, ancient group of birds known as ‘ratites’ – flightless but widely distributed, spanning all southern hemisphere continents. This group includes species such as the ostrich, rhea, kiwi, cassowary and tinamou. The ratites are one of the most pre-historic groups of birds, in part because they are highly adaptable.</p>



<p>Emus have persisted in Australia through thousands of years; but anecdotal evidence suggests they are less common than they used to be. Increasing urbanisation and the removal of emus from farming lands means this species isn’t as widespread as it once was.</p>



<p>With populations condensing we begin to ask where will be the safe haven for emus in the future? It turns out answering this simple question is harder than you’d think.</p>



<p>Every species has an area across which it can be found – a ‘geographic distribution’. Knowing exactly where this is helps us develop an understanding of the species, how it may adapt over time, and assist in decision making about conservation. For example, if a species only lives in a small area, it may be of larger concern compared to species that can be found all over the country, across a wide range of habitats and climates.</p>



<p>Australia’s climate has changed over many thousands of years, and the species that live here have moved with it. The country has been subject to long periods where it was wetter or drier, and where sea levels were lower or higher. This begged a series of questions &#8211; how have emus adapted to these changes, being one of the most pre-historic species? What effect have these changes had on where emus can live? How will this change with further human impact on the environment?</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-study-figure-4.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44779" width="495" height="368" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-study-figure-4.jpg 657w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/Emu-study-figure-4-300x223.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 495px) 100vw, 495px" /><figcaption>Predicted distribution change from ensemble models, across Australia and the Great Dividing Range region, past to present and present to future. The figures were generated in R (version 3.6.0, <a href="https://www.r-project.org/">https://www.r-project.org/</a>).</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>To answer these questions, we turned to a method called ‘species distribution modelling’ (SDM). SDMs take maps of where an animal has been seen and combines them with information about the environment at these locations, such as the climate (temperature and rainfall) and habitat (e.g. vegetation available and land uses). These combine to make a ‘prediction map’ of where a species can be found. The more sightings of a species there are, the more accurate these maps are likely to be.</p>



<p>Fortunately, Emus are one of the most easily identified species and people love taking pictures of them! In fact, citizen scientists routinely record between 5,000 and 30,000 emu sightings every year across Australia. These sightings are collected and stored in a single place –the Atlas of Living Australia (<a href="https://www.ala.org.au">https://www.ala.org.au</a>). Here, they can be freely viewed and downloaded by anyone.</p>



<p>With these data, we built a model that shows the climate and habitat that emus prefer today; where suitable climate was 6,000 years ago; and where it will be in 50 years’ time.</p>



<p>We found that in the past 6,000 years, emus have made vast shifts inland across central Australia. These shifts have been driven mostly by climate, with emus minimally influenced by environmental factors such as habitat type, distance from water, land use types or fire frequency. These changes have greatly expanded the emu’s range and are predicted to remain stable over the next 50 years.</p>



<p>At the same time, however, emus have progressively been lost from the east coast. Now on the edge of their climatically suitable range, east coast emus are likely to be more susceptible to other threats, such as poor reproductive success due to predation by feral animals on the eggs and chicks.</p>



<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/emu-camera-trap-image-1024x574.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-44780" width="444" height="250" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/emu-camera-trap-image-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/emu-camera-trap-image-300x168.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/emu-camera-trap-image-768x430.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/06/emu-camera-trap-image.jpg 1099w" sizes="(max-width: 444px) 100vw, 444px" /><figcaption>Camera trap image of emu feeding from an east coast population. Image credit: Julia Ryeland</figcaption></figure></div>



<p>Emu disappearance across the east coast is unlikely to make the species vulnerable to the threat of extinction, because of the stability of their overall expansive range. However, the local extinction of emu populations across the east coast could have ecosystem wide implications.</p>



<p>Emus can travel up to 100km a year and move the seeds of native plants huge distances with them as they go. Without emus, many plant species will find it harder to disperse to new habitats or share genetic material between isolated plant communities. Combined with other threats such as habitat loss and predation by introduced species, our east coast plant communities could soon be in trouble.</p>



<p>Just as poignant, though, is the importance of emus in Australian culture, both in European and Indigenous histories. The emu is a totem to many indigenous groups and is shown on the Australian coat of arms.</p>



<p>Across the east coast where urbanisation is progressing rapidly, encountering a species such as the emu gives many Australian’s an important connection to nature that can help inspire conservation efforts for our lesser known, declining fauna.</p>



<p>For more information, read the full journal article <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-020-79551-0">Past and future potential range changes in one of the last large vertebrates of the Australian continent, the emu <em>Dromaius novaehollandiae</em></a> </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter May 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-may-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 27 May 2021 00:10:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44765</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter May 2021: Next ALA webinar, ALA upgrade, data quality survey and more...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/ALA-Newsletter-May-2021_LR.pdf"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/ALA-newsletter-ay-2021-thumbnail.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44766" width="221" height="300" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/ALA-newsletter-ay-2021-thumbnail.png 490w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/ALA-newsletter-ay-2021-thumbnail-221x300.png 221w" sizes="(max-width: 221px) 100vw, 221px" /></a></figure>



<p>Atlas of Living Australia Newsletter May 2021</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Director&#8217;s message &#8211; May 2021</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/directors-message-may-2021/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 06:34:46 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44748</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[I’d like to welcome you to the May 2021 edition of our newsletter in which&#160;we profile a number of exciting developments&#160;in&#160;the ALA.&#160;&#160; First, it’s a&#160;pleasure&#160;to be releasing&#160;the&#160;ALA’s&#160;annual work&#160;plan&#160;for&#160;2021-22.&#160;Mid-last year we were excited to&#160;release&#160;&#160;ALA Strategy 2020-25&#160;and the&#160;work&#160;plan provides an&#160;annual&#160;view into ALA priorities as articulated primarily through projects.&#160;&#160; The work&#160;plan is an&#160;outcome&#160;of&#160;multiple&#160;stakeholder conversations, the insight of the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large is-resized"><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/Andre-Zerger-portrait-2019-1-300x300-2.png" alt="" class="wp-image-44152" width="154" height="154" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/Andre-Zerger-portrait-2019-1-300x300-2.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/Andre-Zerger-portrait-2019-1-300x300-2-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 154px) 100vw, 154px" /></figure></div>



<p>I’d like to welcome you to the May 2021 edition of our newsletter in which&nbsp;we profile a number of exciting developments&nbsp;in&nbsp;the ALA.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>First, it’s a&nbsp;pleasure&nbsp;to be releasing&nbsp;the&nbsp;ALA’s&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/05/ALA-Workplan-2021-22_Final.pdf" target="_blank">annual work&nbsp;plan&nbsp;for&nbsp;2021-22</a>.&nbsp;Mid-last year we were excited to&nbsp;release&nbsp;&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/07/ALA-Strategy-2020-25-Public-June-6-2020.pdf" target="_blank">ALA Strategy 2020-25</a>&nbsp;and the&nbsp;work&nbsp;plan provides an&nbsp;annual&nbsp;view into ALA priorities as articulated primarily through projects.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>The work&nbsp;plan is an&nbsp;outcome&nbsp;of&nbsp;multiple&nbsp;stakeholder conversations, the insight of the ALA leadership team and&nbsp;guidance&nbsp;from the ALA Advisory Board. It details a range of projects including&nbsp;major activities such as:&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>an extension&nbsp;to our&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-upgrade-on-its-way/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Core Infrastructure Upgrade&nbsp;Project</a>&nbsp;working&nbsp;with the Global Biodiversity Information Facility&nbsp;&#8211;&nbsp;a strategic shift to support more complex biodiversity data&nbsp;</li><li>our&nbsp;three&nbsp;Australian Research Data Commons&nbsp;partnership&nbsp;projects&nbsp;–&nbsp;<a href="https://ardc.edu.au/project/ecoassets/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EcoAssets</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/improving-access-to-sensitive-species-data/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sensitive Species Data Pathways</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://ardc.edu.au/project/ecocommons-australia/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">EcoCommons&nbsp;Australia</a>, and&nbsp;</li><li>more tactical activities such as an uplift&nbsp;of&nbsp;the ALA’s&nbsp;R software&nbsp;suite&nbsp;and enhancements to our Biodiversity Information Explorer.&nbsp;&nbsp;</li></ul>



<p>The ALA has historically focussed on harmonising Australia’s biodiversity data pertaining to native plants and animals, and providing related data products and services to our key users across research, government, industry and community. However, we are increasingly seeing the value of our infrastructure in supporting biosecurity-related applications.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>In this issue we highlight our partnership with the Department of Agriculture, Water and the Environment’s Chief Environmental Biosecurity Office, which has been able to leverage a decade of ALA data partnerships and robust infrastructure to support the development of a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-helps-to-stop-pests-in-their-tracks/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">novel biosecurity alert capability</a>.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>There’s a pressing need for an improved national approach for dealing with biosecurity data.&nbsp;I was reminded of this earlier this week with the Government’s release of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.environment.gov.au/biodiversity/threatened/publications/threatened-species-strategy-2021-2031" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Threatened Species Strategy</a>&nbsp;where again we see the importance of understanding the distribution of invasive species, and the importance of&nbsp; knowledge and tools in supporting our mitigation programs.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>There’s a world of citizen science apps, biosecurity-related research programs,&nbsp;and government programs capturing data pertaining to species of biosecurity concern. Harmonising these data&nbsp;into a national data infrastructure will become an increasingly strategically important part of ALA’s work program.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>It’s also been a tremendous few months with respect to team growth. We’ve welcomed two new data analysts to the ALA, working under Dr Martin Westgate, and in coming weeks we’ll welcome an R-developer to work alongside our partner EcoCommons program. </p>



<p>Our uplift in data analytics capability will provide improved ALA data support to external stakeholders, projects and partners. The new team members will complement our existing data management team responsible for liaising with our data partners to bring data into the ALA. They will provide customised data services to our partners and support the next partnership opportunity that arises.  </p>



<p>I hope you enjoy the May&nbsp;2021&nbsp;edition of our&nbsp;newsletter.&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA upgrade on its way</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-upgrade-on-its-way/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[ALA Communications]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 04:03:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=44736</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia (ALA) team has been busy working on our Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project to improve our systems and make them more robust and more efficient.  ]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div class="wp-block-image"><figure class="alignright size-large"><img loading="lazy" width="288" height="279" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2020/02/AcroRd32_2020-02-05_14-56-31.png" alt="ALA Infrastructure Upgrade Project icon" class="wp-image-43653"/></figure></div>



<p>The&nbsp;upgraded code base&nbsp;will replace the&nbsp;ALA’s&nbsp;species&nbsp;occurrence&nbsp;record&nbsp;ingestion&nbsp;systems&nbsp;and&nbsp;will be released soon&nbsp;(late&nbsp;June-July 2021).&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Most of the work is happening behind the scenes, so hopefully&nbsp;you&nbsp;won’t&nbsp;notice&nbsp;any significant changes to your everyday use of the ALA.&nbsp;If&nbsp;you&nbsp;do&nbsp;see&nbsp;anything out of the&nbsp;ordinary&nbsp;please let us know on&nbsp;<a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">support@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;</p>



<p>This is just&nbsp;the first&nbsp;stage of our&nbsp;three stage&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/core-infrastructure-upgrade-project/">Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>The&nbsp;</strong><strong>Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project</strong><strong>&nbsp;–&nbsp;</strong><strong>our</strong><strong>&nbsp;</strong><strong>focus</strong><strong>&nbsp;for 2020-22</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project is a major&nbsp;project&nbsp;on our ALA Work Plan&nbsp;2020-21 and&nbsp;will continue into the coming year.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The project&nbsp;team&nbsp;has rewritten&nbsp;various components of the ALA&nbsp;species&nbsp;occurrence record&nbsp;ingestion&nbsp;system&nbsp;and&nbsp;it&nbsp;now shares a common code base with&nbsp;the&nbsp;Global Biodiversity Information Facility&nbsp;–&nbsp;<a href="https://www.gbif.org/">GBIF</a>&nbsp;–&nbsp;plus&nbsp;some adjustments&nbsp;for the ALA’s specific requirements. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The new infrastructure will be&nbsp;fit-for-purpose, more maintainable and able to adapt to our future needs as Australia’s national biodiversity&nbsp;data infrastructure.&nbsp;These&nbsp;improvements will enable the ALA to manage increases in data volume and different types&nbsp;of data. ​ &nbsp;</p>



<p>The upgrade will also mean&nbsp;we&#8217;re&nbsp;better positioned to handle data load automation.&nbsp;Our data partners will be empowered to control the currency and quality of their data. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Why are we upgrading ALA’s core infrastructure?  </strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>After 10 years of active development, the ALA’s core data processing infrastructure is approaching ‘end of life’. The Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project will enable the ALA to adapt to changing data and user requirements heading into our next decade of operation. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Getting ready for more data and more complex data</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>We are already seeing large volumes of new generation occurrence records coming from automated observations such as camera trapping, bioacoustics, animal tracking, and genetics including eDNA.&nbsp;Our current infrastructure is at&nbsp;capacity&nbsp;accommodating our&nbsp;occurrence&nbsp;record volume of just under 100m records.&nbsp;We&nbsp;need to&nbsp;be able to&nbsp;handle much larger data volumes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>GBIF&nbsp;already&nbsp;manages 1.7 billion occurrence records and sees exponential year-on-year growth.&nbsp;By collaborating with GBIF, we&nbsp;greatly&nbsp;benefit&nbsp;from their experience with large data volumes.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The new infrastructure will also enable us to join GBIF in adopting newer data types and other TDWG (Biodiversity Information Standards) extensions. It will open up opportunities to collaborate on new initiatives with GBIF’s development team and the international biodiversity data community. </p>



<p><strong>Partnering with&nbsp;</strong><strong>GBIF</strong><strong>&nbsp;and the international Living Atlases</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Throughout the&nbsp;Core Infrastructure Upgrade&nbsp;Project,&nbsp;we’ve&nbsp;been&nbsp;working closely with GBIF&nbsp;and collaborating on&nbsp;a&nbsp;shared codebase. We’re&nbsp;also&nbsp;communicating&nbsp;with our user and stakeholder communities and the <a href="https://living-atlases.gbif.org/">international Living Atlases community. </a>&nbsp;</p>



<p>The Living Atlases is an international&nbsp;community of 26 biodiversity data infrastructures originally built on the&nbsp;ALA code base.&nbsp;It&nbsp;is a vibrant development community,&nbsp;sharing and&nbsp;contributing to a common code base. Most of the&nbsp;Living Atlas instances&nbsp;are nodes of GBIF&nbsp;and as such&nbsp;are stakeholders in the future of the infrastructure&nbsp;upgrade&nbsp;work. Throughout the project, the GBIF and ALA development teams have&nbsp;been&nbsp;keeping&nbsp;the&nbsp;Living Atlases community&nbsp;up-to-date and&nbsp;abreast&nbsp;of the changes.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>For m</strong><strong>ore information</strong>&nbsp;</p>



<ul><li>Email us at&nbsp;<a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">support@ala.org.au</a>&nbsp;</li><li>Check out&nbsp;our&nbsp;<a href="https://www.ala.org.au/current-projects/core-infrastructure-upgrade-project/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Core Infrastructure Upgrade Project page</a>&nbsp;</li></ul>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
