<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.ala.org.au/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<description>Open access to Australia’s biodiversity data</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 02:38:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2019/01/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>Atlas of Living Australia</title>
	<link>https://www.ala.org.au</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>ALA user experience (UX) project: Call for expressions of interest</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-user-experience-ux-project-call-for-expressions-of-interest/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 02:27:50 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47953</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Want to help us improve the ALA? We’re reviewing our website and need your feedback! ALA is looking for volunteers to help us improve the usability, look and feel of our website. If you’re interested in shaping the future of the ALA, we’d love to hear from you! The ALA has undertaken several user satisfaction [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 style="font-size:25px" style="font-size:25px" id="want-to-help-us-improve-the-ala-were-reviewing-our-website-and-need-your-feedback"><strong>Want to help us improve the ALA? We’re reviewing our website and need your feedback!</strong></h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>ALA is looking for volunteers to help us improve the usability, look and feel of our website. If you’re interested in shaping the future of the ALA, we’d love to hear from you!</p>



<p>The ALA has undertaken several user satisfaction surveys since launching in 2010. As a response to your feedback, we’ve implemented many of the comments and suggestions raised. We also have more exciting improvements in our pipeline. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Since web technologies and styles are constantly changing, we are looking to undertake a review of our website and we need your input.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="369" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1024x369.png" alt="Five screenshots of the ALA home page from left to right: 2011, 2013, 2017, 2019, 2023. Dotted line and year labels are also shown left to right. Background is yellow with a tech/system motif of lines, circles and arrows" class="wp-image-47955" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1024x369.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-300x108.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-768x276.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1536x553.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-2048x737.png 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ala-then-and-now-1920x691.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption"><em>ALA homepage over the years</em></figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p>We are looking for volunteers to help us by undertaking a series of tasks. These would include a face-to-face interview (via video conference), reviewing mockups, and testing prototypes. Essentially, we’d like to hear your feedback on the site as it currently is and continue hearing your input as we develop new designs.</p>



<p>We appreciate your time and feedback, and your input will help shape the ALA.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="who-can-participate"><strong>Who can participate?</strong></h2>



<ul>
<li>Any ALA user over 18 may volunteer</li>



<li>You may be a new user or have been using the ALA for years</li>



<li>We are <em>mostly</em> looking for Australian-based users, but international users are welcome too</li>



<li><a>Whether you’re a researcher, government assessor, collections curator, citizen scientist, university student, community group member or otherwise use the ALA on a regular basis, you’re welcome to participate.</a></li>
</ul>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="whats-involved"><strong>What’s involved?</strong></h2>



<p>Participating in our user experience testing will involve a series of tasks including a face-to-face (online) interview, reviewing mockup designs and testing prototypes. All up, these activities would take just 3-4 hours of your time over the next 12 months, starting from late February 2023.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="when-do-registrations-close"><strong>When do registrations close?</strong></h2>



<p>If you are interested in participating, please let us know by Friday, 10 February 2023.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="how-do-i-register"><strong>How do I register?</strong></h2>



<p class="has-text-color has-medium-font-size" style="color:#f26649"><strong><a href="https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/HZG8XJW" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Register my interest</a></strong></p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="next-steps"><strong>Next steps</strong></h2>



<p>In late February we’ll select a representative user group, and email those users to organise the first activities.</p>



<div style="height:10px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 class="has-medium-font-size" class="has-medium-font-size" id="any-questions"><strong>Any questions?</strong></h2>



<p>Please email us at <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2023/01/ux-image-only-1024x586.png" alt="A group of four people sitting around a table, having a conversation. They have laptops and coffee mugs." class="wp-image-47956" width="1000" height="566"/></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Our ALA interns dive into data</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/our-ala-interns-dive-into-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 04:09:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47728</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Atlas of Living Australia was delighted to host three undergraduate students from the University of New South Wales (UNSW) as part of a 12-week internship program across spring – summer 2022. Our interns were spread across two streams: a Data Science Internship, which offered students the opportunity to apply their Python or R skills [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/#tab_pane-B">Atlas of Living Australia</a> was delighted to host three undergraduate students from the <a href="https://www.unsw.edu.au/">University of New South Wales</a> (UNSW) as part of a 12-week internship program across spring – summer 2022. Our interns were spread across two streams: a Data Science Internship, which offered students the opportunity to apply their Python or R skills to biodiversity problem solving, and a Data Visualisation for Communication Internship, which used ALA’s R package, <a href="https://galah.ala.org.au/">{galah}</a>, to create visualisations that are reproducible and scientifically transparent.</p>



<p>We chatted with our students, Steph, Elijah and Thai, to find out more about their ALA internship experience and what they’ve learned throughout the process.</p>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Steph-Wooley-2022-ALA-intern-300x290.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47730" width="370" height="361"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Steph Woolley &#8211; Data Visualisation intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong><u>Steph is studying a Bachelor of Advanced Science majoring in Marine &amp; Coastal Science.</u></strong></p>



<p>Q) What made you apply for the 2022 ALA Internship program?</p>



<p><em>A) Throughout my studies, I had always seen these amazing ways of displaying data and communicating science. When this internship appeared through an email by UNSW, I thought it was the perfect opportunity to develop my skills and to try to create one of the visualisations I had always seen in my courses.</em></p>



<p>Q) What did your ALA internship project focus on?</p>



<p><em>A) My internship was a data visualisation and analysis project. I spent my time analysing ALA data and developing a visualisation from the data that I had chosen to look at.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was a new skill you learned through the program that you’re proud of?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>I’m most proud of how my coding skills have developed over the internship. When I look back to the knowledge I had when I started this internship compared to what I have now, there’s a really big difference. I’m proud of how much I’ve learnt and the skills I’ve been able to build upon over the last 12 weeks.</em>&nbsp;</p>



<p>Q) What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>The biggest challenge for me across the 12 weeks has been time management and trusting the process. Throughout my university experience, I haven’t really had any experiences like this where we are working towards one main goal for such a long period of time. I think the process of making little steps each week towards the main goal has been a really big learning experience and it was definitely a challenge to get used to trying to achieve smaller tasks on a weekly basis rather than a larger main goal.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was your highlight from the internship program?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>The main highlight of the internship program was having the opportunity to develop my coding skills and being able and develop this skill with help and feedback from my supervisor. Having the opportunity to spend a long period of time working on a project that you have come up with, and that you find interesting, was also a big highlight.</em></p>



<p><em>The best individual moment though was definitely the day I finally got my visualisation and model to work and I could see the project coming together!</em></p>



<p>See what Steph created below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="800" height="600" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year-1.gif" alt="" class="wp-image-47737"/></figure>



<div class="wp-block-file"><a id="wp-block-file--media-d6436e48-4eff-46ff-b33b-1043425fef2d" href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year.gif">Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year</a><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Animation-of-nudibranch-species-distribution-model-across-the-year.gif" class="wp-block-file__button wp-element-button" download aria-describedby="wp-block-file--media-d6436e48-4eff-46ff-b33b-1043425fef2d">Download</a></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="633" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-1024x633.png" alt="" class="wp-image-47736" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-1024x633.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-300x185.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia-768x475.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Species-Distribution-Model-of-Nudibranch-occurences-across-all-of-Australia.png 1400w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Species Distribution Model of Nudibranch occurrences across Australia.</figcaption></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern-300x282.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47729" width="322" height="303" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern-300x282.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern-768x723.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Magistrado-2022-UNSW-intern.jpg 981w" sizes="(max-width: 322px) 100vw, 322px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Elijah Magistrado &#8211; Data Science intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong><u>Elijah is studying a Bachelor of Advanced Science majoring in Ecology</u></strong></p>



<p>Q) What made you apply for the 2022 ALA Internship program?</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em> I had wanted to do an internship position before I started my honours project in February and thought it was a great opportunity to gain real-world experience and further develop my skills in data science.</em></p>



<p>Q) What did your ALA internship project focus on?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p><em>A) My internship focused on standardising expert distribution maps. These are maps that represent where species can be found in Australia. These datasets are sent through to the ALA in different formats and layouts which need to be managed. My task was to convert all of the datasets into the format of existing expert distribution maps in the ALA and upload them so everyone can see the new maps.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was a new skill you learned through the program that you’re proud of?</p>



<p><em>A) I am proud to say that I can now program in Python! I have attempted to learn Python prior to the internship but having a project to work on makes motivation much easier. I am very pleased to have learned this skill as it helps broaden my study and career choices in the future.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?</p>



<p><em>A) Learning how to manage my time properly was definitely my biggest challenge. I hadn’t realised how exhausting it was to balance study, work, and learning Python. However, creating a structured routine has helped significantly with managing my time. It was great to have this opportunity to further develop time-management skills ahead of my honours project.&nbsp;&nbsp;</em></p>



<p>Q) What was your highlight of the internship program?</p>



<p><em>A) The highlight of my internship program was seeing the maps load properly on the test server. Initially, I had many issues that had caused the maps I uploaded to not show up. Once I had figured out what I had done wrong, fixed the issues, and tried uploading again, I felt very relieved to see that the maps were loading properly. After the issues were ironed out, the rest of the datasets were straight-forward.</em></p>



<p>See what Elijah created below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1015" height="980" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map.png" alt="" class="wp-image-47738" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map.png 1015w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map-300x290.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Elijah-Lorikeet-Map-768x742.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1015px) 100vw, 1015px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Occurrence records of Rainbow Lorikeets <em>(Trichoglossus moluccanus</em>) from 2020 onwards against its expert distribution map provided by BirdLife Australia.</figcaption></figure>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft size-medium is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Thai-2022-intern-ALA-300x300.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47731" width="383" height="385"/><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Thai Rushbrook &#8211;  Data Visualisation intern</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong><u>Thai is studying a Bachelor of Fine Arts and Science majoring in Photography &amp; Ecology.</u></strong></p>



<p>Q) What made you apply for the 2022 ALA Internship program?</p>



<p>A)<em>&nbsp;My university posted a list of internship positions available, and the ALA was on there! I’d heard of the ALA before and thought the data analysis/visualization combination suited my interests really well.</em></p>



<p>Q) What did your ALA internship project focus on?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A<em>) My project focused on the number of ducks recorded in greater Melbourne in the COVID-19 lockdown periods of 2020-2021. I was comparing them to ‘normal’ years, 2017-2019, to see if there was any difference.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was a new skill you learned through the program that you’re proud of?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A)&nbsp;<em>I started the term with very basic R-Studio skills, so I learnt a lot about R by organising data, transforming it, and creating the actual visualisations. I think I learnt more R-Studio tricks in this one term than the rest of my degree to date!</em></p>



<p>Q) What was the biggest challenge you encountered during the program?&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A)<em> Initially I was so nervous I didn’t have the skills needed to make a great project, so it took me a while to get started. Once I gained a little confidence, I was able to get creative and I’m very happy with the results.</em></p>



<p>Q) What was your highlight of the internship program?&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>A<em>) Coming together with the other interns at the end of the term to see what they had been working on was amazing. I loved seeing the different paths we took given a similar brief.</em></p>



<p>See what Thai created below:</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="936" height="542" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47739" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow.jpg 936w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow-300x174.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/Visualisation-of-the-number-of-duck-records-submitted-to-the-ALA-2020-21-compared-to-2017-19-with-Covid-19-periods-highlighted-in-yellow-768x445.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 936px) 100vw, 936px" /><figcaption class="wp-element-caption">Visualisation of the number of duck records submitted to the ALA &#8211; 2020-21 compared to 2017-19 &#8211; with COVID-19 periods highlighted in yellow.</figcaption></figure>



<p>If you would like to know more about ALA internship opportunities, contact us <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/" data-type="URL">he</a><a href="communications@ala.org.au">r</a><a href="https://www.ala.org.au/contact-us/">e</a>. </p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA webinar: Advances in Biodiversity Modelling</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-webinar-advances-in-biodiversity-modelling/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 01 Dec 2022 00:44:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47644</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Advancements in scientific modelling have enabled improvements in key decision-making. When it comes to biodiversity this work is crucial, especially in our changing environment. Hear from our distinguished speakers about their work in this space, including the applications of modelling to conservation prioritisation, and sustainable land use.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA webinar: Advances in Biodiversity Modelling – 23 Nov 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/-vuDDO-Dt-k?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<p>This webinar took place at 1.00pm AEDT, Wednesday 23 November 2022, with 201 live viewers in attendance.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="speakers">Speakers</h2>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/s.ferrier-speaker.png" alt="Simon Ferrier" class="wp-image-47647"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="miles-nicholls-atlas-of-living-australia">Simon Ferrier | CSIRO Land &amp; Water</h3>



<p>Simon Ferrier is a Chief Research Scientist with CSIRO Land and Water, an Honorary Professor at the Australian National University, and an Honorary Fellow at the United Nations Environment Programme World Conservation Monitoring Centre (UNEP-WCMC). Simon and his CSIRO colleagues have been developing a new generation of macroecological approaches to biodiversity modelling and scenario analysis, focused on assessing past-to-present change in the status of biodiversity, projecting impacts of future scenarios of climate and land-use change. Prior to this, Simon spent over 20 years working with state-government agencies, including pioneering the development of species- and community-level biodiversity modelling.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/c.archibald-speaker.png" alt="Carla Archibald" class="wp-image-47651"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="arve-solland-ecocommons">Carla Archibald | Centre for Integrative Ecology, Deakin University</h3>



<p>Dr Carla Archibald is a Research Fellow at Deakin University under the Land Use Future project. This Land Use Future project is led by Prof. Brett Bryan and Climateworks in collaboration with CSIRO. This project aims to further develop the LUTO model and to provide pathways towards sustainable environmental and food futures for the Australian agricultural landscape. In this Advances in Biodiversity Modelling talk, Carla will share some of the biodiversity modelling which she conducted as a part of the Land Use Future project. This involved working with the CliMAS team at JCU to update MaxEnt models with CMIP6 climate data and scenarios. The outcome of this modelling has resulted in the construction of specific-level data to use with the LUTO2.0 as both input data, as well as in the environmental accounts.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/12/p.bal_.png" alt="Payal Bal" class="wp-image-47653"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="ana-belgun-data61">Payal Bal | University of Melbourne</h3>



<p>Payal Bal is currently based at the Quantitative and Applied Ecology Group at The University of Melbourne, where she works on developing models to assess the global impacts of socioeconomic trends on biodiversity and on assessing the national-level impacts of bushfires on Australian invertebrate species. During her doctoral research at The University of Queensland, she applied decision analysis and structured decision-making approaches to evaluate monitoring strategies for conservation. She has previously worked on modelling spatial vegetation patterns to develop indicators of ecosystem collapse; on developing methods of abundance estimation for biodiversity from distance sampling; and on studying the human–elephant conflict in India.</p>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>


<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignright size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="135" height="180" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2021/11/Webinar-moderator-Martin.png" alt="Martin Westgate" class="wp-image-45781"/></figure></div>


<h3 id="moderator-bio">Moderator bio</h3>



<p>Martin Westgate leads the Science and Decision Support team at the Atlas of Living Australia. His research focuses on how scientific information can be used to understand and mitigate human impacts on the environment, via a combination of empirical ecology and evidence synthesis. Martin is also a scientific software developer and occasional frog-watcher.</p>



<div style="height:27px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="want-more">Want more?</h2>



<p>All ALA webinars are available to view on&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7PfG5Y80SwAP3dtW8Zkc-g/featured">our YouTube channel</a>&nbsp;along with other video content.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ALA Newsletter November 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/ala-newsletter-november-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2022 05:00:38 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Newsletter]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47624</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[ALA Newsletter November 2022]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fv24jl/202ad5d9fa1b5d465f11542bf8d2f1f1"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/11/newsletter-nov22-807x1024.png" alt="" class="wp-image-47627" width="438" height="554"/></a></figure>



<p>    <a href="https://t.e2ma.net/webview/fv24jl/202ad5d9fa1b5d465f11542bf8d2f1f1">ALA Newsletter November 2022</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Welcome to the November 2022 edition of our newsletter</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/welcome-to-the-november-2022-edition-of-our-newsletter/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2022 03:44:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47517</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Welcome to our November newsletter]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-thumbnail is-style-rounded"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="150" height="150" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/A57I6674-150x150.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47518"/><figcaption>Dr. Andre Zerger &#8211; Atlas of Living Australia Director</figcaption></figure>



<p>In this issue, we are pleased to present you with our Year in Review for 2021-22. Our Year in Review showcases ALA’s highlights, and reflects on the fundamental contribution made by our partners in supporting our mission. 2021-22 was an important year for the ALA, highlighted by some innovative new capability releases including <a href="https://labs.ala.org.au/">ALA Labs</a>, our work with partner NCRIS facilities to establish and launch <a href="https://ecoassets.org.au/">EcoAssets</a>, and the inaugural launch of the <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/abdmp/">ALA Australian Biodiversity Data Mobilisation Program</a>. Last year was also a time of significant team growth for the ALA and we now have staff in six  capital cities working with our partners, our projects and supporting our applications and systems. Having a national team has been a welcome by-product of some of the constraints imposed upon us over the past few years. Finally, doing justice to the breadth of research we enable in any year is always a challenge, but we’ve showcased four stellar examples of how a national biodiversity data infrastructure enables Australian science. We hope you enjoy reading our 2021-22 story as much as we’ve enjoyed building it.</p>



<p>I was recently privileged to represent the Australian delegation at the Governing Board meeting of the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF) held for the first time in person in three years in Brussels, but also supporting a hybrid model. It was a great opportunity to connect with people we only ever see virtually. It&#8217;s nice to see the shared challenges, understand where our partners are heading strategically and benchmark ALA’s approach both technically and strategically. The global context is different to ours but nevertheless, we run a federated data infrastructure built on strong relationships across many sectors, so we learn so much at these events. An additional highlight for me was attending a one-day symposium hosted by GBIF and the European Biodiversa+ program called Data Beyond Borders that explored the role data infrastructure can play in supporting major national research and policy programs. This is clearly one of the next frontiers for capabilities such as ALA, and our partners in the NCRIS program.</p>



<p>The GBIF experience has affirmed the importance of ALA’s international role, and the opportunities this affords moving forward. Our delegation concluded the meeting with a successful nomination to host the 2023 Governing Board Meeting in Canberra – it’s been almost 20 years since Australia played this role and we are excited to welcome our international partners in 2023.</p>



<p>It&#8217;s been some years since we’ve all travelled and engaged in person, but our team have been re-energised by this year’s conference season. This has included our recent participation in eResearch Australasia in Brisbane, remote participation in the TDWG international meeting, GBIF in Europe, and in-person participation at the Ecological Society of Australia conference in Wollongong in November. I’d like to conclude by acknowledging the groups and individuals that do such an amazing job designing, coordinating, and running conferences to support our sector.&nbsp; We appreciate the work you do! We hope you enjoy our November edition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sneak peek of our new API portal</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/sneak-peek-of-our-new-api-portal/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2022 05:55:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47573</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[We’ve just released a new API gateway to access our APIs: docs.ala.org.au! Over 130 API endpoints have been migrated across to Swagger in a beta release, and we’re working on making more available very soon. ALA is passionate about empowering and supporting great research, so we’ve released APIs which were only used internally in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>We’ve just released a new API gateway to access our APIs: <a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/">docs.ala.org.au</a>! Over 130 API endpoints have been migrated across to Swagger in a beta release, and we’re working on making more available very soon.</p>



<p>ALA is passionate about empowering and supporting great research, so we’ve released APIs which were only used internally in the past. You can now use these in your work to access our open-source data more easily and feed into downstream analyses using your own system. We can’t wait for you to try them out and let us know what you think!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/API-portal.png" alt="software developer coding at a computer" class="wp-image-47544" width="597" height="499" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/API-portal.png 940w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/API-portal-300x251.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 597px) 100vw, 597px" /></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="faqs"><strong>FAQs</strong></h3>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="what-about-security"><strong>What about security?</strong></h4>



<p>The new portal will increase security for both ALA and you, our user. By moving to JSON Web Tokens (JWT), we’re able to open up access to previously unreleased APIs.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="jwt-tokens-but-isnt-ala-providing-access-to-open-data"><strong>JWT tokens? But isn’t ALA providing access to open data?</strong></h4>



<p>Yes, we still are! (And we’re still free to use too).</p>



<p>Most of our APIs&nbsp;<strong>do not</strong>&nbsp;require authentication and can be accessed freely as documented in the relevant Swagger specifications found at&nbsp;<a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/">docs.ala.org.au</a>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>For the protected APIs (such as sensitive or private data), you’ll need a&nbsp;JWT, which can be generated via a Client ID and Client Secret&nbsp;– let us know if you require this and we can assist.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="whats-happening-to-the-existing-api-portal"><strong>What’s happening to the existing API portal?</strong></h4>



<p>While we are in the process of migrating more APIs across, the <a href="https://api.ala.org.au/">existing ALA API portal</a> will still be fully available and everything will be backwards compatible.</p>



<div style="height:20px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="still-have-questions"><strong>Still have questions?</strong></h4>



<p>See our updated support article: <a href="https://support.ala.org.au/support/solutions/articles/6000261502-ala-for-developers-how-to-access-ala-apis">ALA for developers, how to access ALA APIs</a> for technical tips on working with the new portal.</p>



<p>Finally, we’d love to hear from you! If you come across any issues, need help, or have questions or feedback about the new portal, feel free to reach out to us on <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a>.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="the-tl-dr-summary"><strong>The TL; DR summary:</strong></h3>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="whats-changed"><strong>What’s changed?</strong></h4>



<ul><li>New ALA API portal with a new URL: <a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/">docs.ala.org.au</a></li><li>More API endpoints now available, and more coming soon</li><li>Increased security</li><li><a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">Contact us</a> for an authorisation key</li></ul>



<div style="height:5px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h4 id="what-hasnt-changed"><strong>What hasn’t changed?</strong></h4>



<ul><li>ALA and our APIs are still <em>open-source</em> and <em>free </em>to use</li><li>The <a href="https://api.ala.org.au/">existing API portal</a> will still be available while we complete the migration</li><li>We’re still here to help if you need assistance: <a href="mailto:support@ala.org.au">support@ala.org.au</a></li></ul>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><a href="https://docs.ala.org.au/"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen.png" alt="screenshot of the new ALA API docs portal" class="wp-image-47564" width="682" height="710" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen.png 820w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen-288x300.png 288w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/docs-portal-screen-768x800.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 682px) 100vw, 682px" /></a></figure>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Are you sitting on camera trap data?</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/are-you-sitting-on-camera-trap-data/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2022 23:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47426</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[WildObs would like to hear about your camera trap work!]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="202" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-1024x202.png" alt="green banner reading &quot;WildObs Australia&quot; with a picture of a dingo, a wallaby, a kangaroo and a cassowary. " class="wp-image-47427" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-1024x202.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-300x59.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-768x152.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs-1536x303.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/WildObs.png 1752w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>WildObs banner (TERN)</figcaption></figure>



<p></p>



<p>Our friends at <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.tern.org.au/wildobs/" target="_blank">WildObs</a> are conducting a review of camera trapping in Australia. This review will help establish a useful synthesis centre devoted to curating vertebrate data. The team are seeking metadata from camera trapping surveys to assist in the project and are offering co-authorship upon receipt of data.</p>



<p>The aim of the project is to generate a modern snapshot of<em> where</em>, <em>how </em>and <em>who</em> is carrying out surveys, including habitats, target species and methods (both deployment and analysis). The project and participant information sheets are below, with a deadline of <strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">15 November 2022</span></strong> for data submissions.<br><br>To participate, please see the below three actions:<br>&nbsp;1) <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://tinyurl.com/3bu89jta" target="_blank">Complete the questionnaire</a>, including the consent form on the first page.&nbsp;<br>&nbsp;2) <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://tinyurl.com/457cc6cm" target="_blank">Add basic metadata</a> from your camera trapping surveys<br>&nbsp;3) <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://tinyurl.com/32r5m6c6" target="_blank">Enter your name and affiliation</a> for co-authorship<br><br>For more information, contact Tom Bruce (<a href="mailto:tom.bruce@uq.edu.au">tom.bruce@uq.edu.au</a>) or Matthew Luskin (<a href="mailto:mluskin@uq.edu.au">mluskin@uq.edu.au</a>).<br></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><a href="http://www.tern.org.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="300" height="77" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/TERN-logo-1-300x77.png" alt="TERN logo with map of Australia" class="wp-image-47433" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/TERN-logo-1-300x77.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/TERN-logo-1.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Spooky Species</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/spooky-species/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[april.suen@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2022 22:05:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47475</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Does it croak or growl, have fangs or howl? Does it scream at night or give you a fright? 🎃 Many iconic living (or dead) things that are seen around Halloween are inspired by species in the natural world! Check out some of the most spook-tacular Aussie species! Goblin Shark (Mitsukurina owstoni) Talk about a [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>Does it croak or growl, have fangs or howl? Does it scream at night or give you a fright? <img src="https://s.w.org/images/core/emoji/14.0.0/72x72/1f383.png" alt="🎃" class="wp-smiley" style="height: 1em; max-height: 1em;" /></p>



<p>Many iconic living (or dead) things that are seen around Halloween are inspired by species in the natural world! Check out some of the most spook-tacular Aussie species!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1009" height="541" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47481" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC.jpg 1009w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC-300x161.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Goblin-Shark-Mitsukurina-owstoni-Museums-Victoria-CC-BY-NC-768x412.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1009px) 100vw, 1009px" /><figcaption>Goblin Shark (<em>Mitsukurina owstoni</em>) Museums Victoria CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/b1b5f1e3-1efa-4d18-b8f7-d26731b964cc#overview">Goblin Shark (<em>Mitsukurina owstoni</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>Talk about a creature from nightmares, the Goblin Shark is one of the most illusive deep-sea sharks known to scientists with a distinctive blade-like snout and pink skin. Specimens have been found along continental slopes at distances up to 1.3 km deep, measuring 3-4 metres in length. The Goblin Shark has distinctive mouthparts, specialised for rapid projection as their jaws can extend and retract to catch prey.</p>



<p>They are the only extant member of the&nbsp;<em>Mitsukurina</em>&nbsp;genus, often called a ‘living fossil’ as this genus traces back 125 million years. These sharks are incredibly illusive, with limited specimens recorded around NSW, Victoria and Tasmania in Australia, as well as Portugal and Japan. Not much is known about the reproductive life cycle of this species as a pregnant Goblin Shark has never been recorded.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47480" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-1920x1440.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Bronze-Orange-Bug-Musgraveia-sulciventris-eRoger-via-iNaturalist-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Bronze Orange Bug (<em>Musgraveia sulciventris</em>) Erin Roger CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><u><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/201952">Bronze Orange Bug</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/201952"><em>Musgraveia sulciventris</em></a>)</u></strong></p>



<p>If the pumpkin-orange colour doesn’t scare you off, maybe its stench will! This stinkbug produces a rotten-smelling spray from the chemical ‘cimicine.’ This spray doesn’t just pack a pungent punch, its main function is to be a defensive mechanism against predators – most commonly other arthropods and birds – which can be lethal to these species. To humans, the spray can cause significant irritation. This is a classic case of ‘look but don’t touch’, no matter your species!</p>



<p>As eggs and nymphs, Bronze Orange Bugs are green in colour but as they mature through their five instar stages of development, they acquire their distinctive orange colour to resemble citrus leaves. They are considered pests in commercial citrus orchards across eastern Australia.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47482" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1024x768.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1536x1152.jpeg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-1920x1440.jpeg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC-640x480.jpeg 640w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Jimsonweed-Datura-stramonium-Ecocentric_Consultulting-CC-BY-NC.jpeg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Jimsonweed (<em>Datura stramonium)</em> Ecocentric_Consultulting CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/55854">Jimsonweed</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/55854"><em>Datura stramonium</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>It’s not just it’s physical appearance that’s scary, this plant’s impact on biosecurity is equally terrifying.</p>



<p>Also known as the ‘cemetery flower’ or ‘common thorn apple’, this plant is one of the most invasive noxious weeds around the world, including in Australia. It has been known to poison humans and animals, reduce pasture productivity and compete with native flora.</p>



<p>A member of the nightshade family, Jimsonweed was originally introduced in Australia in the 1800s for medicinal and ornamental purposes. The most toxic part of the plant are its black seeds which disperse through water, contaminated hay and mud stuck to vehicles.&nbsp;The spiny seed capsule is as aggressive as it looks and will injure those who dare to touch…</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-1024x683.jpeg" alt="" class="wp-image-47478" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Spectacled-Flying-Fox-Pteropus-conspicillatus-via-iNaturalist-credit-kcomeau.jpeg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Spectacled Flying Fox (<em>Pteropus conspicillatus</em>) Kcomeau CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/27d443cb-290b-4d53-8010-5e230f840d67">Spectacled Flying Fox (<em>Pteropus conspicillatus</em></a><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https://biodiversity.org.au/afd/taxa/5ff29bca-f02f-468f-9f96-9ae956015e01">)</a></strong></p>



<p>Australia is home to more than 90 species of bats including both mega bats and micro bats. Although some bat species around the world do feed on blood (and are most likely the inspiration for Halloween stories), the Spectacled Flying Fox is more likely bring you joy rather than terror!</p>



<p>These endangered fruit bats live in the northern tropics and feed on native fruits, flowers, and myrtle plants. They play a pivotal role in rainforest ecosystems as seed dispersers and pollinators. Aptly named, the Spectacled Flying Fox has light yellow fur around its eyes and snout giving the appearance that its wearing glasses. They typically live to be around 12 -15 years old in the wild but have been known to live up to 30 years old in captivity.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-1024x682.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47479" width="1000" height="666" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC-1536x1023.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Far-Eastern-Curlew-Numenius-madagascariensis-Mark-Ayres-CC-BY-NC.jpg 1560w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" /><figcaption>Far Eastern Curlew (<em>Numenius madagascariensis</em>) Mark Ayres CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/3898">Far Eastern Curlew</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/3898"><em>Numenius madagascariensis</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>A shriek in the night, a blood curdling scream, you investigate the source only to find…a Far Eastern Curlew?</p>



<p>Known for making exceptionally long migratory travels to breed between northern and southern hemispheres, Far Eastern Curlews are also iconic for their scream-like vocalisation calls.&nbsp;They use their hauntingly beautiful calls as part of mating displays and to assert dominance over their territory.</p>



<p>With a long scimitar-shaped beak which can be more than 50% the length of their body and dark-streaked plumage, the Far Eastern Curlew is the largest shorebird in the world. This species is reliant on mudflats and mangrove swamps for feeding and breeding. Unfortunately, this species is listed as ‘endangered’ due to loss of habitat, causing population decline across their ranges.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="608" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1024x608.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47477" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1024x608.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-300x178.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-768x456.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1536x911.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC-1920x1139.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Speckled-Orbweaver-Araneus-circulissparsus-Jackie-Lien-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Speckled Orbweaver (<em>Araneus circulissparsus)</em> Jackie Lien CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/487451">Speckled Orbweaver</a>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/487451"><em>Araneus circulissparsus</em></a>)</strong></p>



<p>Hairy, spotty and slime green! Could this spider be the ultimate creature for Halloween?</p>



<p>Orbweaver spiders are common across Australia, known for making intricate, sticky webs at night to catch prey. Orbweavers occupy crevices and leaves during the day, and if they feel significantly threatened, they will drop to the ground and ‘play dead.’</p>



<p>The Speckled Orbweaver prefers to occupy green foliage, to blend in with the surroundings. As with many spider species, females are larger than males at approximately 6mm in length, with males 3mm in length.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="683" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-47526" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-300x200.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-768x512.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC-1920x1280.jpg 1920w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/Ghost-Fungus-Omphalotus-nidiformis-credit-Monica-knipler-CC-BY-NC.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Ghost Fungus (<em>Omphalotus nidiformis</em>) Monica Knipler CC BY NC</figcaption></figure>



<p><strong><u><a href="https://bie.ala.org.au/species/https:/id.biodiversity.org.au/node/fungi/60094367">Ghost Fungus <em>(Omphalotus nidiformis</em></a></u></strong>)</p>



<p>Like something out of a fairy-tale, Ghost Fungi glow through their gills with a green-tinged light. They emit ‘cold light’ where less than 20% of light emitted is capable of radiating heat. Ghost Fungi, and other bioluminescent creatures, fluoresce using a compound called ‘luciferin’. They grow on dead or decaying wood and are commonly found across Australia in temperate areas. The exact reason this species uses bioluminescence is not known, however a theory is that by glowing the fungi attracts insects which disperse its spores.</p>



<p>Ghost Fungi are poisonous if consumed, however are often mistaken for Oyster Mushrooms due to their similar fan-like appearance and milky-white colouration in the daytime.</p>



<p>To learn how to upload species records and contribute to the Atlas of Living Australia, check our this <a href="https://www.ala.org.au/home/record-a-sighting/">link</a>.</p>



<p></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Q4 Conferences – Where to find ALA</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/q4-conferences-where-to-find-ala/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Oct 2022 01:49:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47410</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Across October – December 2022 you’ll find ALA at a number of in-person and virtual events. These events offer a fantastic opportunity to network, share knowledge and connect. See below for where to find the ALA. eResearch Australasia Conference 2022 &#8211; Brisbane &#160;17-20 October 2022 ALA will have a booth at this event. Come by [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Across October – December 2022 you’ll find ALA at a number of in-person and virtual events. These events offer a fantastic opportunity to network, share knowledge and connect. </p>



<p>See below for where to find the ALA.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="577" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ALA-Q4-Upcoming-Conferences-3-1024x577.png" alt="&quot;&quot;" class="wp-image-47414" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ALA-Q4-Upcoming-Conferences-3-1024x577.png 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ALA-Q4-Upcoming-Conferences-3-300x169.png 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ALA-Q4-Upcoming-Conferences-3-768x433.png 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ALA-Q4-Upcoming-Conferences-3-1536x865.png 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ALA-Q4-Upcoming-Conferences-3.png 1640w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>Events across October to December 2022 where ALA will be present</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="eresearch-australasia-conference-2022-brisbane-17-20-october-2022"><strong>eResearch Australasia Conference 2022 &#8211; Brisbane &nbsp;17-20 October 2022</strong></h2>



<p>ALA will have a booth at this event. Come by and say hello!</p>



<p><em>Tuesday 18<sup>th</sup> October </em></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Amanda Buyan</strong> &#8211; <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://conference.eresearch.edu.au/2022/08/ecocommons-providing-reputable-high-quality-data-to-protect-a-high-quality-planet/" target="_blank">EcoCommons: providing reputable, high-quality data to protect a high-quality planet</a></p>



<p><em>Wednesday 19<sup>th</sup> October </em></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Kathryn Hall </strong>&#8211; <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://conference.eresearch.edu.au/2022/08/a-fairer-future-for-genomics-research-in-australia-creating-an-australian-genome-reference-atlas/" target="_blank">A FAIRer future for genomics research in Australia: creating an Australian Genome Reference Atlas</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="292" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-1024x292.jpg" alt="Blue background that reads eResearch Australasia 2022 Conference" class="wp-image-47401" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-1024x292.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-300x86.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-768x219.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-1536x439.jpg 1536w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-2048x585.jpg 2048w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/eResearch-2022-1920x548.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" /><figcaption>eResearch Australasia 2022 Conference banner</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="biodiversity-information-standards-taxonomic-databases-working-group-tdwg-2022-sofia-bulgaria-online-17-21-october-2022"><strong>Biodiversity Information Standards Taxonomic Databases Working Group (TDWG) 2022 &#8211; Sofia, Bulgaria &amp; online</strong> <strong>17 &#8211; 21 October 2022</strong></h2>



<p><em>Monday 17<sup>th </sup>October</em></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Nicole Kearney </strong>&#8211; Supplying the Missing Links: Providing immediate access to the taxonomic literature from our taxonomic databases. By Nicole Kearney and Roderic Page <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91104">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91104</a></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Mahmoud Sadeghi </strong>&#8211; A Pre-ingestion Framework for Darwin Core Archives. By Mahmoud Sadeghi, Patricia Koh, Peggy Newman <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.93853">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.93853</a></p>



<p><em>Tuesday 18<sup>th </sup>October</em></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Lee Belbin</strong> &#8211; It Takes Years for a Good Wine to Mature: Task Group 2 &#8211; data quality tests and assertions. By Lee Belbin, Arthur Chapman, Paul J. Morris, John Richard Wieczorek <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91078">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91078</a></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Arthur Chapman</strong> &#8211; Formulaic Unpublished Names: The need for a TDWG standard and for the inclusion of such names in apps such as iNaturalist. By Arthur D Chapman, Thomas Mesaglio, Guy Taseski <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91062">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91062</a></p>



<p><em>Thursday 20<sup>th </sup>October</em></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Javier Molina</strong> &#8211; A Practical Approach to Publishing and Using Event-based Biodiversity Data. By Javier Molina, Federico Mendez, Dax Kelly, David Martin, Doug Palmer <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91512">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91512</a></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Peggy Newman</strong> &#8211; Growth and Collaboration in the Atlas of Living Australia. By Peggy Newman, Hamish Holewa, Elycia Wallis <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.93854">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.93854</a></p>



<p><em>Friday 21<sup>st </sup>October</em></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Kathryn Hall</strong> &#8211; Building an Australian Reference Genome Atlas. By Nicholas J dos Remedios, Sarah Richmond, Jeff Christiansen, Nigel Ward, Hamish Holewa, Kathryn A Hall <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91415">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.91415</a></p>



<p><strong>Presenter: Doug Palmer</strong> &#8211; The Large Taxon Collider: Building the Atlas of Living Australia&#8217;s taxonomic backbone. By Doug Palmer, Peggy Newman <a href="https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.95102">https://doi.org/10.3897/biss.6.95102</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-full is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/tdwg-2022-cover-e1652452236700.jpg" alt="Black banner with a picture of a building on the left side that reads Biodiversity Information Standards TDWG 2022 Bulgaria" class="wp-image-47404" width="1001" height="564" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/tdwg-2022-cover-e1652452236700.jpg 900w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/tdwg-2022-cover-e1652452236700-300x169.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/tdwg-2022-cover-e1652452236700-768x432.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1001px) 100vw, 1001px" /><figcaption>Biodiversity Information Standards TDWG 2022  banner</figcaption></figure>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="ecological-society-of-australia-esa-society-for-conservation-biology-oceania-scbo-joint-conference-wollongong-28-november-2-december"><strong>Ecological Society of Australia (ESA) &amp; Society for Conservation Biology Oceania (SCBO) Joint Conference &nbsp;– Wollongong 28 November &#8211; 2 December</strong></h2>



<p>ALA will have a booth at this event. Come by and say hello! </p>



<p><em>Friday 2<sup>nd</sup> December</em> </p>



<p>Full agenda <a href="https://kaigi.eventsair.com/QuickEventWebsitePortal/esa-scb-2022/esascboinfo/Agenda" data-type="URL" data-id="https://kaigi.eventsair.com/QuickEventWebsitePortal/esa-scb-2022/esascboinfo/Agenda">here</a>.</p>



<p>Workshop: A Beginner’s Guide to Data Analysis and Visualisation in Python for Ecologists &amp; Conservation Scientists using EcoCommons’ Coding Cloud<br>Facilitated by:&nbsp;<strong>Dr Amanda Buyan, Data Analyst, CSIRO The Atlas of Living Australia &amp; EcoCommons Australia, Dr Rob Clemens, Change &amp; Communications Manager, EcoCommons Australia, Griffith University, Dr Emilia Decker, Support and Training Officer, EcoCommons Australia, Griffith University &amp; Dr Jessica Fenker, R</strong> <strong>Programmer, EcoCommons Australia, CSIRO The Atlas of Living Australia</strong></p>



<p>Workshop: Using the EcoCommons’ Point-and-click Dashboards to run Species Distribution Models, make Climate Projections and carry out Biosecurity Risk Mapping<br>Facilitated by:&nbsp;<strong>Dr Rob Clemens, Change &amp; Communications Manager, EcoCommons Australia, Griffith University, Dr Emilia Decker, Support and Training Officer, EcoCommons Australia, Griffith University, Dr Jessica Fenker, R Programmer, EcoCommons Australia, The Atlas of Living Australia, Dr Peter D. Wilson, Adjunct Fellow, Macquarie University &amp; Dr Sean Haythorne, Research Software Engineer, Centre of Excellence for Biosecurity Risk Analysis, University of Melbourne</strong></p>



<p>Workshop: Running Species Distribution Models in the EcoCommons’ R environment<br>Facilitated by:&nbsp;<strong>Dr Rob Clemens, Change &amp; Communications Manager, EcoCommons Australia, Griffith University, Abhimanyu Raj Singh, Functional Analyst, EcoCommons Australia, Griffith University &amp; Dr Jessica Fenker, R Programmer, EcoCommons Australia, The Atlas of Living Australia</strong></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large is-resized"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ESA-SCBO-1024x134.jpg" alt="White banner with threee stripes on right hand side that reads ESA - SCBO 2022 28 November - 2 December 2022 Wollongong NSW" class="wp-image-47403" width="998" height="130" srcset="https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ESA-SCBO-1024x134.jpg 1024w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ESA-SCBO-300x39.jpg 300w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ESA-SCBO-768x101.jpg 768w, https://www.ala.org.au/app/uploads/2022/10/ESA-SCBO.jpg 1512w" sizes="(max-width: 998px) 100vw, 998px" /><figcaption>ESA &#8211; SCBO 2022 banner</figcaption></figure>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>National Science Week 2022</title>
		<link>https://www.ala.org.au/blogs-news/national-science-week-2022/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[kylie.morrow@csiro.au]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 23:11:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Webinars]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[ALA Blog]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.ala.org.au/?p=47166</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In August 2022 the ALA celebrated National Science Week! It was exciting to share, discuss and celebrate science with you over a series of three online events throughout the week. Hear from ALA and Industry experts discussing careers in STEM, learn how to use the ALA R-package galah and follow along for an introductory how-to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p></p>



<p>In August 2022 the ALA celebrated <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.scienceweek.net.au/" target="_blank">National Science Week</a>! It was exciting to share, discuss and celebrate science with you over a series of three online events throughout the week.</p>



<p>Hear from ALA and Industry experts discussing careers in STEM, learn how to use the ALA R-package <em>galah</em> and follow along for an introductory how-to beginner’s guide to the ALA.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h2 id="ala-events">ALA events</h2>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="stem-career-stories">ALA Webinar: STEM Career Stories</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA webinar: STEM Career Stories – 16 Aug, 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/5EnctbSAUHo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Tuesday 16 August, 2022</strong></p>



<p>As Australia’s national biodiversity database, the Atlas of Living Australia delivers trusted data services for Australia, supporting world-class biodiversity research and decision-making. Our data are used by a range of professionals from different fields, such as research, government, museums &amp; herbaria, and industry, just to name a few. As diverse as these fields are, they all share something in common, and that’s the potential for an exciting career in STEM. In this webinar, hear from three speakers who have followed their passions to forge unique and rewarding career paths in STEM.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="intro-to-galah">ALA How-to Session: Intro to {galah}</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA How to session: Intro to {galah} – 17 Aug, 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VsyMh9RCY1c?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Wednesday 17 August, 2022</strong></p>



<p>At the ALA, we store biodiversity data in a way that is open and accessible, but the ALA website is not the only way to access them!</p>



<p>Our R package {galah} gives you the tools to query the ALA directly and work with data in your preferred way. Join us for a step-by-step guide to getting started in {galah}.</p>



<p>Please note: some basic familiarity with RStudio is recommended.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<h3 id="beginners-guide-to-ALA">ALA How-to Session: Beginner&#8217;s guide to using the ALA</h3>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe loading="lazy" title="ALA How-to session: Beginner&#039;s guide to using the ALA – 18 Aug, 2022" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dwtKaqlJOss?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div></figure>



<div style="height:15px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<p><strong>Thursday 18 August 2022</strong></p>



<p>The Atlas of Living Australia aggregates biodiversity data and stores them in a way that is open and accessible. But what does this actually mean, and what can you use the ALA for? Find out in this interactive workshop!</p>



<p>Follow along as we share tips and tricks for getting the most out of the ALA. We’ll cover how to look up information about your favourite species, how to find out which species have been recorded in your local area, plus much more! Beginner friendly.</p>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>



<div style="height:30px" aria-hidden="true" class="wp-block-spacer"></div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
